Why Do People Use Python?

Because there are many programming languages available today, this is the usual first question of newcomers. Given that there are roughly 1 million Python users out there at the moment, there really is no way to answer this question with complete accuracy; the choice of development tools is sometimes based on unique constraints or personal preference.

But after teaching Python to roughly 225 groups and over 3,000 students during the last 12 years, some common themes have emerged. The primary factors cited by Python users seem to be these:

Software quality

For many, Python’s focus on readability, coherence, and software quality in general sets it apart from other tools in the scripting world. Python code is designed to be readable, and hence reusable and maintainable—much more so than traditional scripting languages. The uniformity of Python code makes it easy to understand, even if you did not write it. In addition, Python has deep support for more advanced software reuse mechanisms, such as object-oriented programming (OOP).

Developer productivity

Python boosts developer productivity many times beyond compiled or statically typed languages such as C, C++, and Java. Python code is typically one-third to one-fifth the size of equivalent C++ or Java code. That means there is less to type, less to debug, and less to maintain after the fact. Python programs also run immediately, without the lengthy compile and link steps required by some other tools, further boosting programmer speed.

Program portability

Most Python programs run unchanged on all major computer platforms. Porting Python code between Linux and Windows, for example, is usually just a matter of copying a script’s code between machines. Moreover, Python offers multiple options for coding portable graphical user interfaces, database access programs, web-based systems, and more. Even operating system interfaces, including program launches and directory processing, are as portable in Python as they can possibly be.

Support libraries

Python comes with a large collection of prebuilt and portable functionality, known as the standard library. This library supports an array of application-level programming tasks, from text pattern matching to network scripting. In addition, Python can be extended with both homegrown libraries and a vast collection of third-party application support software. Python’s third-party domain offers tools for website construction, numeric programming, serial port access, game development, and much more. The NumPy extension, for instance, has been described as a free and more powerful equivalent to the Matlab numeric programming system.

Component integration

Python scripts can easily communicate with other parts of an application, using a variety of integration mechanisms. Such integrations allow Python to be used as a product customization and extension tool. Today, Python code can invoke C and C++ libraries, can be called from C and C++ programs, can integrate with Java and .NET components, can communicate over frameworks such as COM, can interface with devices over serial ports, and can interact over networks with interfaces like SOAP, XML-RPC, and CORBA. It is not a standalone tool.

Enjoyment

Because of Python’s ease of use and built-in toolset, it can make the act of programming more pleasure than chore. Although this may be an intangible benefit, its effect on productivity is an important asset.

Of these factors, the first two (quality and productivity) are probably the most compelling benefits to most Python users.

Software Quality

By design, Python implements a deliberately simple and readable syntax and a highly coherent programming model. As a slogan at a recent Python conference attests, the net result is that Python seems to “fit your brain”—that is, features of the language interact in consistent and limited ways and follow naturally from a small set of core concepts. This makes the language easier to learn, understand, and remember. In practice, Python programmers do not need to constantly refer to manuals when reading or writing code; it’s a consistently designed system that many find yields surprisingly regular-looking code.

By philosophy, Python adopts a somewhat minimalist approach. This means that although there are usually multiple ways to accomplish a coding task, there is usually just one obvious way, a few less obvious alternatives, and a small set of coherent interactions everywhere in the language. Moreover, Python doesn’t make arbitrary decisions for you; when interactions are ambiguous, explicit intervention is preferred over “magic.” In the Python way of thinking, explicit is better than implicit, and simple is better than complex.[2]

Beyond such design themes, Python includes tools such as modules and OOP that naturally promote code reusability. And because Python is focused on quality, so too, naturally, are Python programmers.

Developer Productivity

During the great Internet boom of the mid-to-late 1990s, it was difficult to find enough programmers to implement software projects; developers were asked to implement systems as fast as the Internet evolved. Today, in an era of layoffs and economic recession, the picture has shifted. Programming staffs are often now asked to accomplish the same tasks with even fewer people.

In both of these scenarios, Python has shined as a tool that allows programmers to get more done with less effort. It is deliberately optimized for speed of development—its simple syntax, dynamic typing, lack of compile steps, and built-in toolset allow programmers to develop programs in a fraction of the time needed when using some other tools. The net effect is that Python typically boosts developer productivity many times beyond the levels supported by traditional languages. That’s good news in both boom and bust times, and everywhere the software industry goes in between.

Is Python a “Scripting Language”?

Python is a general-purpose programming language that is often applied in scripting roles. It is commonly defined as an object-oriented scripting language—a definition that blends support for OOP with an overall orientation toward scripting roles. In fact, people often use the word “script” instead of “program” to describe a Python code file. In this book, the terms “script” and “program” are used interchangeably, with a slight preference for “script” to describe a simpler top-level file and “program” to refer to a more sophisticated multifile application.

Because the term “scripting language” has so many different meanings to different observers, some would prefer that it not be applied to Python at all. In fact, people tend to make three very different associations, some of which are more useful than others, when they hear Python labeled as such:

Shell tools

Sometimes when people hear Python described as a scripting language, they think it means that Python is a tool for coding operating-system-oriented scripts. Such programs are often launched from console command lines and perform tasks such as processing text files and launching other programs.

Python programs can and do serve such roles, but this is just one of dozens of common Python application domains. It is not just a better shell-script language.

Control language

To others, scripting refers to a “glue” layer used to control and direct (i.e., script) other application components. Python programs are indeed often deployed in the context of larger applications. For instance, to test hardware devices, Python programs may call out to components that give low-level access to a device. Similarly, programs may run bits of Python code at strategic points to support end-user product customization without the need to ship and recompile the entire system’s source code.

Python’s simplicity makes it a naturally flexible control tool. Technically, though, this is also just a common Python role; many (perhaps most) Python programmers code standalone scripts without ever using or knowing about any integrated components. It is not just a control language.

Ease of use

Probably the best way to think of the term “scripting language” is that it refers to a simple language used for quickly coding tasks. This is especially true when the term is applied to Python, which allows much faster program development than compiled languages like C++. Its rapid development cycle fosters an exploratory, incremental mode of programming that has to be experienced to be appreciated.

Don’t be fooled, though—Python is not just for simple tasks. Rather, it makes tasks simple by its ease of use and flexibility. Python has a simple feature set, but it allows programs to scale up in sophistication as needed. Because of that, it is commonly used for quick tactical tasks and longer-term strategic development.

So, is Python a scripting language or not? It depends on whom you ask. In general, the term “scripting” is probably best used to describe the rapid and flexible mode of development that Python supports, rather than a particular application domain.

OK, but What’s the Downside?

After using it for 17 years and teaching it for 12, the only downside to Python I’ve found is that, as currently implemented, its execution speed may not always be as fast as that of compiled languages such as C and C++.

We’ll talk about implementation concepts in detail later in this book. In short, the standard implementations of Python today compile (i.e., translate) source code statements to an intermediate format known as byte code and then interpret the byte code. Byte code provides portability, as it is a platform-independent format. However, because Python is not compiled all the way down to binary machine code (e.g., instructions for an Intel chip), some programs will run more slowly in Python than in a fully compiled language like C.

Whether you will ever care about the execution speed difference depends on what kinds of programs you write. Python has been optimized numerous times, and Python code runs fast enough by itself in most application domains. Furthermore, whenever you do something “real” in a Python script, like processing a file or constructing a graphical user interface (GUI), your program will actually run at C speed, since such tasks are immediately dispatched to compiled C code inside the Python interpreter. More fundamentally, Python’s speed-of-development gain is often far more important than any speed-of-execution loss, especially given modern computer speeds.

Even at today’s CPU speeds, though, there still are some domains that do require optimal execution speeds. Numeric programming and animation, for example, often need at least their core number-crunching components to run at C speed (or better). If you work in such a domain, you can still use Python—simply split off the parts of the application that require optimal speed into compiled extensions, and link those into your system for use in Python scripts.

We won’t talk about extensions much in this text, but this is really just an instance of the Python-as-control-language role we discussed earlier. A prime example of this dual language strategy is the NumPy numeric programming extension for Python; by combining compiled and optimized numeric extension libraries with the Python language, NumPy turns Python into a numeric programming tool that is efficient and easy to use. You may never need to code such extensions in your own Python work, but they provide a powerful optimization mechanism if you ever do.

Who Uses Python Today?

At this writing, the best estimate anyone can seem to make of the size of the Python user base is that there are roughly 1 million Python users around the world today (plus or minus a few). This estimate is based on various statistics, like download rates and developer surveys. Because Python is open source, a more exact count is difficult—there are no license registrations to tally. Moreover, Python is automatically included with Linux distributions, Macintosh computers, and some products and hardware, further clouding the user-base picture.

In general, though, Python enjoys a large user base and a very active developer community. Because Python has been around for some 19 years and has been widely used, it is also very stable and robust. Besides being employed by individual users, Python is also being applied in real revenue-generating products by real companies. For instance:

Google makes extensive use of Python in its web search systems, and employs Python’s creator.

The YouTube video sharing service is largely written in Python.

The popular BitTorrent peer-to-peer file sharing system is a Python program.

Google’s popular App Engine web development framework uses Python as its application language.

EVE Online, a Massively Multiplayer Online Game (MMOG), makes extensive use of Python.

Maya, a powerful integrated 3D modeling and animation system, provides a Python scripting API.

Intel, Cisco, Hewlett-Packard, Seagate, Qualcomm, and IBM use Python for hardware testing.

Industrial Light & Magic, Pixar, and others use Python in the production of animated movies.

JPMorgan Chase, UBS, Getco, and Citadel apply Python for financial market forecasting.

NASA, Los Alamos, Fermilab, JPL, and others use Python for scientific programming tasks.

iRobot uses Python to develop commercial robotic devices.

ESRI uses Python as an end-user customization tool for its popular GIS mapping products.

The NSA uses Python for cryptography and intelligence analysis.

The IronPort email server product uses more than 1 million lines of Python code to do its job.

The One Laptop Per Child (OLPC) project builds its user interface and activity model in Python.

And so on. Probably the only common thread amongst the companies using Python today is that Python is used all over the map, in terms of application domains. Its general-purpose nature makes it applicable to almost all fields, not just one. In fact, it’s safe to say that virtually every substantial organization writing software is using Python, whether for short-term tactical tasks, such as testing and administration, or for long-term strategic product development. Python has proven to work well in both modes.

For more details on companies using Python today, see Python’s website at http://www.python.org.

What Can I Do with Python?

In addition to being a well-designed programming language, Python is useful for accomplishing real-world tasks—the sorts of things developers do day in and day out. It’s commonly used in a variety of domains, as a tool for scripting other components and implementing standalone programs. In fact, as a general-purpose language, Python’s roles are virtually unlimited: you can use it for everything from website development and gaming to robotics and spacecraft control.

However, the most common Python roles currently seem to fall into a few broad categories. The next few sections describe some of Python’s most common applications today, as well as tools used in each domain. We won’t be able to explore the tools mentioned here in any depth—if you are interested in any of these topics, see the Python website or other resources for more details.

Systems Programming

Python’s built-in interfaces to operating-system services make it ideal for writing portable, maintainable system-administration tools and utilities (sometimes called shell tools). Python programs can search files and directory trees, launch other programs, do parallel processing with processes and threads, and so on.

Python’s standard library comes with POSIX bindings and support for all the usual OS tools: environment variables, files, sockets, pipes, processes, multiple threads, regular expression pattern matching, command-line arguments, standard stream interfaces, shell-command launchers, filename expansion, and more. In addition, the bulk of Python’s system interfaces are designed to be portable; for example, a script that copies directory trees typically runs unchanged on all major Python platforms. The Stackless Python system, used by EVE Online, also offers advanced solutions to multiprocessing requirements.

GUIs

Python’s simplicity and rapid turnaround also make it a good match for graphical user interface programming. Python comes with a standard object-oriented interface to the Tk GUI API called tkinter (Tkinter in 2.6) that allows Python programs to implement portable GUIs with a native look and feel. Python/tkinter GUIs run unchanged on Microsoft Windows, X Windows (on Unix and Linux), and the Mac OS (both Classic and OS X). A free extension package, PMW, adds advanced widgets to the tkinter toolkit. In addition, the wxPython GUI API, based on a C++ library, offers an alternative toolkit for constructing portable GUIs in Python.

Higher-level toolkits such as PythonCard and Dabo are built on top of base APIs such as wxPython and tkinter. With the proper library, you can also use GUI support in other toolkits in Python, such as Qt with PyQt, GTK with PyGTK, MFC with PyWin32, .NET with IronPython, and Swing with Jython (the Java version of Python, described in Chapter 2) or JPype. For applications that run in web browsers or have simple interface requirements, both Jython and Python web frameworks and server-side CGI scripts, described in the next section, provide additional user interface options.

Internet Scripting

Python comes with standard Internet modules that allow Python programs to perform a wide variety of networking tasks, in client and server modes. Scripts can communicate over sockets; extract form information sent to server-side CGI scripts; transfer files by FTP; parse, generate, and analyze XML files; send, receive, compose, and parse email; fetch web pages by URLs; parse the HTML and XML of fetched web pages; communicate over XML-RPC, SOAP, and Telnet; and more. Python’s libraries make these tasks remarkably simple.

In addition, a large collection of third-party tools are available on the Web for doing Internet programming in Python. For instance, the HTMLGen system generates HTML files from Python class-based descriptions, the mod_python package runs Python efficiently within the Apache web server and supports server-side templating with its Python Server Pages, and the Jython system provides for seamless Python/Java integration and supports coding of server-side applets that run on clients.

In addition, full-blown web development framework packages for Python, such as Django, TurboGears, web2py, Pylons, Zope, and WebWare, support quick construction of full-featured and production-quality websites with Python. Many of these include features such as object-relational mappers, a Model/View/Controller architecture, server-side scripting and templating, and AJAX support, to provide complete and enterprise-level web development solutions.

Component Integration

We discussed the component integration role earlier when describing Python as a control language. Python’s ability to be extended by and embedded in C and C++ systems makes it useful as a flexible glue language for scripting the behavior of other systems and components. For instance, integrating a C library into Python enables Python to test and launch the library’s components, and embedding Python in a product enables onsite customizations to be coded without having to recompile the entire product (or ship its source code at all).

Tools such as the SWIG and SIP code generators can automate much of the work needed to link compiled components into Python for use in scripts, and the Cython system allows coders to mix Python and C-like code. Larger frameworks, such as Python’s COM support on Windows, the Jython Java-based implementation, the IronPython .NET-based implementation, and various CORBA toolkits for Python, provide alternative ways to script components. On Windows, for example, Python scripts can use frameworks to script Word and Excel.

Database Programming

For traditional database demands, there are Python interfaces to all commonly used relational database systems—Sybase, Oracle, Informix, ODBC, MySQL, PostgreSQL, SQLite, and more. The Python world has also defined a portable database API for accessing SQL database systems from Python scripts, which looks the same on a variety of underlying database systems. For instance, because the vendor interfaces implement the portable API, a script written to work with the free MySQL system will work largely unchanged on other systems (such as Oracle); all you have to do is replace the underlying vendor interface.

Python’s standard pickle module provides a simple object persistence system—it allows programs to easily save and restore entire Python objects to files and file-like objects. On the Web, you’ll also find a third-party open source system named ZODB that provides a complete object-oriented database system for Python scripts, and others (such as SQLObject and SQLAlchemy) that map relational tables onto Python’s class model. Furthermore, as of Python 2.5, the in-process SQLite embedded SQL database engine is a standard part of Python itself.

Rapid Prototyping

To Python programs, components written in Python and C look the same. Because of this, it’s possible to prototype systems in Python initially, and then move selected components to a compiled language such as C or C++ for delivery. Unlike some prototyping tools, Python doesn’t require a complete rewrite once the prototype has solidified. Parts of the system that don’t require the efficiency of a language such as C++ can remain coded in Python for ease of maintenance and use.

Numeric and Scientific Programming

The NumPy numeric programming extension for Python mentioned earlier includes such advanced tools as an array object, interfaces to standard mathematical libraries, and much more. By integrating Python with numeric routines coded in a compiled language for speed, NumPy turns Python into a sophisticated yet easy-to-use numeric programming tool that can often replace existing code written in traditional compiled languages such as FORTRAN or C++. Additional numeric tools for Python support animation, 3D visualization, parallel processing, and so on. The popular SciPy and ScientificPython extensions, for example, provide additional libraries of scientific programming tools and use NumPy code.

Gaming, Images, Serial Ports, XML, Robots, and More

Python is commonly applied in more domains than can be mentioned here. For example, you can do:

Game programming and multimedia in Python with the pygame system

Serial port communication on Windows, Linux, and more with the PySerial extension

Image processing with PIL, PyOpenGL, Blender, Maya, and others

Robot control programming with the PyRo toolkit

XML parsing with the xml library package, the xmlrpclib module, and third-party extensions

Artificial intelligence programming with neural network simulators and expert system shells

Natural language analysis with the NLTK package

You can even play solitaire with the PySol program. You’ll find support for many such fields at the PyPI websites, and via web searches (search Google or http://www.python.org for links).

Many of these specific domains are largely just instances of Python’s component integration role in action again. Adding it as a frontend to libraries of components written in a compiled language such as C makes Python useful for scripting in a wide variety of domains. As a general-purpose language that supports integration, Python is widely applicable.

How Is Python Supported?

As a popular open source system, Python enjoys a large and active development community that responds to issues and develops enhancements with a speed that many commercial software developers would find remarkable (if not downright shocking). Python developers coordinate work online with a source-control system. Changes follow a formal PEP (Python Enhancement Proposal) protocol and must be accompanied by extensions to Python’s extensive regression testing system. In fact, modifying Python today is roughly as involved as changing commercial software—a far cry from Python’s early days, when an email to its creator would suffice, but a good thing given its current large user base.

The PSF (Python Software Foundation), a formal nonprofit group, organizes conferences and deals with intellectual property issues. Numerous Python conferences are held around the world; O’Reilly’s OSCON and the PSF’s PyCon are the largest. The former of these addresses multiple open source projects, and the latter is a Python-only event that has experienced strong growth in recent years. Attendance at PyCon 2008 nearly doubled from the prior year, growing from 586 attendees in 2007 to over 1,000 in 2008. This was on the heels of a 40% attendance increase in 2007, from 410 in 2006. PyCon 2009 had 943 attendees, a slight decrease from 2008, but a still very strong showing during a global recession.

What Are Python’s Technical Strengths?

Naturally, this is a developer’s question. If you don’t already have a programming background, the language in the next few sections may be a bit baffling—don’t worry, we’ll explore all of these terms in more detail as we proceed through this book. For developers, though, here is a quick introduction to some of Python’s top technical features.

It’s Object-Oriented

Python is an object-oriented language, from the ground up. Its class model supports advanced notions such as polymorphism, operator overloading, and multiple inheritance; yet, in the context of Python’s simple syntax and typing, OOP is remarkably easy to apply. In fact, if you don’t understand these terms, you’ll find they are much easier to learn with Python than with just about any other OOP language available.

Besides serving as a powerful code structuring and reuse device, Python’s OOP nature makes it ideal as a scripting tool for object-oriented systems languages such as C++ and Java. For example, with the appropriate glue code, Python programs can subclass (specialize) classes implemented in C++, Java, and C#.

Of equal significance, OOP is an option in Python; you can go far without having to become an object guru all at once. Much like C++, Python supports both procedural and object-oriented programming modes. Its object-oriented tools can be applied if and when constraints allow. This is especially useful in tactical development modes, which preclude design phases.

It’s Free

Python is completely free to use and distribute. As with other open source software, such as Tcl, Perl, Linux, and Apache, you can fetch the entire Python system’s source code for free on the Internet. There are no restrictions on copying it, embedding it in your systems, or shipping it with your products. In fact, you can even sell Python’s source code, if you are so inclined.

But don’t get the wrong idea: “free” doesn’t mean “unsupported.” On the contrary, the Python online community responds to user queries with a speed that most commercial software help desks would do well to try to emulate. Moreover, because Python comes with complete source code, it empowers developers, leading to the creation of a large team of implementation experts. Although studying or changing a programming language’s implementation isn’t everyone’s idea of fun, it’s comforting to know that you can do so if you need to. You’re not dependent on the whims of a commercial vendor; the ultimate documentation source is at your disposal.

As mentioned earlier, Python development is performed by a community that largely coordinates its efforts over the Internet. It consists of Python’s creator—Guido van Rossum, the officially anointed Benevolent Dictator for Life (BDFL) of Python—plus a supporting cast of thousands. Language changes must follow a formal enhancement procedure and be scrutinized by both other developers and the BDFL. Happily, this tends to make Python more conservative with changes than some other languages.

It’s Portable

The standard implementation of Python is written in portable ANSI C, and it compiles and runs on virtually every major platform currently in use. For example, Python programs run today on everything from PDAs to supercomputers. As a partial list, Python is available on:

Linux and Unix systems

Microsoft Windows and DOS (all modern flavors)

Mac OS (both OS X and Classic)

BeOS, OS/2, VMS, and QNX

Real-time systems such as VxWorks

Cray supercomputers and IBM mainframes

PDAs running Palm OS, PocketPC, and Linux

Cell phones running Symbian OS and Windows Mobile

Gaming consoles and iPods

And more

Like the language interpreter itself, the standard library modules that ship with Python are implemented to be as portable across platform boundaries as possible. Further, Python programs are automatically compiled to portable byte code, which runs the same on any platform with a compatible version of Python installed (more on this in the next chapter).

What that means is that Python programs using the core language and standard libraries run the same on Linux, Windows, and most other systems with a Python interpreter. Most Python ports also contain platform-specific extensions (e.g., COM support on Windows), but the core Python language and libraries work the same everywhere. As mentioned earlier, Python also includes an interface to the Tk GUI toolkit called tkinter (Tkinter in 2.6), which allows Python programs to implement full-featured graphical user interfaces that run on all major GUI platforms without program changes.

It’s Powerful

From a features perspective, Python is something of a hybrid. Its toolset places it between traditional scripting languages (such as Tcl, Scheme, and Perl) and systems development languages (such as C, C++, and Java). Python provides all the simplicity and ease of use of a scripting language, along with more advanced software-engineering tools typically found in compiled languages. Unlike some scripting languages, this combination makes Python useful for large-scale development projects. As a preview, here are some of the main things you’ll find in Python’s toolbox:

Dynamic typing

Python keeps track of the kinds of objects your program uses when it runs; it doesn’t require complicated type and size declarations in your code. In fact, as you’ll see in Chapter 6, there is no such thing as a type or variable declaration anywhere in Python. Because Python code does not constrain data types, it is also usually automatically applicable to a whole range of objects.

Automatic memory management

Python automatically allocates objects and reclaims (“garbage collects”) them when they are no longer used, and most can grow and shrink on demand. As you’ll learn, Python keeps track of low-level memory details so you don’t have to.

Programming-in-the-large support

For building larger systems, Python includes tools such as modules, classes, and exceptions. These tools allow you to organize systems into components, use OOP to reuse and customize code, and handle events and errors gracefully.

Built-in object types

Python provides commonly used data structures such as lists, dictionaries, and strings as intrinsic parts of the language; as you’ll see, they’re both flexible and easy to use. For instance, built-in objects can grow and shrink on demand, can be arbitrarily nested to represent complex information, and more.

Built-in tools

To process all those object types, Python comes with powerful and standard operations, including concatenation (joining collections), slicing (extracting sections), sorting, mapping, and more.

Library utilities

For more specific tasks, Python also comes with a large collection of precoded library tools that support everything from regular expression matching to networking. Once you learn the language itself, Python’s library tools are where much of the application-level action occurs.

Third-party utilities

Because Python is open source, developers are encouraged to contribute precoded tools that support tasks beyond those supported by its built-ins; on the Web, you’ll find free support for COM, imaging, CORBA ORBs, XML, database access, and much more.

Despite the array of tools in Python, it retains a remarkably simple syntax and design. The result is a powerful programming tool with all the usability of a scripting language.

It’s Mixable

Python programs can easily be “glued” to components written in other languages in a variety of ways. For example, Python’s C API lets C programs call and be called by Python programs flexibly. That means you can add functionality to the Python system as needed, and use Python programs within other environments or systems.

Mixing Python with libraries coded in languages such as C or C++, for instance, makes it an easy-to-use frontend language and customization tool. As mentioned earlier, this also makes Python good at rapid prototyping; systems may be implemented in Python first, to leverage its speed of development, and later moved to C for delivery, one piece at a time, according to performance demands.

It’s Easy to Use

To run a Python program, you simply type it and run it. There are no intermediate compile and link steps, like there are for languages such as C or C++. Python executes programs immediately, which makes for an interactive programming experience and rapid turnaround after program changes—in many cases, you can witness the effect of a program change as fast as you can type it.

Of course, development cycle turnaround is only one aspect of Python’s ease of use. It also provides a deliberately simple syntax and powerful built-in tools. In fact, some have gone so far as to call Python “executable pseudocode.” Because it eliminates much of the complexity in other tools, Python programs are simpler, smaller, and more flexible than equivalent programs in languages like C, C++, and Java.

It’s Easy to Learn

This brings us to a key point of this book: compared to other programming languages, the core Python language is remarkably easy to learn. In fact, you can expect to be coding significant Python programs in a matter of days (or perhaps in just hours, if you’re already an experienced programmer). That’s good news for professional developers seeking to learn the language to use on the job, as well as for end users of systems that expose a Python layer for customization or control.

Today, many systems rely on the fact that end users can quickly learn enough Python to tailor their Python customizations’ code onsite, with little or no support. Although Python does have advanced programming tools, its core language will still seem simple to beginners and gurus alike.

It’s Named After Monty Python

OK, this isn’t quite a technical strength, but it does seem to be a surprisingly well-kept secret that I wish to expose up front. Despite all the reptile icons in the Python world, the truth is that Python creator Guido van Rossum named it after the BBC comedy series Monty Python’s Flying Circus. He is a big fan of Monty Python, as are many software developers (indeed, there seems to almost be a symmetry between the two fields).

This legacy inevitably adds a humorous quality to Python code examples. For instance, the traditional “foo” and “bar” for generic variable names become “spam” and “eggs” in the Python world. The occasional “Brian,” “ni,” and “shrubbery” likewise owe their appearances to this namesake. It even impacts the Python community at large: talks at Python conferences are regularly billed as “The Spanish Inquisition.”

All of this is, of course, very funny if you are familiar with the show, but less so otherwise. You don’t need to be familiar with the series to make sense of examples that borrow references to Monty Python (including many you will see in this book), but at least you now know their root.

How Does Python Stack Up to Language X?

Finally, to place it in the context of what you may already know, people sometimes compare Python to languages such as Perl, Tcl, and Java. We talked about performance earlier, so here we’ll focus on functionality. While other languages are also useful tools to know and use, many people find that Python:

Is more powerful than Tcl. Python’s support for “programming in the large” makes it applicable to the development of larger systems.

Has a cleaner syntax and simpler design than Perl, which makes it more readable and maintainable and helps reduce program bugs.

Is simpler and easier to use than Java. Python is a scripting language, but Java inherits much of the complexity and syntax of systems languages such as C++.

Is simpler and easier to use than C++, but it doesn’t often compete with C++; as a scripting language, Python typically serves different roles.

Is both more powerful and more cross-platform than Visual Basic. Its open source nature also means it is not controlled by a single company.

Is more readable and general-purpose than PHP. Python is sometimes used to construct websites, but it’s also widely used in nearly every other computer domain, from robotics to movie animation.

Is more mature and has a more readable syntax than Ruby. Unlike Ruby and Java, OOP is an option in Python—Python does not impose OOP on users or projects to which it may not apply.

Has the dynamic flavor of languages like SmallTalk and Lisp, but also has a simple, traditional syntax accessible to developers as well as end users of customizable systems.

Especially for programs that do more than scan text files, and that might have to be read in the future by others (or by you!), many people find that Python fits the bill better than any other scripting or programming language available today. Furthermore, unless your application requires peak performance, Python is often a viable alternative to systems development languages such as C, C++, and Java: Python code will be much less difficult to write, debug, and maintain.

Of course, your author has been a card-carrying Python evangelist since 1992, so take these comments as you may. They do, however, reflect the common experience of many developers who have taken time to explore what Python has to offer.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

How did you do? Here are the answers I came up with, though there may be multiple solutions to some quiz questions. Again, even if you’re sure you got a question right, I encourage you to look at these answers for additional context. See the chapter’s text for more details if any of these responses don’t make sense to you.

Software quality, developer productivity, program portability, support libraries, component integration, and simple enjoyment. Of these, the quality and productivity themes seem to be the main reasons that people choose to use Python.

Google, Industrial Light & Magic, EVE Online, Jet Propulsion Labs, Maya, ESRI, and many more. Almost every organization doing software development uses Python in some fashion, whether for long-term strategic product development or for short-term tactical tasks such as testing and system administration.

Python’s downside is performance: it won’t run as quickly as fully compiled languages like C and C++. On the other hand, it’s quick enough for most applications, and typical Python code runs at close to C speed anyhow because it invokes linked-in C code in the interpreter. If speed is critical, compiled extensions are available for number-crunching parts of an application.

You can use Python for nearly anything you can do with a computer, from website development and gaming to robotics and spacecraft control.

import this triggers an Easter egg inside Python that displays some of the design philosophies underlying the language. You’ll learn how to run this statement in the next chapter.

“Spam” is a reference from a famous Monty Python skit in which people trying to order food in a cafeteria are drowned out by a chorus of Vikings singing about spam. Oh, and it’s also a common variable name in Python scripts....

Blue. No, yellow!

Python Is Engineering, Not Art

When Python first emerged on the software scene in the early 1990s, it spawned what is now something of a classic conflict between its proponents and those of another popular scripting language, Perl. Personally, I think the debate is tired and unwarranted today—developers are smart enough to draw their own conclusions. Still, this is one of the most common topics I’m asked about on the training road, so it seems fitting to say a few words about it here.

The short story is this: you can do everything in Python that you can in Perl, but you can read your code after you do it. That’s it—their domains largely overlap, but Python is more focused on producing readable code. For many, the enhanced readability of Python translates to better code reusability and maintainability, making Python a better choice for programs that will not be written once and thrown away. Perl code is easy to write, but difficult to read. Given that most software has a lifespan much longer than its initial creation, many see Python as a more effective tool.

The somewhat longer story reflects the backgrounds of the designers of the two languages and underscores some of the main reasons people choose to use Python. Python’s creator is a mathematician by training; as such, he produced a language with a high degree of uniformity—its syntax and toolset are remarkably coherent. Moreover, like math, Python’s design is orthogonal—most of the language follows from a small set of core concepts. For instance, once one grasps Python’s flavor of polymorphism, the rest is largely just details.

By contrast, the creator of the Perl language is a linguist, and its design reflects this heritage. There are many ways to accomplish the same tasks in Perl, and language constructs interact in context-sensitive and sometimes quite subtle ways—much like natural language. As the well-known Perl motto states, “There’s more than one way to do it.” Given this design, both the Perl language and its user community have historically encouraged freedom of expression when writing code. One person’s Perl code can be radically different from another’s. In fact, writing unique, tricky code is often a source of pride among Perl users.

But as anyone who has done any substantial code maintenance should be able to attest, freedom of expression is great for art, but lousy for engineering. In engineering, we need a minimal feature set and predictability. In engineering, freedom of expression can lead to maintenance nightmares. As more than one Perl user has confided to me, the result of too much freedom is often code that is much easier to rewrite from scratch than to modify.

Consider this: when people create a painting or a sculpture, they do so for themselves for purely aesthetic purposes. The possibility of someone else having to change that painting or sculpture later does not enter into it. This is a critical difference between art and engineering. When people write software, they are not writing it for themselves. In fact, they are not even writing primarily for the computer. Rather, good programmers know that code is written for the next human being who has to read it in order to maintain or reuse it. If that person cannot understand the code, it’s all but useless in a realistic development scenario.

This is where many people find that Python most clearly differentiates itself from scripting languages like Perl. Because Python’s syntax model almost forces users to write readable code, Python programs lend themselves more directly to the full software development cycle. And because Python emphasizes ideas such as limited interactions, code uniformity and regularity, and feature consistency, it more directly fosters code that can be used long after it is first written.

In the long run, Python’s focus on code quality in itself boosts programmer productivity, as well as programmer satisfaction. Python programmers can be creative, too, of course, and as we’ll see, the language does offer multiple solutions for some tasks. At its core, though, Python encourages good engineering in ways that other scripting languages often do not.

At least, that’s the common consensus among many people who have adopted Python. You should always judge such claims for yourself, of course, by learning what Python has to offer. To help you get started, let’s move on to the next chapter.

[2] For a more complete look at the Python philosophy, type the command import this at any Python interactive prompt (you’ll see how in Chapter 2). This invokes an “Easter egg” hidden in Python—a collection of design principles underlying Python. The acronym EIBTI is now fashionable jargon for the “explicit is better than implicit” rule.

Execution Model Variations

Before moving on, I should point out that the internal execution flow described in the prior section reflects the standard implementation of Python today but is not really a requirement of the Python language itself. Because of that, the execution model is prone to changing with time. In fact, there are already a few systems that modify the picture in Figure 2-2 somewhat. Let’s take a few moments to explore the most prominent of these variations.

Python Implementation Alternatives

Really, as this book is being written, there are three primary implementations of the Python language—CPython, Jython, and IronPython—along with a handful of secondary implementations such as Stackless Python. In brief, CPython is the standard implementation; all the others have very specific purposes and roles. All implement the same Python language but execute programs in different ways.

CPython

The original, and standard, implementation of Python is usually called CPython, when you want to contrast it with the other two. Its name comes from the fact that it is coded in portable ANSI C language code. This is the Python that you fetch from http://www.python.org, get with the ActivePython distribution, and have automatically on most Linux and Mac OS X machines. If you’ve found a preinstalled version of Python on your machine, it’s probably CPython, unless your company is using Python in very specialized ways.

Unless you want to script Java or .NET applications with Python, you probably want to use the standard CPython system. Because it is the reference implementation of the language, it tends to run the fastest, be the most complete, and be more robust than the alternative systems. Figure 2-2 reflects CPython’s runtime architecture.

Jython

The Jython system (originally known as JPython) is an alternative implementation of the Python language, targeted for integration with the Java programming language. Jython consists of Java classes that compile Python source code to Java byte code and then route the resulting byte code to the Java Virtual Machine (JVM). Programmers still code Python statements in .py text files as usual; the Jython system essentially just replaces the rightmost two bubbles in Figure 2-2 with Java-based equivalents.

Jython’s goal is to allow Python code to script Java applications, much as CPython allows Python to script C and C++ components. Its integration with Java is remarkably seamless. Because Python code is translated to Java byte code, it looks and feels like a true Java program at runtime. Jython scripts can serve as web applets and servlets, build Java-based GUIs, and so on. Moreover, Jython includes integration support that allows Python code to import and use Java classes as though they were coded in Python. Because Jython is slower and less robust than CPython, though, it is usually seen as a tool of interest primarily to Java developers looking for a scripting language to be a frontend to Java code.

IronPython

A third implementation of Python, and newer than both CPython and Jython, IronPython is designed to allow Python programs to integrate with applications coded to work with Microsoft’s .NET Framework for Windows, as well as the Mono open source equivalent for Linux. .NET and its C# programming language runtime system are designed to be a language-neutral object communication layer, in the spirit of Microsoft’s earlier COM model. IronPython allows Python programs to act as both client and server components, accessible from other .NET languages.

By implementation, IronPython is very much like Jython (and, in fact, was developed by the same creator)—it replaces the last two bubbles in Figure 2-2 with equivalents for execution in the .NET environment. Also, like Jython, IronPython has a special focus—it is primarily of interest to developers integrating Python with .NET components. Because it is being developed by Microsoft, though, IronPython might also be able to leverage some important optimization tools for better performance. IronPython’s scope is still evolving as I write this; for more details, consult the Python online resources or search the Web.[4]

Execution Optimization Tools

CPython, Jython, and IronPython all implement the Python language in similar ways: by compiling source code to byte code and executing the byte code on an appropriate virtual machine. Still other systems, including the Psyco just-in-time compiler and the Shedskin C++ translator, instead attempt to optimize the basic execution model. These systems are not required knowledge at this point in your Python career, but a quick look at their place in the execution model might help demystify the model in general.

The Psyco just-in-time compiler

The Psyco system is not another Python implementation, but rather a component that extends the byte code execution model to make programs run faster. In terms of Figure 2-2, Psyco is an enhancement to the PVM that collects and uses type information while the program runs to translate portions of the program’s byte code all the way down to real binary machine code for faster execution. Psyco accomplishes this translation without requiring changes to the code or a separate compilation step during development.

Roughly, while your program runs, Psyco collects information about the kinds of objects being passed around; that information can be used to generate highly efficient machine code tailored for those object types. Once generated, the machine code then replaces the corresponding part of the original byte code to speed your program’s overall execution. The net effect is that, with Psyco, your program becomes much quicker over time and as it is running. In ideal cases, some Python code may become as fast as compiled C code under Psyco.

Because this translation from byte code happens at program runtime, Psyco is generally known as a just-in-time (JIT) compiler. Psyco is actually a bit different from the JIT compilers some readers may have seen for the Java language, though. Really, Psyco is a specializing JIT compiler—it generates machine code tailored to the data types that your program actually uses. For example, if a part of your program uses different data types at different times, Psyco may generate a different version of machine code to support each different type combination.

Psyco has been shown to speed Python code dramatically. According to its web page, Psyco provides “2x to 100x speed-ups, typically 4x, with an unmodified Python interpreter and unmodified source code, just a dynamically loadable C extension module.” Of equal significance, the largest speedups are realized for algorithmic code written in pure Python—exactly the sort of code you might normally migrate to C to optimize. With Psyco, such migrations become even less important.

Psyco is not yet a standard part of Python; you will have to fetch and install it separately. It is also still something of a research project, so you’ll have to track its evolution online. In fact, at this writing, although Psyco can still be fetched and installed by itself, it appears that much of the system may eventually be absorbed into the newer “PyPy” project—an attempt to reimplement Python’s PVM in Python code, to better support optimizations like Psyco.

Perhaps the largest downside of Psyco is that it currently only generates machine code for Intel x86 architecture chips, though this includes Windows and Linux boxes and recent Macs. For more details on the Psyco extension, and other JIT efforts that may arise, consult http://www.python.org; you can also check out Psyco’s home page, which currently resides at http://psyco.sourceforge.net.

The Shedskin C++ translator

Shedskin is an emerging system that takes a different approach to Python program execution—it attempts to translate Python source code to C++ code, which your computer’s C++ compiler then compiles to machine code. As such, it represents a platform-neutral approach to running Python code. Shedskin is still somewhat experimental as I write these words, and it limits Python programs to an implicit statically typed constraint that is technically not normal Python, so we won’t go into further detail here. Initial results, though, show that it has the potential to outperform both standard Python and the Psyco extension in terms of execution speed, and it is a promising project. Search the Web for details on the project’s current status.

Frozen Binaries

Sometimes when people ask for a “real” Python compiler, what they’re really seeking is simply a way to generate standalone binary executables from their Python programs. This is more a packaging and shipping idea than an execution-flow concept, but it’s somewhat related. With the help of third-party tools that you can fetch off the Web, it is possible to turn your Python programs into true executables, known as frozen binaries in the Python world.

Frozen binaries bundle together the byte code of your program files, along with the PVM (interpreter) and any Python support files your program needs, into a single package. There are some variations on this theme, but the end result can be a single binary executable program (e.g., an .exe file on Windows) that can easily be shipped to customers. In Figure 2-2, it is as though the byte code and PVM are merged into a single component—a frozen binary file.

Today, three primary systems are capable of generating frozen binaries: py2exe (for Windows), PyInstaller (which is similar to py2exe but also works on Linux and Unix and is capable of generating self-installing binaries), and freeze (the original). You may have to fetch these tools separately from Python itself, but they are available free of charge. They are also constantly evolving, so consult http://www.python.org or your favorite web search engine for more on these tools. To give you an idea of the scope of these systems, py2exe can freeze standalone programs that use the tkinter, PMW, wxPython, and PyGTK GUI libraries; programs that use the pygame game programming toolkit; win32com client programs; and more.

Frozen binaries are not the same as the output of a true compiler—they run byte code through a virtual machine. Hence, apart from a possible startup improvement, frozen binaries run at the same speed as the original source files. Frozen binaries are not small (they contain a PVM), but by current standards they are not unusually large either. Because Python is embedded in the frozen binary, though, it does not have to be installed on the receiving end to run your program. Moreover, because your code is embedded in the frozen binary, it is more effectively hidden from recipients.

This single file-packaging scheme is especially appealing to developers of commercial software. For instance, a Python-coded user interface program based on the tkinter toolkit can be frozen into an executable file and shipped as a self-contained program on a CD or on the Web. End users do not need to install (or even have to know about) Python to run the shipped program.

Other Execution Options

Still other schemes for running Python programs have more focused goals:

The Stackless Python system is a standard CPython implementation variant that does not save state on the C language call stack. This makes Python more easy to port to small stack architectures, provides efficient multiprocessing options, and fosters novel programming structures such as coroutines.

The Cython system (based on work done by the Pyrex project) is a hybrid language that combines Python code with the ability to call C functions and use C type declarations for variables, parameters, and class attributes. Cython code can be compiled to C code that uses the Python/C API, which may then be compiled completely. Though not completely compatible with standard Python, Cython can be useful both for wrapping external C libraries and for coding efficient C extensions for Python.

For more details on these systems, search the Web for recent links.

Future Possibilities?

Finally, note that the runtime execution model sketched here is really an artifact of the current implementation of Python, not of the language itself. For instance, it’s not impossible that a full, traditional compiler for translating Python source code to machine code may appear during the shelf life of this book (although one has not in nearly two decades!). New byte code formats and implementation variants may also be adopted in the future. For instance:

The Parrot project aims to provide a common byte code format, virtual machine, and optimization techniques for a variety of programming languages (see http://www.python.org). Python’s own PVM runs Python code more efficiently than Parrot, but it’s unclear how Parrot will evolve.

The PyPy project is an attempt to reimplement the PVM in Python itself to enable new implementation techniques. Its goal is to produce a fast and flexible implementation of Python.

The Google-sponsored Unladen Swallow project aims to make standard Python faster by a factor of at least 5, and fast enough to replace the C language in many contexts. It is an optimization branch of CPython, intended to be fully compatible and significantly faster. This project also hopes to remove the Python multithreading Global Interpreter Lock (GIL), which prevents pure Python threads from truly overlapping in time. This is currently an emerging project being developed as open source by Google engineers; it is initially targeting Python 2.6, though 3.0 may acquire its changes too. Search Google for up-to-date details.

Although such future implementation schemes may alter the runtime structure of Python somewhat, it seems likely that the byte code compiler will still be the standard for some time to come. The portability and runtime flexibility of byte code are important features of many Python systems. Moreover, adding type constraint declarations to support static compilation would break the flexibility, conciseness, simplicity, and overall spirit of Python coding. Due to Python’s highly dynamic nature, any future implementation will likely retain many artifacts of the current PVM.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

The Python interpreter is a program that runs the Python programs you write.

Source code is the statements you write for your program—it consists of text in text files that normally end with a .py extension.

Byte code is the lower-level form of your program after Python compiles it. Python automatically stores byte code in files with a .pyc extension.

The PVM is the Python Virtual Machine—the runtime engine of Python that interprets your compiled byte code.

Psyco, Shedskin, and frozen binaries are all variations on the execution model.

CPython is the standard implementation of the language. Jython and IronPython implement Python programs for use in Java and .NET environments, respectively; they are alternative compilers for Python.

[3] And, strictly speaking, byte code is saved only for files that are imported, not for the top-level file of a program. We’ll explore imports in Chapter 3, and again in Part V. Byte code is also never saved for code typed at the interactive prompt, which is described in Chapter 3.

[4] Jython and IronPython are completely independent implementations of Python that compile Python source for different runtime architectures. It is also possible to access Java and .NET software from standard CPython programs: JPype and Python for .NET systems, for example, allow CPython code to call out to Java and .NET components.

Chapter 3. How You Run Programs

OK, it’s time to start running some code. Now that you have a handle on program execution, you’re finally ready to start some real Python programming. At this point, I’ll assume that you have Python installed on your computer; if not, see the prior chapter and Appendix A for installation and configuration hints.

There are a variety of ways to tell Python to execute the code you type. This chapter discusses all the program launching techniques in common use today. Along the way, you’ll learn how to type code interactively and how to save it in files to be run with system command lines, icon clicks, module imports and reloads, exec calls, menu options in GUIs such as IDLE, and more.

If you just want to find out how to run a Python program quickly, you may be tempted to read the parts of this chapter that pertain only to your platform and move on to Chapter 4. But don’t skip the material on module imports, as that’s essential to understanding Python’s program architecture. I also encourage you to at least skim the sections on IDLE and other IDEs, so you’ll know what tools are available for when you start developing more sophisticated Python programs.

The Interactive Prompt

Perhaps the simplest way to run Python programs is to type them at Python’s interactive command line, sometimes called the interactive prompt. There are a variety of ways to start this command line: in an IDE, from a system console, and so on. Assuming the interpreter is installed as an executable program on your system, the most platform-neutral way to start an interactive interpreter session is usually just to type python at your operating system’s prompt, without any arguments. For example:

% python
Python 3.0.1 (r301:69561, Feb 13 2009, 20:04:18) [MSC v.1500 32 bit (Intel)] ...
Type "help", "copyright", "credits" or "license" for more information.
>>>

Typing the word “python” at your system shell prompt like this begins an interactive Python session; the “%” character at the start of this listing stands for a generic system prompt in this book—it’s not input that you type yourself. The notion of a system shell prompt is generic, but exactly how you access it varies by platform:

On Windows, you can type python in a DOS console window (a.k.a. the Command Prompt, usually found in the Accessories section of the Start→Programs menu) or in the Start→Run... dialog box.

On Unix, Linux, and Mac OS X, you might type this command in a shell or terminal window (e.g., in an xterm or console running a shell such as ksh or csh).

Other systems may use similar or platform-specific devices. On handheld devices, for example, you generally click the Python icon in the home or application window to launch an interactive session.

If you have not set your shell’s PATH environment variable to include Python’s install directory, you may need to replace the word “python” with the full path to the Python executable on your machine. On Unix, Linux, and similar, /usr/local/bin/python or /usr/bin/python will often suffice. On Windows, try typing C:\Python30\python (for version 3.0):

C:\misc> c:\python30\python
Python 3.0.1 (r301:69561, Feb 13 2009, 20:04:18) [MSC v.1500 32 bit (Intel)] ...
Type "help", "copyright", "credits" or "license" for more information.
>>>

Alternatively, you can run a change-directory command to go to Python’s install directory before typing “python”—try the cd c:\python30 command on Windows, for example:

C:\misc> cd C:\Python30
C:\Python30> python
Python 3.0.1 (r301:69561, Feb 13 2009, 20:04:18) [MSC v.1500 32 bit (Intel)] ...
Type "help", "copyright", "credits" or "license" for more information.
>>>

On Windows, besides typing python in a shell window, you can also begin similar interactive sessions by starting IDLE’s main window (discussed later) or by selecting the “Python (command line)” menu option from the Start button menu for Python, as shown in Figure 2-1 back in Chapter 2. Both spawn a Python interactive prompt with equivalent functionality; typing a shell command isn’t necessary.

Running Code Interactively

However it’s started, the Python interactive session begins by printing two lines of informational text (which I’ll omit from most of this book’s examples to save space), then prompts for input with >>> when it’s waiting for you to type a new Python statement or expression. When working interactively, the results of your code are displayed after the >>> lines after you press the Enter key.

For instance, here are the results of two Python print statements (print is really a function call in Python 3.0, but not in 2.6, so the parentheses here are required in 3.0 only):

% python
>>> print('Hello world!')
Hello world!
>>> print(2 ** 8)
256

Again, you don’t need to worry about the details of the print statements shown here yet; we’ll start digging into syntax in the next chapter. In short, they print a Python string and an integer, as shown by the output lines that appear after each >>> input line (2 ** 8 means 2 raised to the power 8 in Python).

When coding interactively like this, you can type as many Python commands as you like; each is run immediately after it’s entered. Moreover, because the interactive session automatically prints the results of expressions you type, you don’t usually need to say “print” explicitly at this prompt:

>>> lumberjack = 'okay'
>>> lumberjack
'okay'
>>> 2 ** 8
256
>>>                        <== Use Ctrl-D (on Unix) or Ctrl-Z (on Windows) to exit
%

Here, the first line saves a value by assigning it to a variable, and the last two lines typed are expressions (lumberjack and 2 ** 8)—their results are displayed automatically. To exit an interactive session like this one and return to your system shell prompt, type Ctrl-D on Unix-like machines; on MS-DOS and Windows systems, type Ctrl-Z to exit. In the IDLE GUI discussed later, either type Ctrl-D or simply close the window.

Now, we didn’t do much in this session’s code—just typed some Python print and assignment statements, along with a few expressions, which we’ll study in detail later. The main thing to notice is that the interpreter executes the code entered on each line immediately, when the Enter key is pressed.

For example, when we typed the first print statement at the >>> prompt, the output (a Python string) was echoed back right away. There was no need to create a source-code file, and no need to run the code through a compiler and linker first, as you’d normally do when using a language such as C or C++. As you’ll see in later chapters, you can also run multiline statements at the interactive prompt; such a statement runs immediately after you’ve entered all of its lines and pressed Enter twice to add a blank line.

Why the Interactive Prompt?

The interactive prompt runs code and echoes results as you go, but it doesn’t save your code in a file. Although this means you won’t do the bulk of your coding in interactive sessions, the interactive prompt turns out to be a great place to both experiment with the language and test program files on the fly.

Experimenting

Because code is executed immediately, the interactive prompt is a perfect place to experiment with the language and will be used often in this book to demonstrate smaller examples. In fact, this is the first rule of thumb to remember: if you’re ever in doubt about how a piece of Python code works, fire up the interactive command line and try it out to see what happens.

For instance, suppose you’re reading a Python program’s code and you come across an expression like 'Spam!' * 8 whose meaning you don’t understand. At this point, you can spend 10 minutes wading through manuals and books to try to figure out what the code does, or you can simply run it interactively:

>>> 'Spam!' * 8                                  <== Learning by trying
'Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!'

The immediate feedback you receive at the interactive prompt is often the quickest way to deduce what a piece of code does. Here, it’s clear that it does string repetition: in Python * means multiply for numbers, but repeat for strings—it’s like concatenating a string to itself repeatedly (more on strings in Chapter 4).

Chances are good that you won’t break anything by experimenting this way—at least, not yet. To do real damage, like deleting files and running shell commands, you must really try, by importing modules explicitly (you also need to know more about Python’s system interfaces in general before you will become that dangerous!). Straight Python code is almost always safe to run.

For instance, watch what happens when you make a mistake at the interactive prompt:

>>> X                                            <== Making mistakes
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "<stdin>", line 1, in <module>
NameError: name 'X' is not defined

In Python, using a variable before it has been assigned a value is always an error (otherwise, if names were filled in with defaults, some errors might go undetected). We’ll learn more about that later; the important point here is that you don’t crash Python or your computer when you make a mistake this way. Instead, you get a meaningful error message pointing out the mistake and the line of code that made it, and you can continue on in your session or script. In fact, once you get comfortable with Python, its error messages may often provide as much debugging support as you’ll need (you’ll read more on debugging in the sidebar Debugging Python Code).

Testing

Besides serving as a tool for experimenting while you’re learning the language, the interactive interpreter is also an ideal place to test code you’ve written in files. You can import your module files interactively and run tests on the tools they define by typing calls at the interactive prompt.

For instance, the following tests a function in a precoded module that ships with Python in its standard library (it prints the name of the directory you’re currently working in), but you can do the same once you start writing module files of your own:

>>> import os
>>> os.getcwd()                                  <== Testing on the fly
'c:\\Python30'

More generally, the interactive prompt is a place to test program components, regardless of their source—you can import and test functions and classes in your Python files, type calls to linked-in C functions, exercise Java classes under Jython, and more. Partly because of its interactive nature, Python supports an experimental and exploratory programming style you’ll find convenient when getting started.

Using the Interactive Prompt

Although the interactive prompt is simple to use, there are a few tips that beginners should keep in mind. I’m including lists of common mistakes like this in this chapter for reference, but they might also spare you from a few headaches if you read them up front:

Type Python commands only. First of all, remember that you can only type Python code at the Python prompt, not system commands. There are ways to run system commands from within Python code (e.g., with os.system), but they are not as direct as simply typing the commands themselves.

print statements are required only in files. Because the interactive interpreter automatically prints the results of expressions, you do not need to type complete print statements interactively. This is a nice feature, but it tends to confuse users when they move on to writing code in files: within a code file, you must use print statements to see your output because expression results are not automatically echoed. Remember, you must say print in files, but not interactively.

Don’t indent at the interactive prompt (yet). When typing Python programs, either interactively or into a text file, be sure to start all your unnested statements in column 1 (that is, all the way to the left). If you don’t, Python may print a “SyntaxError” message, because blank space to the left of your code is taken to be indentation that groups nested statements. Until Chapter 10, all statements you write will be unnested, so this includes everything for now. This seems to be a recurring confusion in introductory Python classes. Remember, a leading space generates an error message.

Watch out for prompt changes for compound statements. We won’t meet compound (multiline) statements until Chapter 4, and not in earnest until Chapter 10, but as a preview, you should know that when typing lines 2 and beyond of a compound statement interactively, the prompt may change. In the simple shell window interface, the interactive prompt changes to ... instead of >>> for lines 2 and beyond; in the IDLE interface, lines after the first are automatically indented.

You’ll see why this matters in Chapter 10. For now, if you happen to come across a ... prompt or a blank line when entering your code, it probably means that you’ve somehow confused interactive Python into thinking you’re typing a multiline statement. Try hitting the Enter key or a Ctrl-C combination to get back to the main prompt. The >>> and ... prompt strings can also be changed (they are available in the built-in module sys), but I’ll assume they have not been in the book’s example listings.

Terminate compound statements at the interactive prompt with a blank line. At the interactive prompt, inserting a blank line (by hitting the Enter key at the start of a line) is necessary to tell interactive Python that you’re done typing the multiline statement. That is, you must press Enter twice to make a compound statement run. By contrast, blank lines are not required in files and are simply ignored if present. If you don’t press Enter twice at the end of a compound statement when working interactively, you’ll appear to be stuck in a limbo state, because the interactive interpreter will do nothing at all—it’s waiting for you to press Enter again!

The interactive prompt runs one statement at a time. At the interactive prompt, you must run one statement to completion before typing another. This is natural for simple statements, because pressing the Enter key runs the statement entered. For compound statements, though, remember that you must submit a blank line to terminate the statement and make it run before you can type the next statement.

Entering multiline statements

At the risk of repeating myself, I received emails from readers who’d gotten burned by the last two points as I was updating this chapter, so it probably merits emphasis. I’ll introduce multiline (a.k.a. compound) statements in the next chapter, and we’ll explore their syntax more formally later in this book. Because their behavior differs slightly in files and at the interactive prompt, though, two cautions are in order here.

First, be sure to terminate multiline compound statements like for loops and if tests at the interactive prompt with a blank line. You must press the Enter key twice, to terminate the whole multiline statement and then make it run. For example (pun not intended...):

>>> for x in 'spam':
...     print(x)              <== Press Enter twice here to make this loop run
...

You don’t need the blank line after compound statements in a script file, though; this is required only at the interactive prompt. In a file, blank lines are not required and are simply ignored when present; at the interactive prompt, they terminate multiline statements.

Also bear in mind that the interactive prompt runs just one statement at a time: you must press Enter twice to run a loop or other multiline statement before you can type the next statement:

>>> for x in 'spam':
...     print(x)              <== Need to press Enter twice before a new statement
... print('done')
  File "<stdin>", line 3
    print('done')
        ^
SyntaxError: invalid syntax

This means you can’t cut and paste multiple lines of code into the interactive prompt, unless the code includes blank lines after each compound statement. Such code is better run in a file—the next section’s topic.

System Command Lines and Files

Although the interactive prompt is great for experimenting and testing, it has one big disadvantage: programs you type there go away as soon as the Python interpreter executes them. Because the code you type interactively is never stored in a file, you can’t run it again without retyping it from scratch. Cut-and-paste and command recall can help some here, but not much, especially when you start writing larger programs. To cut and paste code from an interactive session, you would have to edit out Python prompts, program outputs, and so on—not exactly a modern software development methodology!

To save programs permanently, you need to write your code in files, which are usually known as modules. Modules are simply text files containing Python statements. Once coded, you can ask the Python interpreter to execute the statements in such a file any number of times, and in a variety of ways—by system command lines, by file icon clicks, by options in the IDLE user interface, and more. Regardless of how it is run, Python executes all the code in a module file from top to bottom each time you run the file.

Terminology in this domain can vary somewhat. For instance, module files are often referred to as programs in Python—that is, a program is considered to be a series of precoded statements stored in a file for repeated execution. Module files that are run directly are also sometimes called scripts—an informal term usually meaning a top-level program file. Some reserve the term “module” for a file imported from another file. (More on the meaning of “top-level” and imports in a few moments.)

Whatever you call them, the next few sections explore ways to run code typed into module files. In this section, you’ll learn how to run files in the most basic way: by listing their names in a python command line entered at your computer’s system prompt. Though it might seem primitive to some, for many programmers a system shell command-line window, together with a text editor window, constitutes as much of an integrated development environment as they will ever need.

A First Script

Let’s get started. Open your favorite text editor (e.g., vi, Notepad, or the IDLE editor), and type the following statements into a new text file named script1.py:

# A first Python script
import sys                  # Load a library module
print(sys.platform)
print(2 ** 100)             # Raise 2 to a power
x = 'Spam!'
print(x * 8)                # String repetition

This file is our first official Python script (not counting the two-liner in Chapter 2). You shouldn’t worry too much about this file’s code, but as a brief description, this file:

Imports a Python module (libraries of additional tools), to fetch the name of the platform

Runs three print function calls, to display the script’s results

Uses a variable named x, created when it’s assigned, to hold onto a string object

Applies various object operations that we’ll begin studying in the next chapter

The sys.platform here is just a string that identifies the kind of computer you’re working on; it lives in a standard Python module called sys, which you must import to load (again, more on imports later).

For color, I’ve also added some formal Python comments here—the text after the # characters. Comments can show up on lines by themselves, or to the right of code on a line. The text after a # is simply ignored as a human-readable comment and is not considered part of the statement’s syntax. If you’re copying this code, you can ignore the comments as well. In this book, we usually use a different formatting style to make comments more visually distinctive, but they’ll appear as normal text in your code.

Again, don’t focus on the syntax of the code in this file for now; we’ll learn about all of it later. The main point to notice is that you’ve typed this code into a file, rather than at the interactive prompt. In the process, you’ve coded a fully functional Python script.

Notice that the module file is called script1.py. As for all top-level files, it could also be called simply script, but files of code you want to import into a client have to end with a .py suffix. We’ll study imports later in this chapter. Because you may want to import them in the future, it’s a good idea to use .py suffixes for most Python files that you code. Also, some text editors detect Python files by their .py suffix; if the suffix is not present, you may not get features like syntax colorization and automatic indentation.

Running Files with Command Lines

Once you’ve saved this text file, you can ask Python to run it by listing its full filename as the first argument to a python command, typed at the system shell prompt:

% python script1.py
win32
1267650600228229401496703205376
Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!

Again, you can type such a system shell command in whatever your system provides for command-line entry—a Windows Command Prompt window, an xterm window, or similar. Remember to replace “python” with a full directory path, as before, if your PATH setting is not configured.

If all works as planned, this shell command makes Python run the code in this file line by line, and you will see the output of the script’s three print statements—the name of the underlying platform, 2 raised to the power 100, and the result of the same string repetition expression we saw earlier (again, more on the last two of these in Chapter 4).

If all didn’t work as planned, you’ll get an error message—make sure you’ve entered the code in your file exactly as shown, and try again. We’ll talk about debugging options in the sidebar Debugging Python Code, but at this point in the book your best bet is probably rote imitation.

Because this scheme uses shell command lines to start Python programs, all the usual shell syntax applies. For instance, you can route the output of a Python script to a file to save it for later use or inspection by using special shell syntax:

% python script1.py > saveit.txt

In this case, the three output lines shown in the prior run are stored in the file saveit.txt instead of being printed. This is generally known as stream redirection; it works for input and output text and is available on Windows and Unix-like systems. It also has little to do with Python (Python simply supports it), so we will skip further details on shell redirection syntax here.

If you are working on a Windows platform, this example works the same, but the system prompt is normally different:

C:\Python30> python script1.py
win32
1267650600228229401496703205376
Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!

As usual, be sure to type the full path to Python if you haven’t set your PATH environment variable to include this path or run a change-directory command to go to the path:

D:\temp> C:\python30\python script1.py
win32
1267650600228229401496703205376
Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!

On all recent versions of Windows, you can also type just the name of your script, and omit the name of Python itself. Because newer Windows systems use the Windows Registry to find a program with which to run a file, you don’t need to name “python” on the command line explicitly to run a .py file. The prior command, for example, could be simplified to this on most Windows machines:

D:\temp> script1.py

Finally, remember to give the full path to your script file if it lives in a different directory from the one in which you are working. For example, the following system command line, run from D:\other, assumes Python is in your system path but runs a file located elsewhere:

D:\other> python c:\code\otherscript.py

If your PATH doesn’t include Python’s directory, and neither Python nor your script file is in the directory you’re working in, use full paths for both:

D:\other> C:\Python30\python c:\code\otherscript.py

Using Command Lines and Files

Running program files from system command lines is also a fairly straightforward launch option, especially if you are familiar with command lines in general from prior work. For newcomers, though, here are a few pointers about common beginner traps that might help you avoid some frustration:

Beware of automatic extensions on Windows. If you use the Notepad program to code program files on Windows, be careful to pick the type All Files when it comes time to save your file, and give the file a .py suffix explicitly. Otherwise, Notepad will save your file with a .txt extension (e.g., as script1.py.txt), making it difficult to run in some launching schemes.

Worse, Windows hides file extensions by default, so unless you have changed your view options you may not even notice that you’ve coded a text file and not a Python file. The file’s icon may give this away—if it doesn’t have a snake on it, you may have trouble. Uncolored code in IDLE and files that open to edit instead of run when clicked are other symptoms of this problem.

Microsoft Word similarly adds a .doc extension by default; much worse, it adds formatting characters that are not legal Python syntax. As a rule of thumb, always pick All Files when saving under Windows, or use a more programmer-friendly text editor such as IDLE. IDLE does not even add a .py suffix automatically—a feature programmers tend to like, but users do not.

Use file extensions and directory paths at system prompts, but not for imports. Don’t forget to type the full name of your file in system command lines—that is, use python script1.py rather than python script1. By contrast, Python’s import statements, which we’ll meet later in this chapter, omit both the .py file suffix and the directory path (e.g., import script1). This may seem trivial, but confusing these two is a common mistake.

At the system prompt, you are in a system shell, not Python, so Python’s module file search rules do not apply. Because of that, you must include both the .py extension and, if necessary, the full directory path leading to the file you wish to run. For instance, to run a file that resides in a different directory from the one in which you are working, you would typically list its full path (e.g., python d:\tests\spam.py). Within Python code, however, you can just say import spam and rely on the Python module search path to locate your file, as described later.

Use print statements in files. Yes, we’ve already been over this, but it is such a common mistake that it’s worth repeating at least once here. Unlike in interactive coding, you generally must use print statements to see output from program files. If you don’t see any output, make sure you’ve said “print” in your file. Again, though, print statements are not required in an interactive session, since Python automatically echoes expression results; prints don’t hurt here, but are superfluous extra typing.

Unix Executable Scripts (#!)

If you are going to use Python on a Unix, Linux, or Unix-like system, you can also turn files of Python code into executable programs, much as you would for programs coded in a shell language such as csh or ksh. Such files are usually called executable scripts. In simple terms, Unix-style executable scripts are just normal text files containing Python statements, but with two special properties:

Their first line is special. Scripts usually start with a line that begins with the characters #! (often called “hash bang”), followed by the path to the Python interpreter on your machine.

They usually have executable privileges. Script files are usually marked as executable to tell the operating system that they may be run as top-level programs. On Unix systems, a command such as chmod +x file.py usually does the trick.

Let’s look at an example for Unix-like systems. Use your text editor again to create a file of Python code called brian:

#!/usr/local/bin/python
print('The Bright Side ' + 'of Life...')        # + means concatenate for strings

The special line at the top of the file tells the system where the Python interpreter lives. Technically, the first line is a Python comment. As mentioned earlier, all comments in Python programs start with a # and span to the end of the line; they are a place to insert extra information for human readers of your code. But when a comment such as the first line in this file appears, it’s special because the operating system uses it to find an interpreter for running the program code in the rest of the file.

Also, note that this file is called simply brian, without the .py suffix used for the module file earlier. Adding a .py to the name wouldn’t hurt (and might help you remember that this is a Python program file), but because you don’t plan on letting other modules import the code in this file, the name of the file is irrelevant. If you give the file executable privileges with a chmod +x brian shell command, you can run it from the operating system shell as though it were a binary program:

% brian
The Bright Side of Life...

A note for Windows users: the method described here is a Unix trick, and it may not work on your platform. Not to worry; just use the basic command-line technique explored earlier. List the file’s name on an explicit python command line:[5]

C:\misc> python brian
The Bright Side of Life...

In this case, you don’t need the special #! comment at the top (although Python just ignores it if it’s present), and the file doesn’t need to be given executable privileges. In fact, if you want to run files portably between Unix and Microsoft Windows, your life will probably be simpler if you always use the basic command-line approach, not Unix-style scripts, to launch programs.

The Unix env Lookup Trick

On some Unix systems, you can avoid hardcoding the path to the Python interpreter by writing the special first-line comment like this:

#!/usr/bin/env python
...script goes here...

When coded this way, the env program locates the Python interpreter according to your system search path settings (i.e., in most Unix shells, by looking in all the directories listed in the PATH environment variable). This scheme can be more portable, as you don’t need to hardcode a Python install path in the first line of all your scripts.

Provided you have access to env everywhere, your scripts will run no matter where Python lives on your system—you need only change the PATH environment variable settings across platforms, not in the first line in all your scripts. Of course, this assumes that env lives in the same place everywhere (on some machines, it may be in /sbin, /bin, or elsewhere); if not, all portability bets are off!

Module Imports and Reloads

So far, I’ve been talking about “importing modules” without really explaining what this term means. We’ll study modules and larger program architecture in depth in Part V, but because imports are also a way to launch programs, this section will introduce enough module basics to get you started.

In simple terms, every file of Python source code whose name ends in a .py extension is a module. Other files can access the items a module defines by importing that module; import operations essentially load another file and grant access to that file’s contents. The contents of a module are made available to the outside world through its attributes (a term I’ll define in the next section).

This module-based services model turns out to be the core idea behind program architecture in Python. Larger programs usually take the form of multiple module files, which import tools from other module files. One of the modules is designated as the main or top-level file, and this is the one launched to start the entire program.

We’ll delve into such architectural issues in more detail later in this book. This chapter is mostly interested in the fact that import operations run the code in a file that is being loaded as a final step. Because of this, importing a file is yet another way to launch it.

For instance, if you start an interactive session (from a system command line, from the Start menu, from IDLE, or otherwise), you can run the script1.py file you created earlier with a simple import (be sure to delete the input line you added in the prior section first, or you’ll need to press Enter for no reason):

C:\misc> c:\python30\python
>>> import script1
win32
1267650600228229401496703205376
Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!

This works, but only once per session (really, process) by default. After the first import, later imports do nothing, even if you change and save the module’s source file again in another window:

>>> import script1
>>> import script1

This is by design; imports are too expensive an operation to repeat more than once per file, per program run. As you’ll learn in Chapter 21, imports must find files, compile them to byte code, and run the code.

If you really want to force Python to run the file again in the same session without stopping and restarting the session, you need to instead call the reload function available in the imp standard library module (this function is also a simple built-in in Python 2.6, but not in 3.0):

>>> from imp import reload           # Must load from module in 3.0
>>> reload(script1)
win32
65536
Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!
<module 'script1' from 'script1.py'>
>>>

The from statement here simply copies a name out of a module (more on this soon). The reload function itself loads and runs the current version of your file’s code, picking up changes if you’ve changed and saved it in another window.

This allows you to edit and pick up new code on the fly within the current Python interactive session. In this session, for example, the second print statement in script1.py was changed in another window to print 2 ** 16 between the time of the first import and the reload call.

The reload function expects the name of an already loaded module object, so you have to have successfully imported a module once before you reload it. Notice that reload also expects parentheses around the module object name, whereas import does not. reload is a function that is called, and import is a statement.

That’s why you must pass the module name to reload as an argument in parentheses, and that’s why you get back an extra output line when reloading. The last output line is just the display representation of the reload call’s return value, a Python module object. We’ll learn more about using functions in general in Chapter 16.

Note

Version skew note: Python 3.0 moved the reload built-in function to the imp standard library module. It still reloads files as before, but you must import it in order to use it. In 3.0, run an import imp and use imp.reload(M), or run a from imp import reload and use reload(M), as shown here. We’ll discuss import and from statements in the next section, and more formally later in this book.

If you are working in Python 2.6 (or 2.X in general), reload is available as a built-in function, so no import is required. In Python 2.6, reload is available in both forms—built-in and module function—to aid the transition to 3.0. In other words, reloading is still available in 3.0, but an extra line of code is required to fetch the reload call.

The move in 3.0 was likely motivated in part by some well-known issues involving reload and from statements that we’ll encounter in the next section. In short, names loaded with a from are not directly updated by a reload, but names accessed with an import statement are. If your names don’t seem to change after a reload, try using import and module.attribute name references instead.

The Grander Module Story: Attributes

Imports and reloads provide a natural program launch option because import operations execute files as a last step. In the broader scheme of things, though, modules serve the role of libraries of tools, as you’ll learn in Part V. More generally, a module is mostly just a package of variable names, known as a namespace. The names within that package are called attributes—an attribute is simply a variable name that is attached to a specific object (like a module).

In typical use, importers gain access to all the names assigned at the top level of a module’s file. These names are usually assigned to tools exported by the module—functions, classes, variables, and so on—that are intended to be used in other files and other programs. Externally, a module file’s names can be fetched with two Python statements, import and from, as well as the reload call.

To illustrate, use a text editor to create a one-line Python module file called myfile.py with the following contents:

title = "The Meaning of Life"

This may be one of the world’s simplest Python modules (it contains a single assignment statement), but it’s enough to illustrate the point. When this file is imported, its code is run to generate the module’s attribute. The assignment statement creates a module attribute named title.

You can access this module’s title attribute in other components in two different ways. First, you can load the module as a whole with an import statement, and then qualify the module name with the attribute name to fetch it:

% python                           # Start Python
>>> import myfile                  # Run file; load module as a whole
>>> print(myfile.title)            # Use its attribute names: '.' to qualify
The Meaning of Life

In general, the dot expression syntax object.attribute lets you fetch any attribute attached to any object, and this is a very common operation in Python code. Here, we’ve used it to access the string variable title inside the module myfile—in other words, myfile.title.

Alternatively, you can fetch (really, copy) names out of a module with from statements:

% python                           # Start Python
>>> from myfile import title       # Run file; copy its names
>>> print(title)                   # Use name directly: no need to qualify
The Meaning of Life

As you’ll see in more detail later, from is just like an import, with an extra assignment to names in the importing component. Technically, from copies a module’s attributes, such that they become simple variables in the recipient—thus, you can simply refer to the imported string this time as title (a variable) instead of myfile.title (an attribute reference).[7]

Whether you use import or from to invoke an import operation, the statements in the module file myfile.py are executed, and the importing component (here, the interactive prompt) gains access to names assigned at the top level of the file. There’s only one such name in this simple example—the variable title, assigned to a string—but the concept will be more useful when you start defining objects such as functions and classes in your modules: such objects become reusable software components that can be accessed by name from one or more client modules.

In practice, module files usually define more than one name to be used in and outside the files. Here’s an example that defines three:

a = 'dead'                      # Define three attributes
b = 'parrot'                    # Exported to other files
c = 'sketch'
print(a, b, c)                  # Also used in this file

This file, threenames.py, assigns three variables, and so generates three attributes for the outside world. It also uses its own three variables in a print statement, as we see when we run this as a top-level file:

% python threenames.py
dead parrot sketch

All of this file’s code runs as usual the first time it is imported elsewhere (by either an import or from). Clients of this file that use import get a module with attributes, while clients that use from get copies of the file’s names:

% python
>>> import threenames                    # Grab the whole module
dead parrot sketch
>>>
>>> threenames.b, threenames.c
('parrot', 'sketch')
>>>
>>> from threenames import a, b, c       # Copy multiple names
>>> b, c
('parrot', 'sketch')

The results here are printed in parentheses because they are really tuples (a kind of object covered in the next part of this book); you can safely ignore them for now.

Once you start coding modules with multiple names like this, the built-in dir function starts to come in handy—you can use it to fetch a list of the names available inside a module. The following returns a Python list of strings (we’ll start studying lists in the next chapter):

>>> dir(threenames)
['__builtins__', '__doc__', '__file__', '__name__', '__package__', 'a', 'b', 'c']

I ran this on Python 3.0 and 2.6; older Pythons may return fewer names. When the dir function is called with the name of an imported module passed in parentheses like this, it returns all the attributes inside that module. Some of the names it returns are names you get “for free”: names with leading and trailing double underscores are built-in names that are always predefined by Python and that have special meaning to the interpreter. The variables our code defined by assignment—a, b, and c—show up last in the dir result.

Modules and namespaces

Module imports are a way to run files of code, but, as we’ll discuss later in the book, modules are also the largest program structure in Python programs.

In general, Python programs are composed of multiple module files, linked together by import statements. Each module file is a self-contained package of variables—that is, a namespace. One module file cannot see the names defined in another file unless it explicitly imports that other file, so modules serve to minimize name collisions in your code—because each file is a self-contained namespace, the names in one file cannot clash with those in another, even if they are spelled the same way.

In fact, as you’ll see, modules are one of a handful of ways that Python goes to great lengths to package your variables into compartments to avoid name clashes. We’ll discuss modules and other namespace constructs (including classes and function scopes) further later in the book. For now, modules will come in handy as a way to run your code many times without having to retype it.

Note

import versus from: I should point out that the from statement in a sense defeats the namespace partitioning purpose of modules—because the from copies variables from one file to another, it can cause same-named variables in the importing file to be overwritten (and won’t warn you if it does). This essentially collapses namespaces together, at least in terms of the copied variables.

Because of this, some recommend using import instead of from. I won’t go that far, though; not only does from involve less typing, but its purported problem is rarely an issue in practice. Besides, this is something you control by listing the variables you want in the from; as long as you understand that they’ll be assigned values, this is no more dangerous than coding assignment statements—another feature you’ll probably want to use!

import and reload Usage Notes

For some reason, once people find out about running files using import and reload, many tend to focus on this alone and forget about other launch options that always run the current version of the code (e.g., icon clicks, IDLE menu options, and system command lines). This approach can quickly lead to confusion, though—you need to remember when you’ve imported to know if you can reload, you need to remember to use parentheses when you call reload (only), and you need to remember to use reload in the first place to get the current version of your code to run. Moreover, reloads aren’t transitive—reloading a module reloads that module only, not any modules it may import—so you sometimes have to reload multiple files.

Because of these complications (and others we’ll explore later, including the reload/from issue mentioned in a prior note in this chapter), it’s generally a good idea to avoid the temptation to launch by imports and reloads for now. The IDLE Run→Run Module menu option described in the next section, for example, provides a simpler and less error-prone way to run your files, and always runs the current version of your code. System shell command lines offer similar benefits. You don’t need to use reload if you use these techniques.

In addition, you may run into trouble if you use modules in unusual ways at this point in the book. For instance, if you want to import a module file that is stored in a directory other than the one you’re working in, you’ll have to skip ahead to Chapter 21 and learn about the module search path.

For now, if you must import, try to keep all your files in the directory you are working in to avoid complications.[8]

That said, imports and reloads have proven to be a popular testing technique in Python classes, and you may prefer using this approach too. As usual, though, if you find yourself running into a wall, stop running into a wall!

Using exec to Run Module Files

In fact, there are more ways to run code stored in module files than have yet been exposed here. For instance, the exec(open('module.py').read()) built-in function call is another way to launch files from the interactive prompt without having to import and later reload. Each exec runs the current version of the file, without requiring later reloads (script1.py is as we left it after a reload in the prior section):

C:\misc> c:\python30\python
>>> exec(open('script1.py').read())
win32
65536
Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!

...change script1.py in a text edit window...

>>> exec(open('script1.py').read())
win32
4294967296
Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!Spam!

The exec call has an effect similar to an import, but it doesn’t technically import the module—by default, each time you call exec this way it runs the file anew, as though you had pasted it in at the place where exec is called. Because of that, exec does not require module reloads after file changes—it skips the normal module import logic.

On the downside, because it works as if pasting code into the place where it is called, exec, like the from statement mentioned earlier, has the potential to silently overwrite variables you may currently be using. For example, our script1.py assigns to a variable named x. If that name is also being used in the place where exec is called, the name’s value is replaced:

>>> x = 999
>>> exec(open('script1.py').read())     # Code run in this namespace by default
...same output...
>>> x                                   # Its assignments can overwrite names here
'Spam!'

By contrast, the basic import statement runs the file only once per process, and it makes the file a separate module namespace so that its assignments will not change variables in your scope. The price you pay for the namespace partitioning of modules is the need to reload after changes.

Note

Version skew note: Python 2.6 also includes an execfile('module.py') built-in function, in addition to allowing the form exec(open('module.py')), which both automatically read the file’s content. Both of these are equivalent to the exec(open('module.py').read()) form, which is more complex but runs in both 2.6 and 3.0.

Unfortunately, neither of these two simpler 2.6 forms is available in 3.0, which means you must understand both files and their read methods to fully understand this technique today (alas, this seems to be a case of aesthetics trouncing practicality in 3.0). In fact, the exec form in 3.0 involves so much typing that the best advice may simply be not to do it—it’s usually best to launch files by typing system shell command lines or by using the IDLE menu options described in the next section. For more on the file interfaces used by the 3.0 exec form, see Chapter 9.

Other IDEs

Because IDLE is free, portable, and a standard part of Python, it’s a nice first development tool to become familiar with if you want to use an IDE at all. Again, I recommend that you use IDLE for this book’s exercises if you’re just starting out, unless you are already familiar with and prefer a command-line-based development mode. There are, however, a handful of alternative IDEs for Python developers, some of which are substantially more powerful and robust than IDLE. Here are some of the most commonly used IDEs:

Eclipse and PyDev

Eclipse is an advanced open source IDE GUI. Originally developed as a Java IDE, Eclipse also supports Python development when you install the PyDev (or a similar) plug-in. Eclipse is a popular and powerful option for Python development, and it goes well beyond IDLE’s feature set. It includes support for code completion, syntax highlighting, syntax analysis, refactoring, debugging, and more. Its downsides are that it is a large system to install and may require shareware extensions for some features (this may vary over time). Still, when you are ready to graduate from IDLE, the Eclipse/PyDev combination is worth your attention.

Komodo

A full-featured development environment GUI for Python (and other languages), Komodo includes standard syntax-coloring, text-editing, debugging, and other features. In addition, Komodo offers many advanced features that IDLE does not, including project files, source-control integration, regular-expression debugging, and a drag-and-drop GUI builder that generates Python/tkinter code to implement the GUIs you design interactively. At this writing, Komodo is not free; it is available at http://www.activestate.com.

NetBeans IDE for Python

NetBeans is a powerful open-source development environment GUI with support for many advanced features for Python developers: code completion, automatic indentation and code colorization, editor hints, code folding, refactoring, debugging, code coverage and testing, projects, and more. It may be used to develop both CPython and Jython code. Like Eclipse, NetBeans requires installation steps beyond those of the included IDLE GUI, but it is seen by many as more than worth the effort. Search the Web for the latest information and links.

PythonWin

PythonWin is a free Windows-only IDE for Python that ships as part of ActiveState’s ActivePython distribution (and may also be fetched separately from http://www.python.org resources). It is roughly like IDLE, with a handful of useful Windows-specific extensions added; for example, PythonWin has support for COM objects. Today, IDLE is probably more advanced than PythonWin (for instance, IDLE’s dual-process architecture often prevents it from hanging). However, PythonWin still offers tools for Windows developers that IDLE does not. See http://www.activestate.com for more information.

Others

There are roughly half a dozen other widely used IDEs that I’m aware of (including the commercial Wing IDE and PythonCard) but do not have space to do justice to here, and more will probably appear over time. In fact, almost every programmer-friendly text editor has some sort of support for Python development these days, whether it be preinstalled or fetched separately. Emacs and Vim, for instance, have substantial Python support.

I won’t try to document all such options here; for more information, see the resources available at http://www.python.org or search the Web for “Python IDE.” You might also try running a web search for “Python editors”—today, this leads you to a wiki page that maintains information about many IDE and text-editor options for Python programming.

Other Launch Options

At this point, we’ve seen how to run code typed interactively, and how to launch code saved in files in a variety of ways—system command lines, imports and execs, GUIs like IDLE, and more. That covers most of the cases you’ll see in this book. There are additional ways to run Python code, though, most of which have special or narrow roles. The next few sections take a quick look at some of these.

Embedding Calls

In some specialized domains, Python code may be run automatically by an enclosing system. In such cases, we say that the Python programs are embedded in (i.e., run by) another program. The Python code itself may be entered into a text file, stored in a database, fetched from an HTML page, parsed from an XML document, and so on. But from an operational perspective, another system—not you—may tell Python to run the code you’ve created.

Such an embedded execution mode is commonly used to support end-user customization—a game program, for instance, might allow for play modifications by running user-accessible embedded Python code at strategic points in time. Users can modify this type of system by providing or changing Python code. Because Python code is interpreted, there is no need to recompile the entire system to incorporate the change (see Chapter 2 for more on how Python code is run).

In this mode, the enclosing system that runs your code might be written in C, C++, or even Java when the Jython system is used. As an example, it’s possible to create and run strings of Python code from a C program by calling functions in the Python runtime API (a set of services exported by the libraries created when Python is compiled on your machine):

#include <Python.h>
...
Py_Initialize();                                     // This is C, not Python
PyRun_SimpleString("x = 'brave ' + 'sir robin'");    // But it runs Python code

In this C code snippet, a program coded in the C language embeds the Python interpreter by linking in its libraries, and passes it a Python assignment statement string to run. C programs may also gain access to Python modules and objects and process or execute them using other Python API tools.

This book isn’t about Python/C integration, but you should be aware that, depending on how your organization plans to use Python, you may or may not be the one who actually starts the Python programs you create. Regardless, you can usually still use the interactive and file-based launching techniques described here to test code in isolation from those enclosing systems that may eventually use it.[11]

Frozen Binary Executables

Frozen binary executables, described in Chapter 2, are packages that combine your program’s byte code and the Python interpreter into a single executable program. This approach enables Python programs to be launched in the same ways that you would launch any other executable program (icon clicks, command lines, etc.). While this option works well for delivery of products, it is not really intended for use during program development; you normally freeze just before shipping (after development is finished). See the prior chapter for more on this option.

Text Editor Launch Options

As mentioned previously, although they’re not full-blown IDE GUIs, most programmer-friendly text editors have support for editing, and possibly running, Python programs. Such support may be built in or fetchable on the Web. For instance, if you are familiar with the Emacs text editor, you can do all your Python editing and launching from inside that text editor. See the text editor resources page at http://www.python.org/editors for more details, or search the Web for the phrase “Python editors.”

Still Other Launch Options

Depending on your platform, there may be additional ways that you can start Python programs. For instance, on some Macintosh systems you may be able to drag Python program file icons onto the Python interpreter icon to make them execute, and on Windows you can always start Python scripts with the Run... option in the Start menu. Additionally, the Python standard library has utilities that allow Python programs to be started by other Python programs in separate processes (e.g., os.popen, os.system), and Python scripts might also be spawned in larger contexts like the Web (for instance, a web page might invoke a script on a server); however, these are beyond the scope of the present chapter.

Future Possibilities?

This chapter reflects current practice, but much of the material is both platform- and time-specific. Indeed, many of the execution and launch details presented arose during the shelf life of this book’s various editions. As with program execution options, it’s not impossible that new program launch options may arise over time.

New operating systems, and new versions of existing systems, may also provide execution techniques beyond those outlined here. In general, because Python keeps pace with such changes, you should be able to launch Python programs in whatever way makes sense for the machines you use, both now and in the future—be that by drawing on tablet PCs or PDAs, grabbing icons in a virtual reality, or shouting a script’s name over your coworkers’ conversations.

Implementation changes may also impact launch schemes somewhat (e.g., a full compiler could produce normal executables that are launched much like frozen binaries today). If I knew what the future truly held, though, I would probably be talking to a stockbroker instead of writing these words!

Which Option Should I Use?

With all these options, one question naturally arises: which one is best for me? In general, you should give the IDLE interface a try if you are just getting started with Python. It provides a user-friendly GUI environment and hides some of the underlying configuration details. It also comes with a platform-neutral text editor for coding your scripts, and it’s a standard and free part of the Python system.

If, on the other hand, you are an experienced programmer, you might be more comfortable with simply the text editor of your choice in one window, and another window for launching the programs you edit via system command lines and icon clicks (in fact, this is how I develop Python programs, but I have a Unix-biased past). Because the choice of development environments is very subjective, I can’t offer much more in the way of universal guidelines; in general, whatever environment you like to use will be the best for you to use.

Debugging Python Code

Naturally, none of my readers or students ever have bugs in their code (insert smiley here), but for less fortunate friends of yours who may, here’s a quick look at the strategies commonly used by real-world Python programmers to debug code:

Do nothing. By this, I don’t mean that Python programmers don’t debug their code—but when you make a mistake in a Python program, you get a very useful and readable error message (you’ll get to see some soon, if you haven’t already). If you already know Python, and especially for your own code, this is often enough—read the error message, and go fix the tagged line and file. For many, this is debugging in Python. It may not always be ideal for larger system you didn’t write, though.

Insert print statements. Probably the main way that Python programmers debug their code (and the way that I debug Python code) is to insert print statements and run again. Because Python runs immediately after changes, this is usually the quickest way to get more information than error messages provide. The print statements don’t have to be sophisticated—a simple “I am here” or display of variable values is usually enough to provide the context you need. Just remember to delete or comment out (i.e., add a # before) the debugging prints before you ship your code!

Use IDE GUI debuggers. For larger systems you didn’t write, and for beginners who want to trace code in more detail, most Python development GUIs have some sort of point-and-click debugging support. IDLE has a debugger too, but it doesn’t appear to be used very often in practice—perhaps because it has no command line, or perhaps because adding print statements is usually quicker than setting up a GUI debugging session. To learn more, see IDLE’s Help, or simply try it on your own; its basic interface is described in the section Advanced IDLE Tools. Other IDEs, such as Eclipse, NetBeans, Komodo, and Wing IDE, offer advanced point-and-click debuggers as well; see their documentation if you use them.

Use the pdb command-line debugger. For ultimate control, Python comes with a source-code debugger named pdb, available as a module in Python’s standard library. In pdb, you type commands to step line by line, display variables, set and clear breakpoints, continue to a breakpoint or error, and so on. pdb can be launched interactively by importing it, or as a top-level script. Either way, because you can type commands to control the session, it provides a powerful debugging tool. pdb also includes a postmortem function you can run after an exception occurs, to get information from the time of the error. See the Python library manual and Chapter 35 for more details on pdb.

Other options. For more specific debugging requirements, you can find additional tools in the open source domain, including support for multithreaded programs, embedded code, and process attachment. The Winpdb system, for example, is a standalone debugger with advanced debugging support and cross-platform GUI and console interfaces.

These options will become more important as we start writing larger scripts. Probably the best news on the debugging front, though, is that errors are detected and reported in Python, rather than passing silently or crashing the system altogether. In fact, errors themselves are a well-defined mechanism known as exceptions, which you can catch and process (more on exceptions in Part VII). Making mistakes is never fun, of course, but speaking as someone who recalls when debugging meant getting out a hex calculator and poring over piles of memory dump printouts, Python’s debugging support makes errors much less painful than they might otherwise be.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

You can start an interactive session on Windows by clicking your Start button, picking the All Programs option, clicking the Python entry, and selecting the “Python (command line)” menu option. You can also achieve the same effect on Windows and other platforms by typing python as a system command line in your system’s console window (a Command Prompt window on Windows). Another alternative is to launch IDLE, as its main Python shell window is an interactive session. If you have not set your system’s PATH variable to find Python, you may need to cd to where Python is installed, or type its full directory path instead of just python (e.g., C:\Python30\python on Windows).

You type system command lines in whatever your platform provides as a system console: a Command Prompt window on Windows; an xterm or terminal window on Unix, Linux, and Mac OS X; and so on.

Code in a script (really, module) file can be run with system command lines, file icon clicks, imports and reloads, the exec built-in function, and IDE GUI selections such as IDLE’s Run→Run Module menu option. On Unix, they can also be run as executables with the #! trick, and some platforms support more specialized launching techniques (e.g., drag-and-drop). In addition, some text editors have unique ways to run Python code, some Python programs are provided as standalone “frozen binary” executables, and some systems use Python code in embedded mode, where it is run automatically by an enclosing program written in a language like C, C++, or Java. The latter technique is usually done to provide a user customization layer.

Scripts that print and then exit cause the output file to disappear immediately, before you can view the output (which is why the input trick comes in handy); error messages generated by your script also appear in an output window that closes before you can examine its contents (which is one reason that system command lines and IDEs such as IDLE are better for most development).

Python only imports (loads) a module once per process, by default, so if you’ve changed its source code and want to run the new version without stopping and restarting Python, you’ll have to reload it. You must import a module at least once before you can reload it. Running files of code from a system shell command line, via an icon click, or via an IDE such as IDLE generally makes this a nonissue, as those launch schemes usually run the current version of the source code file each time.

Within the text edit window of the file you wish to run, select the window’s Run→Run Module menu option. This runs the window’s source code as a top-level script file and displays its output back in the interactive Python shell window.

IDLE can still be hung by some types of programs—especially GUI programs that perform multithreading (an advanced technique beyond this book’s scope). Also, IDLE has some usability features that can burn you once you leave the IDLE GUI: a script’s variables are automatically imported to the interactive scope in IDLE, for instance, but not by Python in general.

A namespace is just a package of variables (i.e., names). It takes the form of an object with attributes in Python. Each module file is automatically a namespace—that is, a package of variables reflecting the assignments made at the top level of the file. Namespaces help avoid name collisions in Python programs: because each module file is a self-contained namespace, files must explicitly import other files in order to use their names.

Test Your Knowledge: Part I Exercises

It’s time to start doing a little coding on your own. This first exercise session is fairly simple, but a few of these questions hint at topics to come in later chapters. Be sure to check Part I, Getting Started in the solutions appendix (Appendix B) for the answers; the exercises and their solutions sometimes contain supplemental information not discussed in the main text, so you should take a peek at the solutions even if you manage to answer all the questions on your own.

Interaction. Using a system command line, IDLE, or another method, start the Python interactive command line (>>> prompt), and type the expression "Hello World!" (including the quotes). The string should be echoed back to you. The purpose of this exercise is to get your environment configured to run Python. In some scenarios, you may need to first run a cd shell command, type the full path to the Python executable, or add its path to your PATH environment variable. If desired, you can set PATH in your .cshrc or .kshrc file to make Python permanently available on Unix systems; on Windows, use a setup.bat, autoexec.bat, or the environment variable GUI. See Appendix A for help with environment variable settings.

Programs. With the text editor of your choice, write a simple module file containing the single statement print('Hello module world!') and store it as module1.py. Now, run this file by using any launch option you like: running it in IDLE, clicking on its file icon, passing it to the Python interpreter on the system shell’s command line (e.g., python module1.py), built-in exec calls, imports and reloads, and so on. In fact, experiment by running your file with as many of the launch techniques discussed in this chapter as you can. Which technique seems easiest? (There is no right answer to this, of course.)

Modules. Start the Python interactive command line (>>> prompt) and import the module you wrote in exercise 2. Try moving the file to a different directory and importing it again from its original directory (i.e., run Python in the original directory when you import). What happens? (Hint: is there still a module1.pyc byte code file in the original directory?)

Scripts. If your platform supports it, add the #! line to the top of your module1.py module file, give the file executable privileges, and run it directly as an executable. What does the first line need to contain? #! usually only has meaning on Unix, Linux, and Unix-like platforms such as Mac OS X; if you’re working on Windows, instead try running your file by listing just its name in a DOS console window without the word “python” before it (this works on recent versions of Windows), or via the Start→Run... dialog box.

Errors and debugging. Experiment with typing mathematical expressions and assignments at the Python interactive command line. Along the way, type the expressions 2 ** 500 and 1 / 0, and reference an undefined variable name as we did in this chapter. What happens?

You may not know it yet, but when you make a mistake, you’re doing exception processing (a topic we’ll explore in depth in Part VII). As you’ll learn there, you are technically triggering what’s known as the default exception handler—logic that prints a standard error message. If you do not catch an error, the default handler does and prints the standard error message in response.

Exceptions are also bound up with the notion of debugging in Python. When you’re first starting out, Python’s default error messages on exceptions will probably provide as much error-handling support as you need—they give the cause of the error, as well as showing the lines in your code that were active when the error occurred. For more about debugging, see the sidebar Debugging Python Code.

Breaks and cycles. At the Python command line, type:

L = [1, 2]              # Make a 2-item list
L.append(L)             # Append L as a single item to itself
L                       # Print L

What happens? In all recent versions of Python, you’ll see a strange output that we’ll describe in the solutions appendix, and which will make more sense when we study references in the next part of the book. If you’re using a Python version older than 1.5.1, a Ctrl-C key combination will probably help on most platforms. Why do you think your version of Python responds the way it does for this code?

Warning

If you do have a Python older than Release 1.5.1 (a hopefully rare scenario today!), make sure your machine can stop a program with a Ctrl-C key combination of some sort before running this test, or you may be waiting a long time.

Documentation. Spend at least 17 minutes browsing the Python library and language manuals before moving on to get a feel for the available tools in the standard library and the structure of the documentation set. It takes at least this long to become familiar with the locations of major topics in the manual set; once you’ve done this, it’s easy to find what you need. You can find this manual via the Python Start button entry on Windows, in the Python Docs option on the Help pull-down menu in IDLE, or online at http://www.python.org/doc. I’ll also have a few more words to say about the manuals and other documentation sources available (including PyDoc and the help function) in Chapter 15. If you still have time, go explore the Python website, as well as its PyPI third-party extension repository. Especially check out the Python.org documentation and search pages; they can be crucial resources.

[5] As we discussed when exploring command lines, modern Windows versions also let you type just the name of a .py file at the system command line—they use the Registry to determine that the file should be opened with Python (e.g., typing brian.py is equivalent to typing python brian.py). This command-line mode is similar in spirit to the Unix #!, though it is system-wide on Windows, not per-file. Note that some programs may actually interpret and use a first #! line on Windows much like on Unix, but the DOS system shell on Windows simply ignores it.

[6] It is also possible to completely suppress the pop-up DOS console window for clicked files on Windows. Files whose names end in a .pyw extension will display only windows constructed by your script, not the default DOS console window. .pyw files are simply .py source files that have this special operational behavior on Windows. They are mostly used for Python-coded user interfaces that build windows of their own, often in conjunction with various techniques for saving printed output and errors to files.

[7] Notice that import and from both list the name of the module file as simply myfile without its .py suffix. As you’ll learn in Part V, when Python looks for the actual file, it knows to include the suffix in its search procedure. Again, you must include the .py suffix in system shell command lines, but not in import statements.

[8] If you’re burning with curiosity, the short story is that Python searches for imported modules in every directory listed in sys.path—a Python list of directory name strings in the sys module, which is initialized from a PYTHONPATH environment variable, plus a set of standard directories. If you want to import from a directory other than the one you are working in, that directory must generally be listed in your PYTHONPATH setting. For more details, see Chapter 21.

[9] IDLE is officially a corruption of IDE, but it’s really named in honor of Monty Python member Eric Idle.

[10] IDLE is a Python program that uses the standard library’s tkinter GUI toolkit (a.k.a. Tkinter in Python 2.6) to build the IDLE GUI. This makes IDLE portable, but it also means that you’ll need to have tkinter support in your Python to use IDLE. The Windows version of Python has this by default, but some Linux and Unix users may need to install the appropriate tkinter support (a yum tkinter command may suffice on some Linux distributions, but see the installation hints in Appendix A for details). Mac OS X may have everything you need preinstalled, too; look for an idle command or script on your machine.

[11] See Programming Python (O’Reilly) for more details on embedding Python in C/C++. The embedding API can call Python functions directly, load modules, and more. Also, note that the Jython system allows Java programs to invoke Python code using a Java-based API (a Python interpreter class).

Chapter 4. Introducing Python Object Types

This chapter begins our tour of the Python language. In an informal sense, in Python, we do things with stuff. “Things” take the form of operations like addition and concatenation, and “stuff” refers to the objects on which we perform those operations. In this part of the book, our focus is on that stuff, and the things our programs can do with it.

Somewhat more formally, in Python, data takes the form of objects—either built-in objects that Python provides, or objects we create using Python or external language tools such as C extension libraries. Although we’ll firm up this definition later, objects are essentially just pieces of memory, with values and sets of associated operations.

Because objects are the most fundamental notion in Python programming, we’ll start this chapter with a survey of Python’s built-in object types.

By way of introduction, however, let’s first establish a clear picture of how this chapter fits into the overall Python picture. From a more concrete perspective, Python programs can be decomposed into modules, statements, expressions, and objects, as follows:

Programs are composed of modules.

Modules contain statements.

Statements contain expressions.

Expressions create and process objects.

The discussion of modules in Chapter 3 introduced the highest level of this hierarchy. This part’s chapters begin at the bottom, exploring both built-in objects and the expressions you can code to use them.

Why Use Built-in Types?

If you’ve used lower-level languages such as C or C++, you know that much of your work centers on implementing objects—also known as data structures—to represent the components in your application’s domain. You need to lay out memory structures, manage memory allocation, implement search and access routines, and so on. These chores are about as tedious (and error-prone) as they sound, and they usually distract from your program’s real goals.

In typical Python programs, most of this grunt work goes away. Because Python provides powerful object types as an intrinsic part of the language, there’s usually no need to code object implementations before you start solving problems. In fact, unless you have a need for special processing that built-in types don’t provide, you’re almost always better off using a built-in object instead of implementing your own. Here are some reasons why:

Built-in objects make programs easy to write. For simple tasks, built-in types are often all you need to represent the structure of problem domains. Because you get powerful tools such as collections (lists) and search tables (dictionaries) for free, you can use them immediately. You can get a lot of work done with Python’s built-in object types alone.

Built-in objects are components of extensions. For more complex tasks, you may need to provide your own objects using Python classes or C language interfaces. But as you’ll see in later parts of this book, objects implemented manually are often built on top of built-in types such as lists and dictionaries. For instance, a stack data structure may be implemented as a class that manages or customizes a built-in list.

Built-in objects are often more efficient than custom data structures. Python’s built-in types employ already optimized data structure algorithms that are implemented in C for speed. Although you can write similar object types on your own, you’ll usually be hard-pressed to get the level of performance built-in object types provide.

Built-in objects are a standard part of the language. In some ways, Python borrows both from languages that rely on built-in tools (e.g., LISP) and languages that rely on the programmer to provide tool implementations or frameworks of their own (e.g., C++). Although you can implement unique object types in Python, you don’t need to do so just to get started. Moreover, because Python’s built-ins are standard, they’re always the same; proprietary frameworks, on the other hand, tend to differ from site to site.

In other words, not only do built-in object types make programming easier, but they’re also more powerful and efficient than most of what can be created from scratch. Regardless of whether you implement new object types, built-in objects form the core of every Python program.

Python’s Core Data Types

Table 4-1 previews Python’s built-in object types and some of the syntax used to code their literals—that is, the expressions that generate these objects.[12] Some of these types will probably seem familiar if you’ve used other languages; for instance, numbers and strings represent numeric and textual values, respectively, and files provide an interface for processing files stored on your computer.

Table 4-1. Built-in objects preview

Object type

|

Example literals/creation

Numbers

|

1234, 3.1415, 3+4j, Decimal, Fraction

Strings

|

'spam', "guido's", b'a\x01c'

Lists

|

[1, [2, 'three'], 4]

Dictionaries

|

{'food': 'spam', 'taste': 'yum'}

Tuples

|

(1, 'spam', 4, 'U')

Files

|

myfile = open('eggs', 'r')

Sets

|

set('abc'), {'a', 'b', 'c'}

Other core types

|

Booleans, types, None

Program unit types

|

Functions, modules, classes (Part IV, Part V, Part VI)

Implementation-related types

|

Compiled code, stack tracebacks (Part IV, Part VII)

Table 4-1 isn’t really complete, because everything we process in Python programs is a kind of object. For instance, when we perform text pattern matching in Python, we create pattern objects, and when we perform network scripting, we use socket objects. These other kinds of objects are generally created by importing and using modules and have behavior all their own.

As we’ll see in later parts of the book, program units such as functions, modules, and classes are objects in Python too—they are created with statements and expressions such as def, class, import, and lambda and may be passed around scripts freely, stored within other objects, and so on. Python also provides a set of implementation-related types such as compiled code objects, which are generally of interest to tool builders more than application developers; these are also discussed in later parts of this text.

We usually call the other object types in Table 4-1 core data types, though, because they are effectively built into the Python language—that is, there is specific expression syntax for generating most of them. For instance, when you run the following code:

>>> 'spam'

you are, technically speaking, running a literal expression that generates and returns a new string object. There is specific Python language syntax to make this object. Similarly, an expression wrapped in square brackets makes a list, one in curly braces makes a dictionary, and so on. Even though, as we’ll see, there are no type declarations in Python, the syntax of the expressions you run determines the types of objects you create and use. In fact, object-generation expressions like those in Table 4-1 are generally where types originate in the Python language.

Just as importantly, once you create an object, you bind its operation set for all time—you can perform only string operations on a string and list operations on a list. As you’ll learn, Python is dynamically typed (it keeps track of types for you automatically instead of requiring declaration code), but it is also strongly typed (you can perform on an object only operations that are valid for its type).

Functionally, the object types in Table 4-1 are more general and powerful than what you may be accustomed to. For instance, you’ll find that lists and dictionaries alone are powerful data representation tools that obviate most of the work you do to support collections and searching in lower-level languages. In short, lists provide ordered collections of other objects, while dictionaries store objects by key; both lists and dictionaries may be nested, can grow and shrink on demand, and may contain objects of any type.

We’ll study each of the object types in Table 4-1 in detail in upcoming chapters. Before digging into the details, though, let’s begin by taking a quick look at Python’s core objects in action. The rest of this chapter provides a preview of the operations we’ll explore in more depth in the chapters that follow. Don’t expect to find the full story here—the goal of this chapter is just to whet your appetite and introduce some key ideas. Still, the best way to get started is to get started, so let’s jump right into some real code.

Numbers

If you’ve done any programming or scripting in the past, some of the object types in Table 4-1 will probably seem familiar. Even if you haven’t, numbers are fairly straightforward. Python’s core objects set includes the usual suspects: integers (numbers without a fractional part), floating-point numbers (roughly, numbers with a decimal point in them), and more exotic numeric types (complex numbers with imaginary parts, fixed-precision decimals, rational fractions with numerator and denominator, and full-featured sets).

Although it offers some fancier options, Python’s basic number types are, well, basic. Numbers in Python support the normal mathematical operations. For instance, the plus sign (+) performs addition, a star (*) is used for multiplication, and two stars (**) are used for exponentiation:

>>> 123 + 222                    # Integer addition
345
>>> 1.5 * 4                      # Floating-point multiplication
6.0
>>> 2 ** 100                     # 2 to the power 100
1267650600228229401496703205376

Notice the last result here: Python 3.0’s integer type automatically provides extra precision for large numbers like this when needed (in 2.6, a separate long integer type handles numbers too large for the normal integer type in similar ways). You can, for instance, compute 2 to the power 1,000,000 as an integer in Python, but you probably shouldn’t try to print the result—with more than 300,000 digits, you may be waiting awhile!

>>> len(str(2 ** 1000000))       # How many digits in a really BIG number?
301030

Once you start experimenting with floating-point numbers, you’re likely to stumble across something that may look a bit odd on first glance:

>>> 3.1415 * 2                   # repr: as code
6.2830000000000004
>>> print(3.1415 * 2)            # str: user-friendly
6.283

The first result isn’t a bug; it’s a display issue. It turns out that there are two ways to print every object: with full precision (as in the first result shown here), and in a user-friendly form (as in the second). Formally, the first form is known as an object’s as-code repr, and the second is its user-friendly str. The difference can matter when we step up to using classes; for now, if something looks odd, try showing it with a print built-in call statement.

Besides expressions, there are a handful of useful numeric modules that ship with Python—modules are just packages of additional tools that we import to use:

>>> import math
>>> math.pi
3.1415926535897931
>>> math.sqrt(85)
9.2195444572928871

The math module contains more advanced numeric tools as functions, while the random module performs random number generation and random selections (here, from a Python list, introduced later in this chapter):

>>> import random
>>> random.random()
0.59268735266273953
>>> random.choice([1, 2, 3, 4])
1

Python also includes more exotic numeric objects—such as complex, fixed-precision, and rational numbers, as well as sets and Booleans—and the third-party open source extension domain has even more (e.g., matrixes and vectors). We’ll defer discussion of these types until later in the book.

So far, we’ve been using Python much like a simple calculator; to do better justice to its built-in types, let’s move on to explore strings.

Strings

Strings are used to record textual information as well as arbitrary collections of bytes. They are our first example of what we call a sequence in Python—that is, a positionally ordered collection of other objects. Sequences maintain a left-to-right order among the items they contain: their items are stored and fetched by their relative position. Strictly speaking, strings are sequences of one-character strings; other types of sequences include lists and tuples, covered later.

Sequence Operations

As sequences, strings support operations that assume a positional ordering among items. For example, if we have a four-character string, we can verify its length with the built-in len function and fetch its components with indexing expressions:

>>> S = 'Spam'
>>> len(S)               # Length
4
>>> S[0]                 # The first item in S, indexing by zero-based position
'S'
>>> S[1]                 # The second item from the left
'p'

In Python, indexes are coded as offsets from the front, and so start from 0: the first item is at index 0, the second is at index 1, and so on.

Notice how we assign the string to a variable named S here. We’ll go into detail on how this works later (especially in Chapter 6), but Python variables never need to be declared ahead of time. A variable is created when you assign it a value, may be assigned any type of object, and is replaced with its value when it shows up in an expression. It must also have been previously assigned by the time you use its value. For the purposes of this chapter, it’s enough to know that we need to assign an object to a variable in order to save it for later use.

In Python, we can also index backward, from the end—positive indexes count from the left, and negative indexes count back from the right:

>>> S[-1]                # The last item from the end in S
'm'
>>> S[-2]                # The second to last item from the end
'a'

Formally, a negative index is simply added to the string’s size, so the following two operations are equivalent (though the first is easier to code and less easy to get wrong):

>>> S[-1]                # The last item in S
'm'
>>> S[len(S)-1]          # Negative indexing, the hard way
'm'

Notice that we can use an arbitrary expression in the square brackets, not just a hardcoded number literal—anywhere that Python expects a value, we can use a literal, a variable, or any expression. Python’s syntax is completely general this way.

In addition to simple positional indexing, sequences also support a more general form of indexing known as slicing, which is a way to extract an entire section (slice) in a single step. For example:

>>> S                     # A 4-character string
'Spam'
>>> S[1:3]                # Slice of S from offsets 1 through 2 (not 3)
'pa'

Probably the easiest way to think of slices is that they are a way to extract an entire column from a string in a single step. Their general form, X[I:J], means “give me everything in X from offset I up to but not including offset J.” The result is returned in a new object. The second of the preceding operations, for instance, gives us all the characters in string S from offsets 1 through 2 (that is, 3 – 1) as a new string. The effect is to slice or “parse out” the two characters in the middle.

In a slice, the left bound defaults to zero, and the right bound defaults to the length of the sequence being sliced. This leads to some common usage variations:

>>> S[1:]                 # Everything past the first (1:len(S))
'pam'
>>> S                     # S itself hasn't changed
'Spam'
>>> S[0:3]                # Everything but the last
'Spa'
>>> S[:3]                 # Same as S[0:3]
'Spa'
>>> S[:-1]                # Everything but the last again, but simpler (0:-1)
'Spa'
>>> S[:]                  # All of S as a top-level copy (0:len(S))
'Spam'

Note how negative offsets can be used to give bounds for slices, too, and how the last operation effectively copies the entire string. As you’ll learn later, there is no reason to copy a string, but this form can be useful for sequences like lists.

Finally, as sequences, strings also support concatenation with the plus sign (joining two strings into a new string) and repetition (making a new string by repeating another):

>>> S
'Spam'
>>> S + 'xyz'             # Concatenation
'Spamxyz'
>>> S                     # S is unchanged
'Spam'
>>> S * 8                 # Repetition
'SpamSpamSpamSpamSpamSpamSpamSpam'

Notice that the plus sign (+) means different things for different objects: addition for numbers, and concatenation for strings. This is a general property of Python that we’ll call polymorphism later in the book—in sum, the meaning of an operation depends on the objects being operated on. As you’ll see when we study dynamic typing, this polymorphism property accounts for much of the conciseness and flexibility of Python code. Because types aren’t constrained, a Python-coded operation can normally work on many different types of objects automatically, as long as they support a compatible interface (like the + operation here). This turns out to be a huge idea in Python; you’ll learn more about it later on our tour.

Immutability

Notice that in the prior examples, we were not changing the original string with any of the operations we ran on it. Every string operation is defined to produce a new string as its result, because strings are immutable in Python—they cannot be changed in-place after they are created. For example, you can’t change a string by assigning to one of its positions, but you can always build a new one and assign it to the same name. Because Python cleans up old objects as you go (as you’ll see later), this isn’t as inefficient as it may sound:

>>> S
'Spam'
>>> S[0] = 'z'             # Immutable objects cannot be changed
...error text omitted...
TypeError: 'str' object does not support item assignment

>>> S = 'z' + S[1:]        # But we can run expressions to make new objects
>>> S
'zpam'

Every object in Python is classified as either immutable (unchangeable) or not. In terms of the core types, numbers, strings, and tuples are immutable; lists and dictionaries are not (they can be changed in-place freely). Among other things, immutability can be used to guarantee that an object remains constant throughout your program.

Type-Specific Methods

Every string operation we’ve studied so far is really a sequence operation—that is, these operations will work on other sequences in Python as well, including lists and tuples. In addition to generic sequence operations, though, strings also have operations all their own, available as methods—functions attached to the object, which are triggered with a call expression.

For example, the string find method is the basic substring search operation (it returns the offset of the passed-in substring, or −1 if it is not present), and the string replace method performs global searches and replacements:

>>> S.find('pa')            # Find the offset of a substring
1
>>> S
'Spam'
>>> S.replace('pa', 'XYZ')  # Replace occurrences of a substring with another
'SXYZm'
>>> S
'Spam'

Again, despite the names of these string methods, we are not changing the original strings here, but creating new strings as the results—because strings are immutable, we have to do it this way. String methods are the first line of text-processing tools in Python. Other methods split a string into substrings on a delimiter (handy as a simple form of parsing), perform case conversions, test the content of the string (digits, letters, and so on), and strip whitespace characters off the ends of the string:

>>> line = 'aaa,bbb,ccccc,dd'
>>> line.split(',')          # Split on a delimiter into a list of substrings
['aaa', 'bbb', 'ccccc', 'dd']
>>> S = 'spam'
>>> S.upper()                # Upper- and lowercase conversions
'SPAM'

>>> S.isalpha()              # Content tests: isalpha, isdigit, etc.
True

>>> line = 'aaa,bbb,ccccc,dd\n'
>>> line = line.rstrip()     # Remove whitespace characters on the right side
>>> line
'aaa,bbb,ccccc,dd'

Strings also support an advanced substitution operation known as formatting, available as both an expression (the original) and a string method call (new in 2.6 and 3.0):

>>> '%s, eggs, and %s' % ('spam', 'SPAM!')          # Formatting expression (all)
'spam, eggs, and SPAM!'

>>> '{0}, eggs, and {1}'.format('spam', 'SPAM!')    # Formatting method (2.6, 3.0)
'spam, eggs, and SPAM!'

One note here: although sequence operations are generic, methods are not—although some types share some method names, string method operations generally work only on strings, and nothing else. As a rule of thumb, Python’s toolset is layered: generic operations that span multiple types show up as built-in functions or expressions (e.g., len(X), X[0]), but type-specific operations are method calls (e.g., aString.upper()). Finding the tools you need among all these categories will become more natural as you use Python more, but the next section gives a few tips you can use right now.

Getting Help

The methods introduced in the prior section are a representative, but small, sample of what is available for string objects. In general, this book is not exhaustive in its look at object methods. For more details, you can always call the built-in dir function, which returns a list of all the attributes available for a given object. Because methods are function attributes, they will show up in this list. Assuming S is still the string, here are its attributes on Python 3.0 (Python 2.6 varies slightly):

>>> dir(S)
['__add__', '__class__', '__contains__', '__delattr__', '__doc__', '__eq__',
'__format__', '__ge__', '__getattribute__', '__getitem__', '__getnewargs__',
'__gt__', '__hash__', '__init__', '__iter__', '__le__', '__len__', '__lt__',
'__mod__', '__mul__', '__ne__', '__new__', '__reduce__', '__reduce_ex__',
'__repr__', '__rmod__', '__rmul__', '__setattr__', '__sizeof__', '__str__',
'__subclasshook__', '_formatter_field_name_split', '_formatter_parser',
'capitalize', 'center', 'count', 'encode', 'endswith', 'expandtabs', 'find',
'format', 'index', 'isalnum','isalpha', 'isdecimal', 'isdigit', 'isidentifier',
'islower', 'isnumeric', 'isprintable', 'isspace', 'istitle', 'isupper', 'join',
'ljust', 'lower', 'lstrip', 'maketrans', 'partition', 'replace', 'rfind',
'rindex', 'rjust', 'rpartition', 'rsplit', 'rstrip', 'split', 'splitlines',
'startswith', 'strip', 'swapcase', 'title', 'translate', 'upper', 'zfill']

You probably won’t care about the names with underscores in this list until later in the book, when we study operator overloading in classes—they represent the implementation of the string object and are available to support customization. In general, leading and trailing double underscores is the naming pattern Python uses for implementation details. The names without the underscores in this list are the callable methods on string objects.

The dir function simply gives the methods’ names. To ask what they do, you can pass them to the help function:

>>> help(S.replace)
Help on built-in function replace:

replace(...)
    S.replace (old, new[, count]) -> str

    Return a copy of S with all occurrences of substring
    old replaced by new.  If the optional argument count is
    given, only the first count occurrences are replaced.

help is one of a handful of interfaces to a system of code that ships with Python known as PyDoc—a tool for extracting documentation from objects. Later in the book, you’ll see that PyDoc can also render its reports in HTML format.

You can also ask for help on an entire string (e.g., help(S)), but you may get more help than you want to see—i.e., information about every string method. It’s generally better to ask about a specific method.

For more details, you can also consult Python’s standard library reference manual or commercially published reference books, but dir and help are the first line of documentation in Python.

Other Ways to Code Strings

So far, we’ve looked at the string object’s sequence operations and type-specific methods. Python also provides a variety of ways for us to code strings, which we’ll explore in greater depth later. For instance, special characters can be represented as backslash escape sequences:

>>> S = 'A\nB\tC'            # \n is end-of-line, \t is tab
>>> len(S)                   # Each stands for just one character
5

>>> ord('\n')                # \n is a byte with the binary value 10 in ASCII
10

>>> S = 'A\0B\0C'            # \0, a binary zero byte, does not terminate string
>>> len(S)
5

Python allows strings to be enclosed in single or double quote characters (they mean the same thing). It also allows multiline string literals enclosed in triple quotes (single or double)—when this form is used, all the lines are concatenated together, and end-of-line characters are added where line breaks appear. This is a minor syntactic convenience, but it’s useful for embedding things like HTML and XML code in a Python script:

>>> msg = """ aaaaaaaaaaaaa
bbb'''bbbbbbbbbb""bbbbbbb'bbbb
cccccccccccccc"""
>>> msg
' aaaaaaaaaaaaa\nbbb\'\'\'bbbbbbbbbb""bbbbbbb\'bbbb\ncccccccccccccc'

Python also supports a raw string literal that turns off the backslash escape mechanism (such string literals start with the letter r), as well as Unicode string support that supports internationalization. In 3.0, the basic str string type handles Unicode too (which makes sense, given that ASCII text is a simple kind of Unicode), and a bytes type represents raw byte strings; in 2.6, Unicode is a separate type, and str handles both 8-bit strings and binary data. Files are also changed in 3.0 to return and accept str for text and bytes for binary data. We’ll meet all these special string forms in later chapters.

Pattern Matching

One point worth noting before we move on is that none of the string object’s methods support pattern-based text processing. Text pattern matching is an advanced tool outside this book’s scope, but readers with backgrounds in other scripting languages may be interested to know that to do pattern matching in Python, we import a module called re. This module has analogous calls for searching, splitting, and replacement, but because we can use patterns to specify substrings, we can be much more general:

>>> import re
>>> match = re.match('Hello[ \t]*(.*)world', 'Hello    Python world')
>>> match.group(1)
'Python '

This example searches for a substring that begins with the word “Hello,” followed by zero or more tabs or spaces, followed by arbitrary characters to be saved as a matched group, terminated by the word “world.” If such a substring is found, portions of the substring matched by parts of the pattern enclosed in parentheses are available as groups. The following pattern, for example, picks out three groups separated by slashes:

>>> match = re.match('/(.*)/(.*)/(.*)', '/usr/home/lumberjack')
>>> match.groups()
('usr', 'home', 'lumberjack')

Pattern matching is a fairly advanced text-processing tool by itself, but there is also support in Python for even more advanced text and language processing, including XML parsing and natural language analysis. I’ve already said enough about strings for this tutorial, though, so let’s move on to the next type.

Lists

The Python list object is the most general sequence provided by the language. Lists are positionally ordered collections of arbitrarily typed objects, and they have no fixed size. They are also mutable—unlike strings, lists can be modified in-place by assignment to offsets as well as a variety of list method calls.

Sequence Operations

Because they are sequences, lists support all the sequence operations we discussed for strings; the only difference is that the results are usually lists instead of strings. For instance, given a three-item list:

>>> L = [123, 'spam', 1.23]          # A list of three different-type objects
>>> len(L)                           # Number of items in the list
3

we can index, slice, and so on, just as for strings:

>>> L[0]                             # Indexing by position
123

>>> L[:-1]                           # Slicing a list returns a new list
[123, 'spam']

>>> L + [4, 5, 6]                    # Concatenation makes a new list too
[123, 'spam', 1.23, 4, 5, 6]

>>> L                                # We're not changing the original list
[123, 'spam', 1.23]

Type-Specific Operations

Python’s lists are related to arrays in other languages, but they tend to be more powerful. For one thing, they have no fixed type constraint—the list we just looked at, for example, contains three objects of completely different types (an integer, a string, and a floating-point number). Further, lists have no fixed size. That is, they can grow and shrink on demand, in response to list-specific operations:

>>> L.append('NI')                  # Growing: add object at end of list
>>> L
[123, 'spam', 1.23, 'NI']

>>> L.pop(2)                        # Shrinking: delete an item in the middle
1.23

>>> L                               # "del L[2]" deletes from a list too
[123, 'spam', 'NI']

Here, the list append method expands the list’s size and inserts an item at the end; the pop method (or an equivalent del statement) then removes an item at a given offset, causing the list to shrink. Other list methods insert an item at an arbitrary position (insert), remove a given item by value (remove), and so on. Because lists are mutable, most list methods also change the list object in-place, instead of creating a new one:

>>> M = ['bb', 'aa', 'cc']
>>> M.sort()
>>> M
['aa', 'bb', 'cc']
>>> M.reverse()
>>> M
['cc', 'bb', 'aa']

The list sort method here, for example, orders the list in ascending fashion by default, and reverse reverses it—in both cases, the methods modify the list directly.

Bounds Checking

Although lists have no fixed size, Python still doesn’t allow us to reference items that are not present. Indexing off the end of a list is always a mistake, but so is assigning off the end:

>>> L
[123, 'spam', 'NI']

>>> L[99]
...error text omitted...
IndexError: list index out of range

>>> L[99] = 1
...error text omitted...
IndexError: list assignment index out of range

This is intentional, as it’s usually an error to try to assign off the end of a list (and a particularly nasty one in the C language, which doesn’t do as much error checking as Python). Rather than silently growing the list in response, Python reports an error. To grow a list, we call list methods such as append instead.

Nesting

One nice feature of Python’s core data types is that they support arbitrary nesting—we can nest them in any combination, and as deeply as we like (for example, we can have a list that contains a dictionary, which contains another list, and so on). One immediate application of this feature is to represent matrixes, or “multidimensional arrays” in Python. A list with nested lists will do the job for basic applications:

>>> M = [[1, 2, 3],               # A 3 × 3 matrix, as nested lists
         [4, 5, 6],               # Code can span lines if bracketed
         [7, 8, 9]]
>>> M
[[1, 2, 3], [4, 5, 6], [7, 8, 9]]

Here, we’ve coded a list that contains three other lists. The effect is to represent a 3 × 3 matrix of numbers. Such a structure can be accessed in a variety of ways:

>>> M[1]                          # Get row 2
[4, 5, 6]

>>> M[1][2]                       # Get row 2, then get item 3 within the row
6

The first operation here fetches the entire second row, and the second grabs the third item within that row. Stringing together index operations takes us deeper and deeper into our nested-object structure.[13]

Comprehensions

In addition to sequence operations and list methods, Python includes a more advanced operation known as a list comprehension expression, which turns out to be a powerful way to process structures like our matrix. Suppose, for instance, that we need to extract the second column of our sample matrix. It’s easy to grab rows by simple indexing because the matrix is stored by rows, but it’s almost as easy to get a column with a list comprehension:

>>> col2 = [row[1] for row in M]             # Collect the items in column 2
>>> col2
[2, 5, 8]

>>> M                                        # The matrix is unchanged
[[1, 2, 3], [4, 5, 6], [7, 8, 9]]

List comprehensions derive from set notation; they are a way to build a new list by running an expression on each item in a sequence, one at a time, from left to right. List comprehensions are coded in square brackets (to tip you off to the fact that they make a list) and are composed of an expression and a looping construct that share a variable name (row, here). The preceding list comprehension means basically what it says: “Give me row[1] for each row in matrix M, in a new list.” The result is a new list containing column 2 of the matrix.

List comprehensions can be more complex in practice:

>>> [row[1] + 1 for row in M]                 # Add 1 to each item in column 2
[3, 6, 9]

>>> [row[1] for row in M if row[1] % 2 == 0]  # Filter out odd items
[2, 8]

The first operation here, for instance, adds 1 to each item as it is collected, and the second uses an if clause to filter odd numbers out of the result using the % modulus expression (remainder of division). List comprehensions make new lists of results, but they can be used to iterate over any iterable object. Here, for instance, we use list comprehensions to step over a hardcoded list of coordinates and a string:

>>> diag = [M[i][i] for i in [0, 1, 2]]      # Collect a diagonal from matrix
>>> diag
[1, 5, 9]

>>> doubles = [c * 2 for c in 'spam']        # Repeat characters in a string
>>> doubles
['ss', 'pp', 'aa', 'mm']

List comprehensions, and relatives like the map and filter built-in functions, are a bit too involved for me to say more about them here. The main point of this brief introduction is to illustrate that Python includes both simple and advanced tools in its arsenal. List comprehensions are an optional feature, but they tend to be handy in practice and often provide a substantial processing speed advantage. They also work on any type that is a sequence in Python, as well as some types that are not. You’ll hear much more about them later in this book.

As a preview, though, you’ll find that in recent Pythons, comprehension syntax in parentheses can also be used to create generators that produce results on demand (the sum built-in, for instance, sums items in a sequence):

>>> G = (sum(row) for row in M)              # Create a generator of row sums
>>> next(G)                                  # iter(G) not required here
6
>>> next(G)                                  # Run the iteration protocol
15

The map built-in can do similar work, by generating the results of running items through a function. Wrapping it in list forces it to return all its values in Python 3.0:

>>> list(map(sum, M))                        # Map sum over items in M
[6, 15, 24]

In Python 3.0, comprehension syntax can also be used to create sets and dictionaries:

>>> {sum(row) for row in M}                  # Create a set of row sums
{24, 6, 15}

>>> {i : sum(M[i]) for i in range(3)}        # Creates key/value table of row sums
{0: 6, 1: 15, 2: 24}

In fact, lists, sets, and dictionaries can all be built with comprehensions in 3.0:

>>> [ord(x) for x in 'spaam']                # List of character ordinals
[115, 112, 97, 97, 109]
>>> {ord(x) for x in 'spaam'}                # Sets remove duplicates
{112, 97, 115, 109}
>>> {x: ord(x) for x in 'spaam'}             # Dictionary keys are unique
{'a': 97, 'p': 112, 's': 115, 'm': 109}

To understand objects like generators, sets, and dictionaries, though, we must move ahead.

Dictionaries

Python dictionaries are something completely different (Monty Python reference intended)—they are not sequences at all, but are instead known as mappings. Mappings are also collections of other objects, but they store objects by key instead of by relative position. In fact, mappings don’t maintain any reliable left-to-right order; they simply map keys to associated values. Dictionaries, the only mapping type in Python’s core objects set, are also mutable: they may be changed in-place and can grow and shrink on demand, like lists.

Mapping Operations

When written as literals, dictionaries are coded in curly braces and consist of a series of “key: value” pairs. Dictionaries are useful anytime we need to associate a set of values with keys—to describe the properties of something, for instance. As an example, consider the following three-item dictionary (with keys “food,” “quantity,” and “color”):

>>> D = {'food': 'Spam', 'quantity': 4, 'color': 'pink'}

We can index this dictionary by key to fetch and change the keys’ associated values. The dictionary index operation uses the same syntax as that used for sequences, but the item in the square brackets is a key, not a relative position:

>>> D['food']              # Fetch value of key 'food'
'Spam'

>>> D['quantity'] += 1     # Add 1 to 'quantity' value
>>> D
{'food': 'Spam', 'color': 'pink', 'quantity': 5}

Although the curly-braces literal form does see use, it is perhaps more common to see dictionaries built up in different ways. The following code, for example, starts with an empty dictionary and fills it out one key at a time. Unlike out-of-bounds assignments in lists, which are forbidden, assignments to new dictionary keys create those keys:

>>> D = {}
>>> D['name'] = 'Bob'      # Create keys by assignment
>>> D['job']  = 'dev'
>>> D['age']  = 40

>>> D
{'age': 40, 'job': 'dev', 'name': 'Bob'}

>>> print(D['name'])
Bob

Here, we’re effectively using dictionary keys as field names in a record that describes someone. In other applications, dictionaries can also be used to replace searching operations—indexing a dictionary by key is often the fastest way to code a search in Python. As we'll learn later, dictionaries may also be made by passing keyword arguments to the type name: dict(name='Bob', job='dev', age=40) makes the same dictionary.

Nesting Revisited

In the prior example, we used a dictionary to describe a hypothetical person, with three keys. Suppose, though, that the information is more complex. Perhaps we need to record a first name and a last name, along with multiple job titles. This leads to another application of Python’s object nesting in action. The following dictionary, coded all at once as a literal, captures more structured information:

>>> rec = {'name': {'first': 'Bob', 'last': 'Smith'},
           'job':  ['dev', 'mgr'],
           'age':  40.5}

Here, we again have a three-key dictionary at the top (keys “name,” “job,” and “age”), but the values have become more complex: a nested dictionary for the name to support multiple parts, and a nested list for the job to support multiple roles and future expansion. We can access the components of this structure much as we did for our matrix earlier, but this time some of our indexes are dictionary keys, not list offsets:

>>> rec['name']                         # 'name' is a nested dictionary
{'last': 'Smith', 'first': 'Bob'}

>>> rec['name']['last']                 # Index the nested dictionary
'Smith'

>>> rec['job']                          # 'job' is a nested list
['dev', 'mgr']
>>> rec['job'][-1]                      # Index the nested list
'mgr'

>>> rec['job'].append('janitor')        # Expand Bob's job description in-place
>>> rec
{'age': 40.5, 'job': ['dev', 'mgr', 'janitor'], 'name': {'last': 'Smith',
'first': 'Bob'}}

Notice how the last operation here expands the nested job list—because the job list is a separate piece of memory from the dictionary that contains it, it can grow and shrink freely (object memory layout will be discussed further later in this book).

The real reason for showing you this example is to demonstrate the flexibility of Python’s core data types. As you can see, nesting allows us to build up complex information structures directly and easily. Building a similar structure in a low-level language like C would be tedious and require much more code: we would have to lay out and declare structures and arrays, fill out values, link everything together, and so on. In Python, this is all automatic—running the expression creates the entire nested object structure for us. In fact, this is one of the main benefits of scripting languages like Python.

Just as importantly, in a lower-level language we would have to be careful to clean up all of the object’s space when we no longer need it. In Python, when we lose the last reference to the object—by assigning its variable to something else, for example—all of the memory space occupied by that object’s structure is automatically cleaned up for us:

>>> rec = 0                             # Now the object's space is reclaimed

Technically speaking, Python has a feature known as garbage collection that cleans up unused memory as your program runs and frees you from having to manage such details in your code. In Python, the space is reclaimed immediately, as soon as the last reference to an object is removed. We’ll study how this works later in this book; for now, it’s enough to know that you can use objects freely, without worrying about creating their space or cleaning up as you go.[14]

Sorting Keys: for Loops

As mappings, as we’ve already seen, dictionaries only support accessing items by key. However, they also support type-specific operations with method calls that are useful in a variety of common use cases.

As mentioned earlier, because dictionaries are not sequences, they don’t maintain any dependable left-to-right order. This means that if we make a dictionary and print it back, its keys may come back in a different order than that in which we typed them:

>>> D = {'a': 1, 'b': 2, 'c': 3}
>>> D
{'a': 1, 'c': 3, 'b': 2}

What do we do, though, if we do need to impose an ordering on a dictionary’s items? One common solution is to grab a list of keys with the dictionary keys method, sort that with the list sort method, and then step through the result with a Python for loop (be sure to press the Enter key twice after coding the for loop below—as explained in Chapter 3, an empty line means “go” at the interactive prompt, and the prompt changes to “...” on some interfaces):

>>> Ks = list(D.keys())                # Unordered keys list
>>> Ks                                 # A list in 2.6, "view" in 3.0: use list()
['a', 'c', 'b']

>>> Ks.sort()                          # Sorted keys list
>>> Ks
['a', 'b', 'c']

>>> for key in Ks:                     # Iterate though sorted keys
        print(key, '=>', D[key])       # <== press Enter twice here

a => 1
b => 2
c => 3

This is a three-step process, although, as we’ll see in later chapters, in recent versions of Python it can be done in one step with the newer sorted built-in function. The sorted call returns the result and sorts a variety of object types, in this case sorting dictionary keys automatically:

>>> D
{'a': 1, 'c': 3, 'b': 2}

>>> for key in sorted(D):
        print(key, '=>', D[key])

a => 1
b => 2
c => 3

Besides showcasing dictionaries, this use case serves to introduce the Python for loop. The for loop is a simple and efficient way to step through all the items in a sequence and run a block of code for each item in turn. A user-defined loop variable (key, here) is used to reference the current item each time through. The net effect in our example is to print the unordered dictionary’s keys and values, in sorted-key order.

The for loop, and its more general cousin the while loop, are the main ways we code repetitive tasks as statements in our scripts. Really, though, the for loop (like its relative the list comprehension, which we met earlier) is a sequence operation. It works on any object that is a sequence and, like the list comprehension, even on some things that are not. Here, for example, it is stepping across the characters in a string, printing the uppercase version of each as it goes:

>>> for c in 'spam':
        print(c.upper())

S
P
A
M

Python’s while loop is a more general sort of looping tool, not limited to stepping across sequences:

>>> x = 4
>>> while x > 0:
        print('spam!' * x)
        x -= 1

spam!spam!spam!spam!
spam!spam!spam!
spam!spam!
spam!

We’ll discuss looping statements, syntax, and tools in depth later in the book.

Iteration and Optimization

If the last section’s for loop looks like the list comprehension expression introduced earlier, it should: both are really general iteration tools. In fact, both will work on any object that follows the iteration protocol—a pervasive idea in Python that essentially means a physically stored sequence in memory, or an object that generates one item at a time in the context of an iteration operation. An object falls into the latter category if it responds to the iter built-in with an object that advances in response to next. The generator comprehension expression we saw earlier is such an object.

I’ll have more to say about the iteration protocol later in this book. For now, keep in mind that every Python tool that scans an object from left to right uses the iteration protocol. This is why the sorted call used in the prior section works on the dictionary directly—we don’t have to call the keys method to get a sequence because dictionaries are iterable objects, with a next that returns successive keys.

This also means that any list comprehension expression, such as this one, which computes the squares of a list of numbers:

>>> squares = [x ** 2 for x in [1, 2, 3, 4, 5]]
>>> squares
[1, 4, 9, 16, 25]

can always be coded as an equivalent for loop that builds the result list manually by appending as it goes:

>>> squares = []
>>> for x in [1, 2, 3, 4, 5]:          # This is what a list comprehension does
        squares.append(x ** 2)         # Both run the iteration protocol internally

>>> squares
[1, 4, 9, 16, 25]

The list comprehension, though, and related functional programming tools like map and filter, will generally run faster than a for loop today (perhaps even twice as fast)—a property that could matter in your programs for large data sets. Having said that, though, I should point out that performance measures are tricky business in Python because it optimizes so much, and performance can vary from release to release.

A major rule of thumb in Python is to code for simplicity and readability first and worry about performance later, after your program is working, and after you’ve proved that there is a genuine performance concern. More often than not, your code will be quick enough as it is. If you do need to tweak code for performance, though, Python includes tools to help you out, including the time and timeit modules and the profile module. You’ll find more on these later in this book, and in the Python manuals.

Missing Keys: if Tests

One other note about dictionaries before we move on. Although we can assign to a new key to expand a dictionary, fetching a nonexistent key is still a mistake:

>>> D
{'a': 1, 'c': 3, 'b': 2}

>>> D['e'] = 99                      # Assigning new keys grows dictionaries
>>> D
{'a': 1, 'c': 3, 'b': 2, 'e': 99}

>>> D['f']                           # Referencing a nonexistent key is an error
...error text omitted...
KeyError: 'f'

This is what we want—it’s usually a programming error to fetch something that isn’t really there. But in some generic programs, we can’t always know what keys will be present when we write our code. How do we handle such cases and avoid errors? One trick is to test ahead of time. The dictionary in membership expression allows us to query the existence of a key and branch on the result with a Python if statement (as with the for, be sure to press Enter twice to run the if interactively here):

>>> 'f' in D
False

>>> if not 'f' in D:
       print('missing')

missing

I’ll have much more to say about the if statement and statement syntax in general later in this book, but the form we’re using here is straightforward: it consists of the word if, followed by an expression that is interpreted as a true or false result, followed by a block of code to run if the test is true. In its full form, the if statement can also have an else clause for a default case, and one or more elif (else if) clauses for other tests. It’s the main selection tool in Python, and it’s the way we code logic in our scripts.

Still, there are other ways to create dictionaries and avoid accessing nonexistent keys: the get method (a conditional index with a default); the Python 2.X has_key method (which is no longer available in 3.0); the try statement (a tool we’ll first meet in Chapter 10 that catches and recovers from exceptions altogether); and the if/else expression (essentially, an if statement squeezed onto a single line). Here are a few examples:

>>> value = D.get('x', 0)                      # Index but with a default
>>> value
0
>>> value = D['x'] if 'x' in D else 0          # if/else expression form
>>> value
0

We’ll save the details on such alternatives until a later chapter. For now, let’s move on to tuples.

Files

File objects are Python code’s main interface to external files on your computer. Files are a core type, but they’re something of an oddball—there is no specific literal syntax for creating them. Rather, to create a file object, you call the built-in open function, passing in an external filename and a processing mode as strings. For example, to create a text output file, you would pass in its name and the 'w' processing mode string to write data:

>>> f = open('data.txt', 'w')      # Make a new file in output mode
>>> f.write('Hello\n')             # Write strings of bytes to it
6
>>> f.write('world\n')             # Returns number of bytes written in Python 3.0
6
>>> f.close()                      # Close to flush output buffers to disk

This creates a file in the current directory and writes text to it (the filename can be a full directory path if you need to access a file elsewhere on your computer). To read back what you just wrote, reopen the file in 'r' processing mode, for reading text input—this is the default if you omit the mode in the call. Then read the file’s content into a string, and display it. A file’s contents are always a string in your script, regardless of the type of data the file contains:

>>> f = open('data.txt')           # 'r' is the default processing mode
>>> text = f.read()                # Read entire file into a string
>>> text
'Hello\nworld\n'

>>> print(text)                    # print interprets control characters
Hello
world

>>> text.split()                   # File content is always a string
['Hello', 'world']

Other file object methods support additional features we don’t have time to cover here. For instance, file objects provide more ways of reading and writing (read accepts an optional byte size, readline reads one line at a time, and so on), as well as other tools (seek moves to a new file position). As we’ll see later, though, the best way to read a file today is to not read it at all—files provide an iterator that automatically reads line by line in for loops and other contexts.

We’ll meet the full set of file methods later in this book, but if you want a quick preview now, run a dir call on any open file and a help on any of the method names that come back:

>>> dir(f)
[ ...many names omitted...
'buffer', 'close', 'closed', 'encoding', 'errors', 'fileno', 'flush', 'isatty',
'line_buffering', 'mode', 'name', 'newlines', 'read', 'readable', 'readline',
'readlines', 'seek', 'seekable', 'tell', 'truncate', 'writable', 'write',
'writelines']

>>>help(f.seek)
...try it and see...

Later in the book, we’ll also see that files in Python 3.0 draw a sharp distinction between text and binary data. Text files represent content as strings and perform Unicode encoding and decoding automatically, while binary files represent content as a special bytes string type and allow you to access file content unaltered (the following partial example assumes there is already a binary file in your current directory):

>>> data = open('data.bin', 'rb').read()       # Open binary file
>>> data                                       # bytes string holds binary data
b'\x00\x00\x00\x07spam\x00\x08'
>>> data[4:8]
b'spam'

Although you won’t generally need to care about this distinction if you deal only with ASCII text, Python 3.0’s strings and files are an asset if you deal with internationalized applications or byte-oriented data.

Other File-Like Tools

The open function is the workhorse for most file processing you will do in Python. For more advanced tasks, though, Python comes with additional file-like tools: pipes, FIFOs, sockets, keyed-access files, persistent object shelves, descriptor-based files, relational and object-oriented database interfaces, and more. Descriptor files, for instance, support file locking and other low-level tools, and sockets provide an interface for networking and interprocess communication. We won’t cover many of these topics in this book, but you’ll find them useful once you start programming Python in earnest.

Other Core Types

Beyond the core types we’ve seen so far, there are others that may or may not qualify for membership in the set, depending on how broadly it is defined. Sets, for example, are a recent addition to the language that are neither mappings nor sequences; rather, they are unordered collections of unique and immutable objects. Sets are created by calling the built-in set function or using new set literals and expressions in 3.0, and they support the usual mathematical set operations (the choice of new {...} syntax for set literals in 3.0 makes sense, since sets are much like the keys of a valueless dictionary):

>>> X = set('spam')                 # Make a set out of a sequence in 2.6 and 3.0
>>> Y = {'h', 'a', 'm'}             # Make a set with new 3.0 set literals
>>> X, Y
({'a', 'p', 's', 'm'}, {'a', 'h', 'm'})

>>> X & Y                           # Intersection
{'a', 'm'}

>>> X | Y                           # Union
{'a', 'p', 's', 'h', 'm'}

>>> X – Y                           # Difference
{'p', 's'}

>>> {x ** 2 for x in [1, 2, 3, 4]}  # Set comprehensions in 3.0
{16, 1, 4, 9}

In addition, Python recently grew a few new numeric types: decimal numbers (fixed-precision floating-point numbers) and fraction numbers (rational numbers with both a numerator and a denominator). Both can be used to work around the limitations and inherent inaccuracies of floating-point math:

>>> 1 / 3                           # Floating-point (use .0 in Python 2.6)
0.33333333333333331
>>> (2/3) + (1/2)
1.1666666666666665

>>> import decimal                  # Decimals: fixed precision
>>> d = decimal.Decimal('3.141')
>>> d + 1
Decimal('4.141')

>>> decimal.getcontext().prec = 2
>>> decimal.Decimal('1.00') / decimal.Decimal('3.00')
Decimal('0.33')

>>> from fractions import Fraction  # Fractions: numerator+denominator
>>> f = Fraction(2, 3)
>>> f + 1
Fraction(5, 3)
>>> f + Fraction(1, 2)
Fraction(7, 6)

Python also comes with Booleans (with predefined True and False objects that are essentially just the integers 1 and 0 with custom display logic), and it has long supported a special placeholder object called None commonly used to initialize names and objects:

>>> 1 > 2, 1 < 2                    # Booleans
(False, True)
>>> bool('spam')
True

>>> X = None                        # None placeholder
>>> print(X)
None
>>> L = [None] * 100                # Initialize a list of 100 Nones
>>> L
[None, None, None, None, None, None, None, None, None, None, None, None,
None, None, None, None, None, None, None, None, ...a list of 100 Nones...]

How to Break Your Code’s Flexibility

I’ll have more to say about all of Python’s object types later, but one merits special treatment here. The type object, returned by the type built-in function, is an object that gives the type of another object; its result differs slightly in 3.0, because types have merged with classes completely (something we’ll explore in the context of “new-style” classes in Part VI). Assuming L is still the list of the prior section:

# In Python 2.6:

>>> type(L)                         # Types: type of L is list type object
<type 'list'>
>>> type(type(L))                   # Even types are objects
<type 'type'>

# In Python 3.0:

>>> type(L)                         # 3.0: types are classes, and vice versa
<class 'list'>
>>> type(type(L))                   # See Chapter 31 for more on class types
<class 'type'>

Besides allowing you to explore your objects interactively, the practical application of this is that it allows code to check the types of the objects it processes. In fact, there are at least three ways to do so in a Python script:

>>> if type(L) == type([]):         # Type testing, if you must...
        print('yes')

yes
>>> if type(L) == list:             # Using the type name
        print('yes')

yes
>>> if isinstance(L, list):         # Object-oriented tests
        print('yes')

yes

Now that I’ve shown you all these ways to do type testing, however, I am required by law to tell you that doing so is almost always the wrong thing to do in a Python program (and often a sign of an ex-C programmer first starting to use Python!). The reason why won’t become completely clear until later in the book, when we start writing larger code units such as functions, but it’s a (perhaps the) core Python concept. By checking for specific types in your code, you effectively break its flexibility—you limit it to working on just one type. Without such tests, your code may be able to work on a whole range of types.

This is related to the idea of polymorphism mentioned earlier, and it stems from Python’s lack of type declarations. As you’ll learn, in Python, we code to object interfaces (operations supported), not to types. Not caring about specific types means that code is automatically applicable to many of them—any object with a compatible interface will work, regardless of its specific type. Although type checking is supported—and even required, in some rare cases—you’ll see that it’s not usually the “Pythonic” way of thinking. In fact, you’ll find that polymorphism is probably the key idea behind using Python well.

User-Defined Classes

We’ll study object-oriented programming in Python—an optional but powerful feature of the language that cuts development time by supporting programming by customization—in depth later in this book. In abstract terms, though, classes define new types of objects that extend the core set, so they merit a passing glance here. Say, for example, that you wish to have a type of object that models employees. Although there is no such specific core type in Python, the following user-defined class might fit the bill:

>>> class Worker:
         def __init__(self, name, pay):          # Initialize when created
             self.name = name                    # self is the new object
             self.pay  = pay
         def lastName(self):
             return self.name.split()[-1]        # Split string on blanks
         def giveRaise(self, percent):
             self.pay *= (1.0 + percent)         # Update pay in-place

This class defines a new kind of object that will have name and pay attributes (sometimes called state information), as well as two bits of behavior coded as functions (normally called methods). Calling the class like a function generates instances of our new type, and the class’s methods automatically receive the instance being processed by a given method call (in the self argument):

>>> bob = Worker('Bob Smith', 50000)             # Make two instances
>>> sue = Worker('Sue Jones', 60000)             # Each has name and pay attrs
>>> bob.lastName()                               # Call method: bob is self
'Smith'
>>> sue.lastName()                               # sue is the self subject
'Jones'
>>> sue.giveRaise(.10)                           # Updates sue's pay
>>> sue.pay
66000.0

The implied “self” object is why we call this an object-oriented model: there is always an implied subject in functions within a class. In a sense, though, the class-based type simply builds on and uses core types—a user-defined Worker object here, for example, is just a collection of a string and a number (name and pay, respectively), plus functions for processing those two built-in objects.

The larger story of classes is that their inheritance mechanism supports software hierarchies that lend themselves to customization by extension. We extend software by writing new classes, not by changing what already works. You should also know that classes are an optional feature of Python, and simpler built-in types such as lists and dictionaries are often better tools than user-coded classes. This is all well beyond the bounds of our introductory object-type tutorial, though, so consider this just a preview; for full disclosure on user-defined types coded with classes, you’ll have to read on to Part VI.

And Everything Else

As mentioned earlier, everything you can process in a Python script is a type of object, so our object type tour is necessarily incomplete. However, even though everything in Python is an “object,” only those types of objects we’ve met so far are considered part of Python’s core type set. Other types in Python either are objects related to program execution (like functions, modules, classes, and compiled code), which we will study later, or are implemented by imported module functions, not language syntax. The latter of these also tend to have application-specific roles—text patterns, database interfaces, network connections, and so on.

Moreover, keep in mind that the objects we’ve met here are objects, but not necessarily object-oriented—a concept that usually requires inheritance and the Python class statement, which we’ll meet again later in this book. Still, Python’s core objects are the workhorses of almost every Python script you’re likely to meet, and they usually are the basis of larger noncore types.

Chapter Summary

And that’s a wrap for our concise data type tour. This chapter has offered a brief introduction to Python’s core object types and the sorts of operations we can apply to them. We’ve studied generic operations that work on many object types (sequence operations such as indexing and slicing, for example), as well as type-specific operations available as method calls (for instance, string splits and list appends). We’ve also defined some key terms, such as immutability, sequences, and polymorphism.

Along the way, we’ve seen that Python’s core object types are more flexible and powerful than what is available in lower-level languages such as C. For instance, Python’s lists and dictionaries obviate most of the work you do to support collections and searching in lower-level languages. Lists are ordered collections of other objects, and dictionaries are collections of other objects that are indexed by key instead of by position. Both dictionaries and lists may be nested, can grow and shrink on demand, and may contain objects of any type. Moreover, their space is automatically cleaned up as you go.

I’ve skipped most of the details here in order to provide a quick tour, so you shouldn’t expect all of this chapter to have made sense yet. In the next few chapters, we’ll start to dig deeper, filling in details of Python’s core object types that were omitted here so you can gain a more complete understanding. We’ll start off in the next chapter with an in-depth look at Python numbers. First, though, another quiz to review.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

Numbers, strings, lists, dictionaries, tuples, files, and sets are generally considered to be the core object (data) types. Types, None, and Booleans are sometimes classified this way as well. There are multiple number types (integer, floating point, complex, fraction, and decimal) and multiple string types (simple strings and Unicode strings in Python 2.X, and text strings and byte strings in Python 3.X).

They are known as “core” types because they are part of the Python language itself and are always available; to create other objects, you generally must call functions in imported modules. Most of the core types have specific syntax for generating the objects: 'spam', for example, is an expression that makes a string and determines the set of operations that can be applied to it. Because of this, core types are hardwired into Python’s syntax. In contrast, you must call the built-in open function to create a file object.

An “immutable” object is an object that cannot be changed after it is created. Numbers, strings, and tuples in Python fall into this category. While you cannot change an immutable object in-place, you can always make a new one by running an expression.

A “sequence” is a positionally ordered collection of objects. Strings, lists, and tuples are all sequences in Python. They share common sequence operations, such as indexing, concatenation, and slicing, but also have type-specific method calls.

The term “mapping” denotes an object that maps keys to associated values. Python’s dictionary is the only mapping type in the core type set. Mappings do not maintain any left-to-right positional ordering; they support access to data stored by key, plus type-specific method calls.

“Polymorphism” means that the meaning of an operation (like a +) depends on the objects being operated on. This turns out to be a key idea (perhaps the key idea) behind using Python well—not constraining code to specific types makes that code automatically applicable to many types.

[12] In this book, the term literal simply means an expression whose syntax generates an object—sometimes also called a constant. Note that the term “constant” does not imply objects or variables that can never be changed (i.e., this term is unrelated to C++’s const or Python’s “immutable”—a topic explored in the section Immutability).

[13] This matrix structure works for small-scale tasks, but for more serious number crunching you will probably want to use one of the numeric extensions to Python, such as the open source NumPy system. Such tools can store and process large matrixes much more efficiently than our nested list structure. NumPy has been said to turn Python into the equivalent of a free and more powerful version of the Matlab system, and organizations such as NASA, Los Alamos, and JPMorgan Chase use this tool for scientific and financial tasks. Search the Web for more details.

[14] Keep in mind that the rec record we just created really could be a database record, when we employ Python’s object persistence system—an easy way to store native Python objects in files or access-by-key databases. We won’t go into details here, but watch for discussion of Python’s pickle and shelve modules later in this book.

Numeric Type Basics

Most of Python’s number types are fairly typical and will probably seem familiar if you’ve used almost any other programming language in the past. They can be used to keep track of your bank balance, the distance to Mars, the number of visitors to your website, and just about any other numeric quantity.

In Python, numbers are not really a single object type, but a category of similar types. Python supports the usual numeric types (integers and floating points), as well as literals for creating numbers and expressions for processing them. In addition, Python provides more advanced numeric programming support and objects for more advanced work. A complete inventory of Python’s numeric toolbox includes:

Integers and floating-point numbers

Complex numbers

Fixed-precision decimal numbers

Rational fraction numbers

Sets

Booleans

Unlimited integer precision

A variety of numeric built-ins and modules

This chapter starts with basic numbers and fundamentals, then moves on to explore the other tools in this list. Before we jump into code, though, the next few sections get us started with a brief overview of how we write and process numbers in our scripts.

Numeric Literals

Among its basic types, Python provides integers (positive and negative whole numbers) and floating-point numbers (numbers with a fractional part, sometimes called “floats” for economy). Python also allows us to write integers using hexadecimal, octal, and binary literals; offers a complex number type; and allows integers to have unlimited precision (they can grow to have as many digits as your memory space allows). Table 5-1 shows what Python’s numeric types look like when written out in a program, as literals.

Table 5-1. Basic numeric literals

Literal

|

Interpretation

1234, −24, 0, 99999999999999

|

Integers (unlimited size)

1.23, 1., 3.14e-10, 4E210, 4.0e+210

|

Floating-point numbers

0177, 0x9ff, 0b101010

|

Octal, hex, and binary literals in 2.6

0o177, 0x9ff, 0b101010

|

Octal, hex, and binary literals in 3.0

3+4j, 3.0+4.0j, 3J

|

Complex number literals

In general, Python’s numeric type literals are straightforward to write, but a few coding concepts are worth highlighting here:

Integer and floating-point literals

Integers are written as strings of decimal digits. Floating-point numbers have a decimal point and/or an optional signed exponent introduced by an e or E and followed by an optional sign. If you write a number with a decimal point or exponent, Python makes it a floating-point object and uses floating-point (not integer) math when the object is used in an expression. Floating-point numbers are implemented as C “doubles,” and therefore get as much precision as the C compiler used to build the Python interpreter gives to doubles.

Integers in Python 2.6: normal and long

In Python 2.6 there are two integer types, normal (32 bits) and long (unlimited precision), and an integer may end in an l or L to force it to become a long integer. Because integers are automatically converted to long integers when their values overflow 32 bits, you never need to type the letter L yourself—Python automatically converts up to long integer when extra precision is needed.

Integers in Python 3.0: a single type

In Python 3.0, the normal and long integer types have been merged—there is only integer, which automatically supports the unlimited precision of Python 2.6’s separate long integer type. Because of this, integers can no longer be coded with a trailing l or L, and integers never print with this character either. Apart from this, most programs are unaffected by this change, unless they do type testing that checks for 2.6 long integers.

Hexadecimal, octal, and binary literals

Integers may be coded in decimal (base 10), hexadecimal (base 16), octal (base 8), or binary (base 2). Hexadecimals start with a leading 0x or 0X, followed by a string of hexadecimal digits (0–9 and A–F). Hex digits may be coded in lower- or uppercase. Octal literals start with a leading 0o or 0O (zero and lower- or uppercase letter “o”), followed by a string of digits (0–7). In 2.6 and earlier, octal literals can also be coded with just a leading 0, but not in 3.0 (this original octal form is too easily confused with decimal, and is replaced by the new 0o format). Binary literals, new in 2.6 and 3.0, begin with a leading 0b or 0B, followed by binary digits (0–1).

Note that all of these literals produce integer objects in program code; they are just alternative syntaxes for specifying values. The built-in calls hex(I), oct(I), and bin(I) convert an integer to its representation string in these three bases, and int(str, base) converts a runtime string to an integer per a given base.

Complex numbers

Python complex literals are written as realpart+imaginarypart, where the imaginarypart is terminated with a j or J. The realpart is technically optional, so the imaginarypart may appear on its own. Internally, complex numbers are implemented as pairs of floating-point numbers, but all numeric operations perform complex math when applied to complex numbers. Complex numbers may also be created with the complex(real, imag) built-in call.

Coding other numeric types

As we’ll see later in this chapter, there are additional, more advanced number types not included in Table 5-1. Some of these are created by calling functions in imported modules (e.g., decimals and fractions), and others have literal syntax all their own (e.g., sets).

Built-in Numeric Tools

Besides the built-in number literals shown in Table 5-1, Python provides a set of tools for processing number objects:

Expression operators

+, -, *, /, >>, **, &, etc.

Built-in mathematical functions

pow, abs, round, int, hex, bin, etc.

Utility modules

random, math, etc.

We’ll meet all of these as we go along.

Although numbers are primarily processed with expressions, built-ins, and modules, they also have a handful of type-specific methods today, which we’ll meet in this chapter as well. Floating-point numbers, for example, have an as_integer_ratio method that is useful for the fraction number type, and an is_integer method to test if the number is an integer. Integers have various attributes, including a new bit_length method in the upcoming Python 3.1 release that gives the number of bits necessary to represent the object’s value. Moreover, as part collection and part number, sets also support both methods and expressions.

Since expressions are the most essential tool for most number types, though, let’s turn to them next.

Python Expression Operators

Perhaps the most fundamental tool that processes numbers is the expression: a combination of numbers (or other objects) and operators that computes a value when executed by Python. In Python, expressions are written using the usual mathematical notation and operator symbols. For instance, to add two numbers X and Y you would say X + Y, which tells Python to apply the + operator to the values named by X and Y. The result of the expression is the sum of X and Y, another number object.

Table 5-2 lists all the operator expressions available in Python. Many are self-explanatory; for instance, the usual mathematical operators (+, −, *, /, and so on) are supported. A few will be familiar if you’ve used other languages in the past: % computes a division remainder, << performs a bitwise left-shift, & computes a bitwise AND result, and so on. Others are more Python-specific, and not all are numeric in nature: for example, the is operator tests object identity (i.e., address in memory, a strict form of equality), and lambda creates unnamed functions.

Table 5-2. Python expression operators and precedence

Operators

|

Description

yield x

|

Generator function send protocol

lambda args: expression

|

Anonymous function generation

x if y else z

|

Ternary selection (x is evaluated only if y is true)

x or y

|

Logical OR (y is evaluated only if x is false)

x and y

|

Logical AND (y is evaluated only if x is true)

not x

|

Logical negation

x in y, x not in y

|

Membership (iterables, sets)

x is y, x is not y

|

Object identity tests

x < y, x <= y, x > y, x >= y

x == y, x != y

|

Magnitude comparison, set subset and superset;

Value equality operators

x | y

|

Bitwise OR, set union

x ^ y

|

Bitwise XOR, set symmetric difference

x & y

|

Bitwise AND, set intersection

x << y, x >> y

|

Shift x left or right by y bits

x + y

x – y

|

Addition, concatenation;

Subtraction, set difference

x * y

x % y

x / y, x // y

|

Multiplication, repetition;

Remainder, format;

Division: true and floor

−x, +x

|

Negation, identity

˜x

|

Bitwise NOT (inversion)

x ** y

|

Power (exponentiation)

x[i]

|

Indexing (sequence, mapping, others)

x[i:j:k]

|

Slicing

x(...)

|

Call (function, method, class, other callable)

x.attr

|

Attribute reference

(...)

|

Tuple, expression, generator expression

[...]

|

List, list comprehension

{...}

|

Dictionary, set, set and dictionary comprehensions

Since this book addresses both Python 2.6 and 3.0, here are some notes about version differences and recent additions related to the operators in Table 5-2:

In Python 2.6, value inequality can be written as either X != Y or X <> Y. In Python 3.0, the latter of these options is removed because it is redundant. In either version, best practice is to use X != Y for all value inequality tests.

In Python 2.6, a backquotes expression `X` works the same as repr(X) and converts objects to display strings. Due to its obscurity, this expression is removed in Python 3.0; use the more readable str and repr built-in functions, described in Numeric Display Formats.

The X // Y floor division expression always truncates fractional remainders in both Python 2.6 and 3.0. The X / Y expression performs true division in 3.0 (retaining remainders) and classic division in 2.6 (truncating for integers). See Division: Classic, Floor, and True.

The syntax [...] is used for both list literals and list comprehension expressions. The latter of these performs an implied loop and collects expression results in a new list. See Chapters 4, 14, and 20 for examples.

The syntax (...) is used for tuples and expressions, as well as generator expressions—a form of list comprehension that produces results on demand, instead of building a result list. See Chapters 4 and 20 for examples. The parentheses may sometimes be omitted in all three constructs.

The syntax {...} is used for dictionary literals, and in Python 3.0 for set literals and both dictionary and set comprehensions. See the set coverage in this chapter and Chapters 4, 8, 14, and 20 for examples.

The yield and ternary if/else selection expressions are available in Python 2.5 and later. The former returns send(...) arguments in generators; the latter is shorthand for a multiline if statement. yield requires parentheses if not alone on the right side of an assignment statement.

Comparison operators may be chained: X < Y < Z produces the same result as X < Y and Y < Z. See Comparisons: Normal and Chained for details.

In recent Pythons, the slice expression X[I:J:K] is equivalent to indexing with a slice object: X[slice(I, J, K)].

In Python 2.X, magnitude comparisons of mixed types—converting numbers to a common type, and ordering other mixed types according to the type name—are allowed. In Python 3.0, nonnumeric mixed-type magnitude comparisons are not allowed and raise exceptions; this includes sorts by proxy.

Magnitude comparisons for dictionaries are also no longer supported in Python 3.0 (though equality tests are); comparing sorted(dict.items()) is one possible replacement.

We’ll see most of the operators in Table 5-2 in action later; first, though, we need to take a quick look at the ways these operators may be combined in expressions.

Mixed operators follow operator precedence

As in most languages, in Python, more complex expressions are coded by stringing together the operator expressions in Table 5-2. For instance, the sum of two multiplications might be written as a mix of variables and operators:

A * B + C * D

So, how does Python know which operation to perform first? The answer to this question lies in operator precedence. When you write an expression with more than one operator, Python groups its parts according to what are called precedence rules, and this grouping determines the order in which the expression’s parts are computed. Table 5-2 is ordered by operator precedence:

Operators lower in the table have higher precedence, and so bind more tightly in mixed expressions.

Operators in the same row in Table 5-2 generally group from left to right when combined (except for exponentiation, which groups right to left, and comparisons, which chain left to right).

For example, if you write X + Y * Z, Python evaluates the multiplication first (Y * Z), then adds that result to X because * has higher precedence (is lower in the table) than +. Similarly, in this section’s original example, both multiplications (A * B and C * D) will happen before their results are added.

Parentheses group subexpressions

You can forget about precedence completely if you’re careful to group parts of expressions with parentheses. When you enclose subexpressions in parentheses, you override Python’s precedence rules; Python always evaluates expressions in parentheses first before using their results in the enclosing expressions.

For instance, instead of coding X + Y * Z, you could write one of the following to force Python to evaluate the expression in the desired order:

(X + Y) * Z
X + (Y * Z)

In the first case, + is applied to X and Y first, because this subexpression is wrapped in parentheses. In the second case, the * is performed first (just as if there were no parentheses at all). Generally speaking, adding parentheses in large expressions is a good idea—it not only forces the evaluation order you want, but also aids readability.

Mixed types are converted up

Besides mixing operators in expressions, you can also mix numeric types. For instance, you can add an integer to a floating-point number:

40 + 3.14

But this leads to another question: what type is the result—integer or floating-point? The answer is simple, especially if you’ve used almost any other language before: in mixed-type numeric expressions, Python first converts operands up to the type of the most complicated operand, and then performs the math on same-type operands. This behavior is similar to type conversions in the C language.

Python ranks the complexity of numeric types like so: integers are simpler than floating-point numbers, which are simpler than complex numbers. So, when an integer is mixed with a floating point, as in the preceding example, the integer is converted up to a floating-point value first, and floating-point math yields the floating-point result. Similarly, any mixed-type expression where one operand is a complex number results in the other operand being converted up to a complex number, and the expression yields a complex result. (In Python 2.6, normal integers are also converted to long integers whenever their values are too large to fit in a normal integer; in 3.0, integers subsume longs entirely.)

You can force the issue by calling built-in functions to convert types manually:

>>> int(3.1415)     # Truncates float to integer
3
>>> float(3)        # Converts integer to float
3.0

However, you won’t usually need to do this: because Python automatically converts up to the more complex type within an expression, the results are normally what you want.

Also, keep in mind that all these mixed-type conversions apply only when mixing numeric types (e.g., an integer and a floating-point) in an expression, including those using numeric and comparison operators. In general, Python does not convert across any other type boundaries automatically. Adding a string to an integer, for example, results in an error, unless you manually convert one or the other; watch for an example when we meet strings in Chapter 7.

Note

In Python 2.6, nonnumeric mixed types can be compared, but no conversions are performed (mixed types compare according to a fixed but arbitrary rule). In 3.0, nonnumeric mixed-type comparisons are not allowed and raise exceptions.

Preview: Operator overloading and polymorphism

Although we’re focusing on built-in numbers right now, all Python operators may be overloaded (i.e., implemented) by Python classes and C extension types to work on objects you create. For instance, you’ll see later that objects coded with classes may be added or concatenated with + expressions, indexed with [i] expressions, and so on.

Furthermore, Python itself automatically overloads some operators, such that they perform different actions depending on the type of built-in objects being processed. For example, the + operator performs addition when applied to numbers but performs concatenation when applied to sequence objects such as strings and lists. In fact, + can mean anything at all when applied to objects you define with classes.

As we saw in the prior chapter, this property is usually called polymorphism—a term indicating that the meaning of an operation depends on the type of the objects being operated on. We’ll revisit this concept when we explore functions in Chapter 16, because it becomes a much more obvious feature in that context.

Numbers in Action

On to the code! Probably the best way to understand numeric objects and expressions is to see them in action, so let’s start up the interactive command line and try some basic but illustrative operations (see Chapter 3 for pointers if you need help starting an interactive session).

Variables and Basic Expressions

First of all, let’s exercise some basic math. In the following interaction, we first assign two variables (a and b) to integers so we can use them later in a larger expression. Variables are simply names—created by you or Python—that are used to keep track of information in your program. We’ll say more about this in the next chapter, but in Python:

Variables are created when they are first assigned values.

Variables are replaced with their values when used in expressions.

Variables must be assigned before they can be used in expressions.

Variables refer to objects and are never declared ahead of time.

In other words, these assignments cause the variables a and b to spring into existence automatically:

% python
>>> a = 3                  # Name created
>>> b = 4

I’ve also used a comment here. Recall that in Python code, text after a # mark and continuing to the end of the line is considered to be a comment and is ignored. Comments are a way to write human-readable documentation for your code. Because code you type interactively is temporary, you won’t normally write comments in this context, but I’ve added them to some of this book’s examples to help explain the code.[15] In the next part of the book, we’ll meet a related feature—documentation strings—that attaches the text of your comments to objects.

Now, let’s use our new integer objects in some expressions. At this point, the values of a and b are still 3 and 4, respectively. Variables like these are replaced with their values whenever they’re used inside an expression, and the expression results are echoed back immediately when working interactively:

>>> a + 1, a – 1           # Addition (3 + 1), subtraction (3 - 1)
(4, 2)
>>> b * 3, b / 2           # Multiplication (4 * 3), division (4 / 2)
(12, 2.0)
>>> a % 2, b ** 2          # Modulus (remainder), power (4 ** 2)
(1, 16)
>>> 2 + 4.0, 2.0 ** b      # Mixed-type conversions
(6.0, 16.0)

Technically, the results being echoed back here are tuples of two values because the lines typed at the prompt contain two expressions separated by commas; that’s why the results are displayed in parentheses (more on tuples later). Note that the expressions work because the variables a and b within them have been assigned values. If you use a different variable that has never been assigned, Python reports an error rather than filling in some default value:

>>> c * 2
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "<stdin>", line 1, in ?
NameError: name 'c' is not defined

You don’t need to predeclare variables in Python, but they must have been assigned at least once before you can use them. In practice, this means you have to initialize counters to zero before you can add to them, initialize lists to an empty list before you can append to them, and so on.

Here are two slightly larger expressions to illustrate operator grouping and more about conversions:

>>> b / 2 + a               # Same as ((4 / 2) + 3)
5.0
>>> print(b / (2.0 + a))    # Same as (4 / (2.0 + 3))
0.8

In the first expression, there are no parentheses, so Python automatically groups the components according to its precedence rules—because / is lower in Table 5-2 than +, it binds more tightly and so is evaluated first. The result is as if the expression had been organized with parentheses as shown in the comment to the right of the code.

Also, notice that all the numbers are integers in the first expression. Because of that, Python 2.6 performs integer division and addition and will give a result of 5, whereas Python 3.0 performs true division with remainders and gives the result shown. If you want integer division in 3.0, code this as b // 2 + a (more on division in a moment).

In the second expression, parentheses are added around the + part to force Python to evaluate it first (i.e., before the /). We also made one of the operands floating-point by adding a decimal point: 2.0. Because of the mixed types, Python converts the integer referenced by a to a floating-point value (3.0) before performing the +. If all the numbers in this expression were integers, integer division (4 / 5) would yield the truncated integer 0 in Python 2.6 but the floating-point 0.8 in Python 3.0 (again, stay tuned for division details).

Numeric Display Formats

Notice that we used a print operation in the last of the preceding examples. Without the print, you’ll see something that may look a bit odd at first glance:

>>> b / (2.0 + a)           # Auto echo output: more digits
0.80000000000000004

>>> print(b / (2.0 + a))    # print rounds off digits
0.8

The full story behind this odd result has to do with the limitations of floating-point hardware and its inability to exactly represent some values in a limited number of bits. Because computer architecture is well beyond this book’s scope, though, we’ll finesse this by saying that all of the digits in the first output are really there in your computer’s floating-point hardware—it’s just that you’re not accustomed to seeing them. In fact, this is really just a display issue—the interactive prompt’s automatic result echo shows more digits than the print statement. If you don’t want to see all the digits, use print; as the sidebar str and repr Display Formats will explain, you’ll get a user-friendly display.

Note, however, that not all values have so many digits to display:

>>> 1 / 2.0
0.5

and that there are more ways to display the bits of a number inside your computer than using print and automatic echoes:

>>> num = 1 / 3.0
>>> num                      # Echoes
0.33333333333333331
>>> print(num)               # print rounds
0.333333333333

>>> '%e' % num               # String formatting expression
'3.333333e-001'
>>> '%4.2f' % num            # Alternative floating-point format
'0.33'
>>> '{0:4.2f}'.format(num)   # String formatting method (Python 2.6 and 3.0)
'0.33'

The last three of these expressions employ string formatting, a tool that allows for format flexibility, which we will explore in the upcoming chapter on strings (Chapter 7). Its results are strings that are typically printed to displays or reports.

str and repr Display Formats

Technically, the difference between default interactive echoes and print corresponds to the difference between the built-in repr and str functions:

>>> num = 1 / 3
>>> repr(num)              # Used by echoes: as-code form
'0.33333333333333331'
>>> str(num)               # Used by print: user-friendly form
'0.333333333333'

Both of these convert arbitrary objects to their string representations: repr (and the default interactive echo) produces results that look as though they were code; str (and the print operation) converts to a typically more user-friendly format if available. Some objects have both—a str for general use, and a repr with extra details. This notion will resurface when we study both strings and operator overloading in classes, and you’ll find more on these built-ins in general later in the book.

Besides providing print strings for arbitrary objects, the str built-in is also the name of the string data type and may be called with an encoding name to decode a Unicode string from a byte string. We’ll study the latter advanced role in Chapter 36 of this book.

Comparisons: Normal and Chained

So far, we’ve been dealing with standard numeric operations (addition and multiplication), but numbers can also be compared. Normal comparisons work for numbers exactly as you’d expect—they compare the relative magnitudes of their operands and return a Boolean result (which we would normally test in a larger statement):

>>> 1 < 2                  # Less than
True
>>> 2.0 >= 1               # Greater than or equal: mixed-type 1 converted to 1.0
True
>>> 2.0 == 2.0             # Equal value
True
>>> 2.0 != 2.0             # Not equal value
False

Notice again how mixed types are allowed in numeric expressions (only); in the second test here, Python compares values in terms of the more complex type, float.

Interestingly, Python also allows us to chain multiple comparisons together to perform range tests. Chained comparisons are a sort of shorthand for larger Boolean expressions. In short, Python lets us string together magnitude comparison tests to code chained comparisons such as range tests. The expression (A < B < C), for instance, tests whether B is between A and C; it is equivalent to the Boolean test (A < B and B < C) but is easier on the eyes (and the keyboard). For example, assume the following assignments:

>>> X = 2
>>> Y = 4
>>> Z = 6

The following two expressions have identical effects, but the first is shorter to type, and it may run slightly faster since Python needs to evaluate Y only once:

>>> X < Y < Z              # Chained comparisons: range tests
True
>>> X < Y and Y < Z
True

The same equivalence holds for false results, and arbitrary chain lengths are allowed:

>>> X < Y > Z
False
>>> X < Y and Y > Z
False

>>> 1 < 2 < 3.0 < 4
True
>>> 1 > 2 > 3.0 > 4
False

You can use other comparisons in chained tests, but the resulting expressions can become nonintuitive unless you evaluate them the way Python does. The following, for instance, is false just because 1 is not equal to 2:

>>> 1 == 2 < 3        # Same as: 1 == 2 and 2 < 3
False                 # Not same as: False < 3 (which means 0 < 3, which is true)

Python does not compare the 1 == 2 False result to 3—this would technically mean the same as 0 < 3, which would be True (as we’ll see later in this chapter, True and False are just customized 1 and 0).

Division: Classic, Floor, and True

You’ve seen how division works in the previous sections, so you should know that it behaves slightly differently in Python 3.0 and 2.6. In fact, there are actually three flavors of division, and two different division operators, one of which changes in 3.0:

X / Y

Classic and true division. In Python 2.6 and earlier, this operator performs classic division, truncating results for integers and keeping remainders for floating-point numbers. In Python 3.0, it performs true division, always keeping remainders regardless of types.

X // Y

Floor division. Added in Python 2.2 and available in both Python 2.6 and 3.0, this operator always truncates fractional remainders down to their floor, regardless of types.

True division was added to address the fact that the results of the original classic division model are dependent on operand types, and so can be difficult to anticipate in a dynamically typed language like Python. Classic division was removed in 3.0 because of this constraint—the / and // operators implement true and floor division in 3.0.

In sum:

In 3.0, the / now always performs true division, returning a float result that includes any remainder, regardless of operand types. The // performs floor division, which truncates the remainder and returns an integer for integer operands or a float if any operand is a float.

In 2.6, the / does classic division, performing truncating integer division if both operands are integers and float division (keeping remainders) otherwise. The // does floor division and works as it does in 3.0, performing truncating division for integers and floor division for floats.

Here are the two operators at work in 3.0 and 2.6:

C:\misc> C:\Python30\python
>>>
>>> 10 / 4            # Differs in 3.0: keeps remainder
2.5
>>> 10 // 4           # Same in 3.0: truncates remainder
2
>>> 10 / 4.0          # Same in 3.0: keeps remainder
2.5
>>> 10 // 4.0         # Same in 3.0: truncates to floor
2.0

C:\misc> C:\Python26\python
>>>
>>> 10 / 4
2
>>> 10 // 4
2
>>> 10 / 4.0
2.5
>>> 10 // 4.0
2.0

Notice that the data type of the result for // is still dependent on the operand types in 3.0: if either is a float, the result is a float; otherwise, it is an integer. Although this may seem similar to the type-dependent behavior of / in 2.X that motivated its change in 3.0, the type of the return value is much less critical than differences in the return value itself. Moreover, because // was provided in part as a backward-compatibility tool for programs that rely on truncating integer division (and this is more common than you might expect), it must return integers for integers.

Supporting either Python

Although / behavior differs in 2.6 and 3.0, you can still support both versions in your code. If your programs depend on truncating integer division, use // in both 2.6 and 3.0. If your programs require floating-point results with remainders for integers, use float to guarantee that one operand is a float around a / when run in 2.6:

X = Y // Z        # Always truncates, always an int result for ints in 2.6 and 3.0

X = Y / float(Z)  # Guarantees float division with remainder in either 2.6 or 3.0

Alternatively, you can enable 3.0 / division in 2.6 with a __future__ import, rather than forcing it with float conversions:

C:\misc> C:\Python26\python
>>> from __future__ import division         # Enable 3.0 "/" behavior
>>> 10 / 4
2.5
>>> 10 // 4
2

Floor versus truncation

One subtlety: the // operator is generally referred to as truncating division, but it’s more accurate to refer to it as floor division—it truncates the result down to its floor, which means the closest whole number below the true result. The net effect is to round down, not strictly truncate, and this matters for negatives. You can see the difference for yourself with the Python math module (modules must be imported before you can use their contents; more on this later):

>>> import math
>>> math.floor(2.5)
2
>>> math.floor(-2.5)
-3
>>> math.trunc(2.5)
2
>>> math.trunc(-2.5)
-2

When running division operators, you only really truncate for positive results, since truncation is the same as floor; for negatives, it’s a floor result (really, they are both floor, but floor is the same as truncation for positives). Here’s the case for 3.0:

C:\misc> c:\python30\python
>>> 5 / 2, 5 / −2
(2.5, −2.5)

>>> 5 // 2, 5 // −2           # Truncates to floor: rounds to first lower integer
(2, −3)                       # 2.5 becomes 2, −2.5 becomes −3

>>> 5 / 2.0, 5 / −2.0
(2.5, −2.5)

>>> 5 // 2.0, 5 // −2.0       # Ditto for floats, though result is float too
(2.0, −3.0)

The 2.6 case is similar, but / results differ again:

C:\misc> c:\python26\python
>>> 5 / 2, 5 / −2             # Differs in 3.0
(2, −3)

>>> 5 // 2, 5 // −2           # This and the rest are the same in 2.6 and 3.0
(2, −3)

>>> 5 / 2.0, 5 / −2.0
(2.5, −2.5)

>>> 5 // 2.0, 5 // −2.0
(2.0, −3.0)

If you really want truncation regardless of sign, you can always run a float division result through math.trunc, regardless of Python version (also see the round built-in for related functionality):

C:\misc> c:\python30\python
>>> import math
>>> 5 / −2                      # Keep remainder
−2.5
>>> 5 // −2                     # Floor below result
-3
>>> math.trunc(5 / −2)          # Truncate instead of floor
−2

C:\misc> c:\python26\python
>>> import math
>>> 5 / float(−2)               # Remainder in 2.6
−2.5
>>> 5 / −2, 5 // −2             # Floor in 2.6
(−3, −3)
>>> math.trunc(5 / float(−2))   # Truncate in 2.6
−2

Why does truncation matter?

If you are using 3.0, here is the short story on division operators for reference:

>>> (5 / 2), (5 / 2.0), (5 / −2.0), (5 / −2)        # 3.0 true division
(2.5, 2.5, −2.5, −2.5)

>>> (5 // 2), (5 // 2.0), (5 // −2.0), (5 // −2)    # 3.0 floor division
(2, 2.0, −3.0, −3)

>>> (9 / 3), (9.0 / 3), (9 // 3), (9 // 3.0)        # Both
(3.0, 3.0, 3, 3.0)

For 2.6 readers, division works as follows:

>>> (5 / 2), (5 / 2.0), (5 / −2.0), (5 / −2)        # 2.6 classic division
(2, 2.5, −2.5, −3)

>>> (5 // 2), (5 // 2.0), (5 // −2.0), (5 // −2)    # 2.6 floor division (same)
(2, 2.0, −3.0, −3)

>>> (9 / 3), (9.0 / 3), (9 // 3), (9 // 3.0)        # Both
(3, 3.0, 3, 3.0)

Although results have yet to come in, it’s possible that the nontruncating behavior of / in 3.0 may break a significant number of programs. Perhaps because of a C language legacy, many programmers rely on division truncation for integers and will have to learn to use // in such contexts instead. Watch for a simple prime number while loop example in Chapter 13, and a corresponding exercise at the end of Part IV that illustrates the sort of code that may be impacted by this / change. Also stay tuned for more on the special from command used in this section; it’s discussed further in Chapter 24.

Integer Precision

Division may differ slightly across Python releases, but it’s still fairly standard. Here’s something a bit more exotic. As mentioned earlier, Python 3.0 integers support unlimited size:

>>> 999999999999999999999999999999 + 1
1000000000000000000000000000000

Python 2.6 has a separate type for long integers, but it automatically converts any number too large to store in a normal integer to this type. Hence, you don’t need to code any special syntax to use longs, and the only way you can tell that you’re using 2.6 longs is that they print with a trailing “L”:

>>> 999999999999999999999999999999 + 1
1000000000000000000000000000000L

Unlimited-precision integers are a convenient built-in tool. For instance, you can use them to count the U.S. national debt in pennies in Python directly (if you are so inclined, and have enough memory on your computer for this year’s budget!). They are also why we were able to raise 2 to such large powers in the examples in Chapter 3. Here are the 3.0 and 2.6 cases:

>>> 2 ** 200
1606938044258990275541962092341162602522202993782792835301376

>>> 2 ** 200
1606938044258990275541962092341162602522202993782792835301376L

Because Python must do extra work to support their extended precision, integer math is usually substantially slower than normal when numbers grow large. However, if you need the precision, the fact that it’s built in for you to use will likely outweigh its performance penalty.

Complex Numbers

Although less widely used than the types we’ve been exploring thus far, complex numbers are a distinct core object type in Python. If you know what they are, you know why they are useful; if not, consider this section optional reading.

Complex numbers are represented as two floating-point numbers—the real and imaginary parts—and are coded by adding a j or J suffix to the imaginary part. We can also write complex numbers with a nonzero real part by adding the two parts with a +. For example, the complex number with a real part of 2 and an imaginary part of −3 is written 2 + −3j. Here are some examples of complex math at work:

>>> 1j * 1J
(-1+0j)
>>> 2 + 1j * 3
(2+3j)
>>> (2 + 1j) * 3
(6+3j)

Complex numbers also allow us to extract their parts as attributes, support all the usual mathematical expressions, and may be processed with tools in the standard cmath module (the complex version of the standard math module). Complex numbers typically find roles in engineering-oriented programs. Because they are advanced tools, check Python’s language reference manual for additional details.

Hexadecimal, Octal, and Binary Notation

As described earlier in this chapter, Python integers can be coded in hexadecimal, octal, and binary notation, in addition to the normal base 10 decimal coding. The coding rules were laid out at the start of this chapter; let’s look at some live examples here.

Keep in mind that these literals are simply an alternative syntax for specifying the value of an integer object. For example, the following literals coded in Python 3.0 or 2.6 produce normal integers with the specified values in all three bases:

>>> 0o1, 0o20, 0o377           # Octal literals
(1, 16, 255)
>>> 0x01, 0x10, 0xFF           # Hex literals
(1, 16, 255)
>>> 0b1, 0b10000, 0b11111111   # Binary literals
(1, 16, 255)

Here, the octal value 0o377, the hex value 0xFF, and the binary value 0b11111111 are all decimal 255. Python prints in decimal (base 10) by default but provides built-in functions that allow you to convert integers to other bases’ digit strings:

>>> oct(64), hex(64), bin(64)
('0o100', '0x40', '0b1000000')

The oct function converts decimal to octal, hex to hexadecimal, and bin to binary. To go the other way, the built-in int function converts a string of digits to an integer, and an optional second argument lets you specify the numeric base:

>>> int('64'), int('100', 8), int('40', 16), int('1000000', 2)
(64, 64, 64, 64)

>>> int('0x40', 16), int('0b1000000', 2)    # Literals okay too
(64, 64)

The eval function, which you’ll meet later in this book, treats strings as though they were Python code. Therefore, it has a similar effect (but usually runs more slowly—it actually compiles and runs the string as a piece of a program, and it assumes you can trust the source of the string being run; a clever user might be able to submit a string that deletes files on your machine!):

>>> eval('64'), eval('0o100'), eval('0x40'), eval('0b1000000')
(64, 64, 64, 64)

Finally, you can also convert integers to octal and hexadecimal strings with string formatting method calls and expressions:

>>> '{0:o}, {1:x}, {2:b}'.format(64, 64, 64)
'100, 40, 1000000'

>>> '%o, %x, %X' % (64, 255, 255)
'100, ff, FF'

String formatting is covered in more detail in Chapter 7.

Two notes before moving on. First, Python 2.6 users should remember that you can code octals with simply a leading zero, the original octal format in Python:

>>> 0o1, 0o20, 0o377     # New octal format in 2.6 (same as 3.0)
(1, 16, 255)
>>> 01, 020, 0377        # Old octal literals in 2.6 (and earlier)
(1, 16, 255)

In 3.0, the syntax in the second of these examples generates an error. Even though it’s not an error in 2.6, be careful not to begin a string of digits with a leading zero unless you really mean to code an octal value. Python 2.6 will treat it as base 8, which may not work as you’d expect—010 is always decimal 8 in 2.6, not decimal 10 (despite what you may or may not think!). This, along with symmetry with the hex and binary forms, is why the octal format was changed in 3.0—you must use 0o010 in 3.0, and probably should in 2.6.

Secondly, note that these literals can produce arbitrarily long integers. The following, for instance, creates an integer with hex notation and then displays it first in decimal and then in octal and binary with converters (run in 2.6 here to reveal the long precision):

>>> X = 0xFFFFFFFFFFFFFFFFFFFFFFFFFFFF
>>> X
5192296858534827628530496329220095L
>>> oct(X)
'017777777777777777777777777777777777777L'
>>> bin(X)
'0b1111111111111111111111111111111111111111111111111111111111 ...and so on...

Speaking of binary digits, the next section shows tools for processing individual bits.

Bitwise Operations

Besides the normal numeric operations (addition, subtraction, and so on), Python supports most of the numeric expressions available in the C language. This includes operators that treat integers as strings of binary bits. For instance, here it is at work performing bitwise shift and Boolean operations:

>>> x = 1               # 0001
>>> x << 2              # Shift left 2 bits: 0100
4
>>> x | 2               # Bitwise OR: 0011
3
>>> x & 1               # Bitwise AND: 0001
1

In the first expression, a binary 1 (in base 2, 0001) is shifted left two slots to create a binary 4 (0100). The last two operations perform a binary OR (0001|0010 = 0011) and a binary AND (0001&0001 = 0001). Such bit-masking operations allow us to encode multiple flags and other values within a single integer.

This is one area where the binary and hexadecimal number support in Python 2.6 and 3.0 become especially useful—they allow us to code and inspect numbers by bit-strings:

>>> X = 0b0001          # Binary literals
>>> X << 2              # Shift left
4
>>> bin(X << 2)         # Binary digits string
'0b100'

>>> bin(X | 0b010)      # Bitwise OR
'0b11'
>>> bin(X & 0b1)        # Bitwise AND
'0b1'

>>> X = 0xFF            # Hex literals
>>> bin(X)
'0b11111111'
>>> X ^ 0b10101010      # Bitwise XOR
85
>>> bin(X ^ 0b10101010)
'0b1010101'

>>> int('1010101', 2)   # String to int per base
85
>>> hex(85)             # Hex digit string
'0x55'

We won’t go into much more detail on “bit-twiddling” here. It’s supported if you need it, and it comes in handy if your Python code must deal with things like network packets or packed binary data produced by a C program. Be aware, though, that bitwise operations are often not as important in a high-level language such as Python as they are in a low-level language such as C. As a rule of thumb, if you find yourself wanting to flip bits in Python, you should think about which language you’re really coding. In general, there are often better ways to encode information in Python than bit strings.

Note

In the upcoming Python 3.1 release, the integer bit_length method also allows you to query the number of bits required to represent a number’s value in binary. The same effect can often be achieved by subtracting 2 from the length of the bin string using the len built-in function we met in Chapter 4, though it may be less efficient:

>>> X = 99
>>> bin(X), X.bit_length()
('0b1100011', 7)
>>> bin(256), (256).bit_length()
('0b100000000', 9)
>>> len(bin(256)) - 2
9

Other Built-in Numeric Tools

In addition to its core object types, Python also provides both built-in functions and standard library modules for numeric processing. The pow and abs built-in functions, for instance, compute powers and absolute values, respectively. Here are some examples of the built-in math module (which contains most of the tools in the C language’s math library) and a few built-in functions at work:

>>> import math
>>> math.pi, math.e                               # Common constants
(3.1415926535897931, 2.7182818284590451)

>>> math.sin(2 * math.pi / 180)                   # Sine, tangent, cosine
0.034899496702500969

>>> math.sqrt(144), math.sqrt(2)                  # Square root
(12.0, 1.4142135623730951)

>>> pow(2, 4), 2 ** 4                             # Exponentiation (power)
(16, 16)

>>> abs(-42.0), sum((1, 2, 3, 4))                 # Absolute value, summation
(42.0, 10)

>>> min(3, 1, 2, 4), max(3, 1, 2, 4)              # Minimum, maximum
(1, 4)

The sum function shown here works on a sequence of numbers, and min and max accept either a sequence or individual arguments. There are a variety of ways to drop the decimal digits of floating-point numbers. We met truncation and floor earlier; we can also round, both numerically and for display purposes:

>>> math.floor(2.567), math.floor(-2.567)         # Floor (next-lower integer)
(2, −3)

>>> math.trunc(2.567), math.trunc(−2.567)         # Truncate (drop decimal digits)
(2, −2)

>>> int(2.567), int(−2.567)                       # Truncate (integer conversion)
(2, −2)

>>> round(2.567), round(2.467), round(2.567, 2)   # Round (Python 3.0 version)
(3, 2, 2.5699999999999998)

>>> '%.1f' % 2.567, '{0:.2f}'.format(2.567)       # Round for display (Chapter 7)
('2.6', '2.57')

As we saw earlier, the last of these produces strings that we would usually print and supports a variety of formatting options. As also described earlier, the second to last test here will output (3, 2, 2.57) if we wrap it in a print call to request a more user-friendly display. The last two lines still differ, though—round rounds a floating-point number but still yields a floating-point number in memory, whereas string formatting produces a string and doesn’t yield a modified number:

>>> (1 / 3), round(1 / 3, 2), ('%.2f' % (1 / 3))
(0.33333333333333331, 0.33000000000000002, '0.33')

Interestingly, there are three ways to compute square roots in Python: using a module function, an expression, or a built-in function (if you’re interested in performance, we will revisit these in an exercise and its solution at the end of Part IV, to see which runs quicker):

>>> import math
>>> math.sqrt(144)              # Module
12.0
>>> 144 ** .5                   # Expression
12.0
>>> pow(144, .5)                # Built-in
12.0

>>> math.sqrt(1234567890)       # Larger numbers
35136.418286444619
>>> 1234567890 ** .5
35136.418286444619
>>> pow(1234567890, .5)
35136.418286444619

Notice that standard library modules such as math must be imported, but built-in functions such as abs and round are always available without imports. In other words, modules are external components, but built-in functions live in an implied namespace that Python automatically searches to find names used in your program. This namespace corresponds to the module called builtins in Python 3.0 (__builtin__ in 2.6). There is much more about name resolution in the function and module parts of this book; for now, when you hear “module,” think “import.”

The standard library random module must be imported as well. This module provides tools for picking a random floating-point number between 0 and 1, selecting a random integer between two numbers, choosing an item at random from a sequence, and more:

>>> import random
>>> random.random()
0.44694718823781876
>>> random.random()
0.28970426439292829

>>> random.randint(1, 10)
5
>>> random.randint(1, 10)
4

>>> random.choice(['Life of Brian', 'Holy Grail', 'Meaning of Life'])
'Life of Brian'
>>> random.choice(['Life of Brian', 'Holy Grail', 'Meaning of Life'])
'Holy Grail'

The random module can be useful for shuffling cards in games, picking images at random in a slideshow GUI, performing statistical simulations, and much more. For more details, see Python’s library manual.

Other Numeric Types

So far in this chapter, we’ve been using Python’s core numeric types—integer, floating point, and complex. These will suffice for most of the number crunching that most programmers will ever need to do. Python comes with a handful of more exotic numeric types, though, that merit a quick look here.

Decimal Type

Python 2.4 introduced a new core numeric type: the decimal object, formally known as Decimal. Syntactically, decimals are created by calling a function within an imported module, rather than running a literal expression. Functionally, decimals are like floating-point numbers, but they have a fixed number of decimal points. Hence, decimals are fixed-precision floating-point values.

For example, with decimals, we can have a floating-point value that always retains just two decimal digits. Furthermore, we can specify how to round or truncate the extra decimal digits beyond the object’s cutoff. Although it generally incurs a small performance penalty compared to the normal floating-point type, the decimal type is well suited to representing fixed-precision quantities like sums of money and can help you achieve better numeric accuracy.

The basics

The last point merits elaboration. As you may or may not already know, floating-point math is less than exact, because of the limited space used to store values. For example, the following should yield zero, but it does not. The result is close to zero, but there are not enough bits to be precise here:

>>> 0.1 + 0.1 + 0.1 - 0.3
5.5511151231257827e-17

Printing the result to produce the user-friendly display format doesn’t completely help either, because the hardware related to floating-point math is inherently limited in terms of accuracy:

>>> print(0.1 + 0.1 + 0.1 - 0.3)
5.55111512313e-17

However, with decimals, the result can be dead-on:

>>> from decimal import Decimal
>>> Decimal('0.1') + Decimal('0.1') + Decimal('0.1') - Decimal('0.3')
Decimal('0.0')

As shown here, we can make decimal objects by calling the Decimal constructor function in the decimal module and passing in strings that have the desired number of decimal digits for the resulting object (we can use the str function to convert floating-point values to strings if needed). When decimals of different precision are mixed in expressions, Python converts up to the largest number of decimal digits automatically:

>>> Decimal('0.1') + Decimal('0.10') + Decimal('0.10') - Decimal('0.30')
Decimal('0.00')

Note

In Python 3.1 (to be released after this book’s publication), it’s also possible to create a decimal object from a floating-point object, with a call of the form decimal.Decimal.from_float(1.25). The conversion is exact but can sometimes yield a large number of digits.

Setting precision globally

Other tools in the decimal module can be used to set the precision of all decimal numbers, set up error handling, and more. For instance, a context object in this module allows for specifying precision (number of decimal digits) and rounding modes (down, ceiling, etc.). The precision is applied globally for all decimals created in the calling thread:

>>> import decimal
>>> decimal.Decimal(1) / decimal.Decimal(7)
Decimal('0.1428571428571428571428571429')

>>> decimal.getcontext().prec = 4
>>> decimal.Decimal(1) / decimal.Decimal(7)
Decimal('0.1429')

This is especially useful for monetary applications, where cents are represented as two decimal digits. Decimals are essentially an alternative to manual rounding and string formatting in this context:

>>> 1999 + 1.33
2000.3299999999999
>>>
>>> decimal.getcontext().prec = 2
>>> pay = decimal.Decimal(str(1999 + 1.33))
>>> pay
Decimal('2000.33')

Decimal context manager

In Python 2.6 and 3.0 (and later), it’s also possible to reset precision temporarily by using the with context manager statement. The precision is reset to its original value on statement exit:

C:\misc> C:\Python30\python
>>> import decimal
>>> decimal.Decimal('1.00') / decimal.Decimal('3.00')
Decimal('0.3333333333333333333333333333')
>>>
>>> with decimal.localcontext() as ctx:
...     ctx.prec = 2
...     decimal.Decimal('1.00') / decimal.Decimal('3.00')
...
Decimal('0.33')
>>>
>>> decimal.Decimal('1.00') / decimal.Decimal('3.00')
Decimal('0.3333333333333333333333333333')

Though useful, this statement requires much more background knowledge than you’ve obtained at this point; watch for coverage of the with statement in Chapter 33.

Because use of the decimal type is still relatively rare in practice, I’ll defer to Python’s standard library manuals and interactive help for more details. And because decimals address some of the same floating-point accuracy issues as the fraction type, let’s move on to the next section to see how the two compare.

Fraction Type

Python 2.6 and 3.0 debut a new numeric type, Fraction, which implements a rational number object. It essentially keeps both a numerator and a denominator explicitly, so as to avoid some of the inaccuracies and limitations of floating-point math.

The basics

Fraction is a sort of cousin to the existing Decimal fixed-precision type described in the prior section, as both can be used to control numerical accuracy by fixing decimal digits and specifying rounding or truncation policies. It’s also used in similar ways—like Decimal, Fraction resides in a module; import its constructor and pass in a numerator and a denominator to make one. The following interaction shows how:

>>> from fractions import Fraction
>>> x = Fraction(1, 3)                    # Numerator, denominator
>>> y = Fraction(4, 6)                    # Simplified to 2, 3 by gcd

>>> x
Fraction(1, 3)
>>> y
Fraction(2, 3)
>>> print(y)
2/3

Once created, Fractions can be used in mathematical expressions as usual:

>>> x + y
Fraction(1, 1)
>>> x – y                           # Results are exact: numerator, denominator
Fraction(-1, 3)
>>> x * y
Fraction(2, 9)

Fraction objects can also be created from floating-point number strings, much like decimals:

>>> Fraction('.25')
Fraction(1, 4)
>>> Fraction('1.25')
Fraction(5, 4)
>>>
>>> Fraction('.25') + Fraction('1.25')
Fraction(3, 2)

Numeric accuracy

Notice that this is different from floating-point-type math, which is constrained by the underlying limitations of floating-point hardware. To compare, here are the same operations run with floating-point objects, and notes on their limited accuracy:

>>> a = 1 / 3.0                     # Only as accurate as floating-point hardware
>>> b = 4 / 6.0                     # Can lose precision over calculations
>>> a
0.33333333333333331
>>> b
0.66666666666666663

>>> a + b
1.0
>>> a - b
-0.33333333333333331
>>> a * b
0.22222222222222221

This floating-point limitation is especially apparent for values that cannot be represented accurately given their limited number of bits in memory. Both Fraction and Decimal provide ways to get exact results, albeit at the cost of some speed. For instance, in the following example (repeated from the prior section), floating-point numbers do not accurately give the zero answer expected, but both of the other types do:

>>> 0.1 + 0.1 + 0.1 - 0.3           # This should be zero (close, but not exact)
5.5511151231257827e-17

>>> from fractions import Fraction
>>> Fraction(1, 10) + Fraction(1, 10) + Fraction(1, 10) - Fraction(3, 10)
Fraction(0, 1)

>>> from decimal import Decimal
>>> Decimal('0.1') + Decimal('0.1') + Decimal('0.1') - Decimal('0.3')
Decimal('0.0')

Moreover, fractions and decimals both allow more intuitive and accurate results than floating points sometimes can, in different ways (by using rational representation and by limiting precision):

>>> 1 / 3                              # Use 3.0 in Python 2.6 for true "/"
0.33333333333333331

>>> Fraction(1, 3)                     # Numeric accuracy
Fraction(1, 3)

>>> import decimal
>>> decimal.getcontext().prec = 2
>>> decimal.Decimal(1) / decimal.Decimal(3)
Decimal('0.33')

In fact, fractions both retain accuracy and automatically simplify results. Continuing the preceding interaction:

>>> (1 / 3) + (6 / 12)                 # Use ".0" in Python 2.6 for true "/"
0.83333333333333326

>>> Fraction(6, 12)                    # Automatically simplified
Fraction(1, 2)

>>> Fraction(1, 3) + Fraction(6, 12)
Fraction(5, 6)

>>> decimal.Decimal(str(1/3)) + decimal.Decimal(str(6/12))
Decimal('0.83')

>>> 1000.0 / 1234567890
8.1000000737100011e-07
>>> Fraction(1000, 1234567890)
Fraction(100, 123456789)

Conversions and mixed types

To support fraction conversions, floating-point objects now have a method that yields their numerator and denominator ratio, fractions have a from_float method, and float accepts a Fraction as an argument. Trace through the following interaction to see how this pans out (the * in the second test is special syntax that expands a tuple into individual arguments; more on this when we study function argument passing in Chapter 18):

>>> (2.5).as_integer_ratio()               # float object method
(5, 2)

>>> f = 2.5
>>> z = Fraction(*f.as_integer_ratio())    # Convert float -> fraction: two args
>>> z                                      # Same as Fraction(5, 2)
Fraction(5, 2)

>>> x                                      # x from prior interaction
Fraction(1, 3)
>>> x + z
Fraction(17, 6)                            # 5/2 + 1/3 = 15/6 + 2/6

>>> float(x)                               # Convert fraction -> float
0.33333333333333331
>>> float(z)
2.5
>>> float(x + z)
2.8333333333333335
>>> 17 / 6
2.8333333333333335

>>> Fraction.from_float(1.75)              # Convert float -> fraction: other way
Fraction(7, 4)
>>> Fraction(*(1.75).as_integer_ratio())
Fraction(7, 4)

Finally, some type mixing is allowed in expressions, though Fraction must sometimes be manually propagated to retain accuracy. Study the following interaction to see how this works:

>>> x
Fraction(1, 3)
>>> x + 2                                  # Fraction + int -> Fraction
Fraction(7, 3)
>>> x + 2.0                                # Fraction + float -> float
2.3333333333333335
>>> x + (1./3)                             # Fraction + float -> float
0.66666666666666663

>>> x + (4./3)
1.6666666666666665
>>> x + Fraction(4, 3)                     # Fraction + Fraction -> Fraction
Fraction(5, 3)

Caveat: although you can convert from floating-point to fraction, in some cases there is an unavoidable precision loss when you do so, because the number is inaccurate in its original floating-point form. When needed, you can simplify such results by limiting the maximum denominator value:

>>> 4.0 / 3
1.3333333333333333
>>> (4.0 / 3).as_integer_ratio()                # Precision loss from float
(6004799503160661, 4503599627370496)

>>> x
Fraction(1, 3)
>>> a = x + Fraction(*(4.0 / 3).as_integer_ratio())
>>> a
Fraction(22517998136852479, 13510798882111488)

>>> 22517998136852479 / 13510798882111488.      # 5 / 3 (or close to it!)
1.6666666666666667

>>> a.limit_denominator(10)                     # Simplify to closest fraction
Fraction(5, 3)

For more details on the Fraction type, experiment further on your own and consult the Python 2.6 and 3.0 library manuals and other documentation.

Sets

Python 2.4 also introduced a new collection type, the set—an unordered collection of unique and immutable objects that supports operations corresponding to mathematical set theory. By definition, an item appears only once in a set, no matter how many times it is added. As such, sets have a variety of applications, especially in numeric and database-focused work.

Because sets are collections of other objects, they share some behavior with objects such as lists and dictionaries that are outside the scope of this chapter. For example, sets are iterable, can grow and shrink on demand, and may contain a variety of object types. As we’ll see, a set acts much like the keys of a valueless dictionary, but it supports extra operations.

However, because sets are unordered and do not map keys to values, they are neither sequence nor mapping types; they are a type category unto themselves. Moreover, because sets are fundamentally mathematical in nature (and for many readers, may seem more academic and be used much less often than more pervasive objects like dictionaries), we’ll explore the basic utility of Python’s set objects here.

Set basics in Python 2.6

There are a few ways to make sets today, depending on whether you are using Python 2.6 or 3.0. Since this book covers both, let’s begin with the 2.6 case, which also is available (and sometimes still required) in 3.0; we’ll refine this for 3.0 extensions in a moment. To make a set object, pass in a sequence or other iterable object to the built-in set function:

>>> x = set('abcde')
>>> y = set('bdxyz')

You get back a set object, which contains all the items in the object passed in (notice that sets do not have a positional ordering, and so are not sequences):

>>> x
set(['a', 'c', 'b', 'e', 'd'])                    # 2.6 display format

Sets made this way support the common mathematical set operations with expression operators. Note that we can’t perform these expressions on plain sequences—we must create sets from them in order to apply these tools:

>>> 'e' in x                                      # Membership
True

>>> x – y                                         # Difference
set(['a', 'c', 'e'])

>>> x | y                                         # Union
set(['a', 'c', 'b', 'e', 'd', 'y', 'x', 'z'])

>>> x & y                                         # Intersection
set(['b', 'd'])

>>> x ^ y                                         # Symmetric difference (XOR)
set(['a', 'c', 'e', 'y', 'x', 'z'])

>>> x > y, x < y                                  # Superset, subset
(False, False)

In addition to expressions, the set object provides methods that correspond to these operations and more, and that support set changes—the set add method inserts one item, update is an in-place union, and remove deletes an item by value (run a dir call on any set instance or the set type name to see all the available methods). Assuming x and y are still as they were in the prior interaction:

>>> z = x.intersection(y)                         # Same as x & y
>>> z
set(['b', 'd'])
>>> z.add('SPAM')                                 # Insert one item
>>> z
set(['b', 'd', 'SPAM'])
>>> z.update(set(['X', 'Y']))                     # Merge: in-place union
>>> z
set(['Y', 'X', 'b', 'd', 'SPAM'])
>>> z.remove('b')                                 # Delete one item
>>> z
set(['Y', 'X', 'd', 'SPAM'])

As iterable containers, sets can also be used in operations such as len, for loops, and list comprehensions. Because they are unordered, though, they don’t support sequence operations like indexing and slicing:

>>> for item in set('abc'): print(item * 3)
...
aaa
ccc
bbb

Finally, although the set expressions shown earlier generally require two sets, their method-based counterparts can often work with any iterable type as well:

>>> S = set([1, 2, 3])

>>> S | set([3, 4])          # Expressions require both to be sets
set([1, 2, 3, 4])
>>> S | [3, 4]
TypeError: unsupported operand type(s) for |: 'set' and 'list'

>>> S.union([3, 4])          # But their methods allow any iterable
set([1, 2, 3, 4])
>>> S.intersection((1, 3, 5))
set([1, 3])
>>> S.issubset(range(-5, 5))
True

For more details on set operations, see Python’s library reference manual or a reference book. Although set operations can be coded manually in Python with other types, like lists and dictionaries (and often were in the past), Python’s built-in sets use efficient algorithms and implementation techniques to provide quick and standard operation.

Set literals in Python 3.0

If you think sets are “cool,” they recently became noticeably cooler. In Python 3.0 we can still use the set built-in to make set objects, but 3.0 also adds a new set literal form, using the curly braces formerly reserved for dictionaries. In 3.0, the following are equivalent:

set([1, 2, 3, 4])                # Built-in call
{1, 2, 3, 4}                     # 3.0 set literals

This syntax makes sense, given that sets are essentially like valueless dictionaries—because a set’s items are unordered, unique, and immutable, the items behave much like a dictionary’s keys. This operational similarity is even more striking given that dictionary key lists in 3.0 are view objects, which support set-like behavior such as intersections and unions (see Chapter 8 for more on dictionary view objects).

In fact, regardless of how a set is made, 3.0 displays it using the new literal format. The set built-in is still required in 3.0 to create empty sets and to build sets from existing iterable objects (short of using set comprehensions, discussed later in this chapter), but the new literal is convenient for initializing sets of known structure:

C:\Misc> c:\python30\python
>>> set([1, 2, 3, 4])            # Built-in: same as in 2.6
{1, 2, 3, 4}
>>> set('spam')                  # Add all items in an iterable
{'a', 'p', 's', 'm'}

>>> {1, 2, 3, 4}                 # Set literals: new in 3.0
{1, 2, 3, 4}
>>> S = {'s', 'p', 'a', 'm'}
>>> S.add('alot')
>>> S
{'a', 'p', 's', 'm', 'alot'}

All the set processing operations discussed in the prior section work the same in 3.0, but the result sets print differently:

>>> S1 = {1, 2, 3, 4}
>>> S1 & {1, 3}                  # Intersection
{1, 3}
>>> {1, 5, 3, 6} | S1            # Union
{1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6}
>>> S1 - {1, 3, 4}               # Difference
{2}
>>> S1 > {1, 3}                  # Superset
True

Note that {} is still a dictionary in Python. Empty sets must be created with the set built-in, and print the same way:

>>> S1 - {1, 2, 3, 4}            # Empty sets print differently
set()
>>> type({})                     # Because {} is an empty dictionary
<class 'dict'>

>>> S = set()                    # Initialize an empty set
>>> S.add(1.23)
>>> S
{1.23}

As in Python 2.6, sets created with 3.0 literals support the same methods, some of which allow general iterable operands that expressions do not:

>>> {1, 2, 3} | {3, 4}
{1, 2, 3, 4}
>>> {1, 2, 3} | [3, 4]
TypeError: unsupported operand type(s) for |: 'set' and 'list'

>>> {1, 2, 3}.union([3, 4])
{1, 2, 3, 4}
>>> {1, 2, 3}.union({3, 4})
{1, 2, 3, 4}
>>> {1, 2, 3}.union(set([3, 4]))
{1, 2, 3, 4}

>>> {1, 2, 3}.intersection((1, 3, 5))
{1, 3}
>>> {1, 2, 3}.issubset(range(-5, 5))
True

Immutable constraints and frozen sets

Sets are powerful and flexible objects, but they do have one constraint in both 3.0 and 2.6 that you should keep in mind—largely because of their implementation, sets can only contain immutable (a.k.a “hashable”) object types. Hence, lists and dictionaries cannot be embedded in sets, but tuples can if you need to store compound values. Tuples compare by their full values when used in set operations:

>>> S
{1.23}
>>> S.add([1, 2, 3])                   # Only immutable objects work in a set
TypeError: unhashable type: 'list'
>>> S.add({'a':1})
TypeError: unhashable type: 'dict'
>>> S.add((1, 2, 3))
>>> S                                  # No list or dict, but tuple okay
{1.23, (1, 2, 3)}

>>> S | {(4, 5, 6), (1, 2, 3)}         # Union: same as S.union(...)
{1.23, (4, 5, 6), (1, 2, 3)}
>>> (1, 2, 3) in S                     # Membership: by complete values
True
>>> (1, 4, 3) in S
False

Tuples in a set, for instance, might be used to represent dates, records, IP addresses, and so on (more on tuples later in this part of the book). Sets themselves are mutable too, and so cannot be nested in other sets directly; if you need to store a set inside another set, the frozenset built-in call works just like set but creates an immutable set that cannot change and thus can be embedded in other sets.

Set comprehensions in Python 3.0

In addition to literals, 3.0 introduces a set comprehension construct; it is similar in form to the list comprehension we previewed in Chapter 4, but is coded in curly braces instead of square brackets and run to make a set instead of a list. Set comprehensions run a loop and collect the result of an expression on each iteration; a loop variable gives access to the current iteration value for use in the collection expression. The result is a new set created by running the code, with all the normal set behavior:

>>> {x ** 2 for x in [1, 2, 3, 4]}         # 3.0 set comprehension
{16, 1, 4, 9}

In this expression, the loop is coded on the right, and the collection expression is coded on the left (x ** 2). As for list comprehensions, we get back pretty much what this expression says: “Give me a new set containing X squared, for every X in a list.” Comprehensions can also iterate across other kinds of objects, such as strings (the first of the following examples illustrates the comprehension-based way to make a set from an existing iterable):

>>> {x for x in 'spam'}                    # Same as: set('spam')
{'a', 'p', 's', 'm'}

>>> {c * 4 for c in 'spam'}                # Set of collected expression results
{'ssss', 'aaaa', 'pppp', 'mmmm'}
>>> {c * 4 for c in 'spamham'}
{'ssss', 'aaaa', 'hhhh', 'pppp', 'mmmm'}

>>> S = {c * 4 for c in 'spam'}
>>> S | {'mmmm', 'xxxx'}
{'ssss', 'aaaa', 'pppp', 'mmmm', 'xxxx'}
>>> S & {'mmmm', 'xxxx'}
{'mmmm'}

Because the rest of the comprehensions story relies upon underlying concepts we’re not yet prepared to address, we’ll postpone further details until later in this book. In Chapter 8, we’ll meet a first cousin in 3.0, the dictionary comprehension, and I’ll have much more to say about all comprehensions (list, set, dictionary, and generator) later, especially in Chapters14 and 20. As we’ll learn later, all comprehensions, including sets, support additional syntax not shown here, including nested loops and if tests, which can be difficult to understand until you’ve had a chance to study larger statements.

Why sets?

Set operations have a variety of common uses, some more practical than mathematical. For example, because items are stored only once in a set, sets can be used to filter duplicates out of other collections. Simply convert the collection to a set, and then convert it back again (because sets are iterable, they work in the list call here):

>>> L = [1, 2, 1, 3, 2, 4, 5]
>>> set(L)
{1, 2, 3, 4, 5}
>>> L = list(set(L))                     # Remove duplicates
>>> L
[1, 2, 3, 4, 5]

Sets can also be used to keep track of where you’ve already been when traversing a graph or other cyclic structure. For example, the transitive module reloader and inheritance tree lister examples we’ll study in Chapters 24 and 30, respectively, must keep track of items visited to avoid loops. Although recording states visited as keys in a dictionary is efficient, sets offer an alternative that’s essentially equivalent (and may be more or less intuitive, depending on who you ask).

Finally, sets are also convenient when dealing with large data sets (database query results, for example)—the intersection of two sets contains objects in common to both categories, and the union contains all items in either set. To illustrate, here’s a somewhat more realistic example of set operations at work, applied to lists of people in a hypothetical company, using 3.0 set literals (use set in 2.6):

>>> engineers = {'bob', 'sue', 'ann', 'vic'}
>>> managers  = {'tom', 'sue'}

>>> 'bob' in engineers                   # Is bob an engineer?
True

>>> engineers & managers                 # Who is both engineer and manager?
{'sue'}

>>> engineers | managers                 # All people in either category
{'vic', 'sue', 'tom', 'bob', 'ann'}

>>> engineers – managers                 # Engineers who are not managers
{'vic', 'bob', 'ann'}

>>> managers – engineers                 # Managers who are not engineers
{'tom'}

>>> engineers > managers                 # Are all managers engineers? (superset)
False

>>> {'bob', 'sue'} < engineers           # Are both engineers? (subset)
True

>>> (managers | engineers) > managers    # All people is a superset of managers
True

>>> managers ^ engineers                 # Who is in one but not both?
{'vic', 'bob', 'ann', 'tom'}

>>> (managers | engineers) - (managers ^ engineers)     # Intersection!
{'sue'}

You can find more details on set operations in the Python library manual and some mathematical and relational database theory texts. Also stay tuned for Chapter 8’s revival of some of the set operations we’ve seen here, in the context of dictionary view objects in Python 3.0.

Booleans

Some argue that the Python Boolean type, bool, is numeric in nature because its two values, True and False, are just customized versions of the integers 1 and 0 that print themselves differently. Although that’s all most programmers need to know, let’s explore this type in a bit more detail.

More formally, Python today has an explicit Boolean data type called bool, with the values True and False available as new preassigned built-in names. Internally, the names True and False are instances of bool, which is in turn just a subclass (in the object-oriented sense) of the built-in integer type int. True and False behave exactly like the integers 1 and 0, except that they have customized printing logic—they print themselves as the words True and False, instead of the digits 1 and 0. bool accomplishes this by redefining str and repr string formats for its two objects.

Because of this customization, the output of Boolean expressions typed at the interactive prompt prints as the words True and False instead of the older and less obvious 1 and 0. In addition, Booleans make truth values more explicit. For instance, an infinite loop can now be coded as while True: instead of the less intuitive while 1:. Similarly, flags can be initialized more clearly with flag = False. We’ll discuss these statements further in Part III.

Again, though, for all other practical purposes, you can treat True and False as though they are predefined variables set to integer 1 and 0. Most programmers used to preassign True and False to 1 and 0 anyway; the bool type simply makes this standard. Its implementation can lead to curious results, though. Because True is just the integer 1 with a custom display format, True + 4 yields 5 in Python:

>>> type(True)
<class 'bool'>
>>> isinstance(True, int)
True
>>> True == 1                # Same value
True
>>> True is 1                # But different object: see the next chapter
False
>>> True or False            # Same as: 1 or 0
True
>>> True + 4                 # (Hmmm)
5

Since you probably won’t come across an expression like the last of these in real Python code, you can safely ignore its deeper metaphysical implications....

We’ll revisit Booleans in Chapter 9 (to define Python’s notion of truth) and again in Chapter 12 (to see how Boolean operators like and and or work).

Numeric Extensions

Finally, although Python core numeric types offer plenty of power for most applications, there is a large library of third-party open source extensions available to address more focused needs. Because numeric programming is a popular domain for Python, you’ll find a wealth of advanced tools.

For example, if you need to do serious number crunching, an optional extension for Python called NumPy (Numeric Python) provides advanced numeric programming tools, such as a matrix data type, vector processing, and sophisticated computation libraries. Hardcore scientific programming groups at places like Los Alamos and NASA use Python with NumPy to implement the sorts of tasks they previously coded in C++, FORTRAN, or Matlab. The combination of Python and NumPy is often compared to a free, more flexible version of Matlab—you get NumPy’s performance, plus the Python language and its libraries.

Because it’s so advanced, we won’t talk further about NumPy in this book. You can find additional support for advanced numeric programming in Python, including graphics and plotting tools, statistics libraries, and the popular SciPy package at Python’s PyPI site, or by searching the Web. Also note that NumPy is currently an optional extension; it doesn’t come with Python and must be installed separately.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

The value will be 14, the result of 2 * 7, because the parentheses force the addition to happen before the multiplication.

The value will be 10, the result of 6 + 4. Python’s operator precedence rules are applied in the absence of parentheses, and multiplication has higher precedence than (i.e., happens before) addition, per Table 5-2.

This expression yields 14, the result of 2 + 12, for the same precedence reasons as in the prior question.

Functions for obtaining the square root, as well as pi, tangents, and more, are available in the imported math module. To find a number’s square root, import math and call math.sqrt(N). To get a number’s square, use either the exponent expression X ** 2 or the built-in function pow(X, 2). Either of these last two can also compute the square root when given a power of 0.5 (e.g., X ** .5).

The result will be a floating-point number: the integers are converted up to floating point, the most complex type in the expression, and floating-point math is used to evaluate it.

The int(N) and math.trunc(N) functions truncate, and the round(N, digits) function rounds. We can also compute the floor with math.floor(N) and round for display with string formatting operations.

The float(I) function converts an integer to a floating point; mixing an integer with a floating point within an expression will result in a conversion as well. In some sense, Python 3.0 / division converts too—it always returns a floating-point result that includes the remainder, even if both operands are integers.

The oct(I) and hex(I) built-in functions return the octal and hexadecimal string forms for an integer. The bin(I) call also returns a number’s binary digits string in Python 2.6 and 3.0. The % string formatting expression and format string method also provide targets for some such conversions.

The int(S, base) function can be used to convert from octal and hexadecimal strings to normal integers (pass in 8, 16, or 2 for the base). The eval(S) function can be used for this purpose too, but it’s more expensive to run and can have security issues. Note that integers are always stored in binary in computer memory; these are just display string format conversions.

[15] If you’re working along, you don’t need to type any of the comment text from the # through to the end of the line; comments are simply ignored by Python and not required parts of the statements we’re running.

Dynamic Typing Is Everywhere

Of course, you don’t really need to draw name/object diagrams with circles and arrows to use Python. When you’re starting out, though, it sometimes helps you understand unusual cases if you can trace their reference structures. If a mutable object changes out from under you when passed around your program, for example, chances are you are witnessing some of this chapter’s subject matter firsthand.

Moreover, even if dynamic typing seems a little abstract at this point, you probably will care about it eventually. Because everything seems to work by assignment and references in Python, a basic understanding of this model is useful in many different contexts. As you’ll see, it works the same in assignment statements, function arguments, for loop variables, module imports, class attributes, and more. The good news is that there is just one assignment model in Python; once you get a handle on dynamic typing, you’ll find that it works the same everywhere in the language.

At the most practical level, dynamic typing means there is less code for you to write. Just as importantly, though, dynamic typing is also the root of Python’s polymorphism, a concept we introduced in Chapter 4 and will revisit again later in this book. Because we do not constrain types in Python code, it is highly flexible. As you’ll see, when used well, dynamic typing and the polymorphism it provides produce code that automatically adapts to new requirements as your systems evolve.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

No: A still prints as "spam". When B is assigned to the string "shrubbery", all that happens is that the variable B is reset to point to the new string object. A and B initially share (i.e., reference/point to) the same single string object "spam", but two names are never linked together in Python. Thus, setting B to a different object has no effect on A. The same would be true if the last statement here was B = B + 'shrubbery', by the way—the concatenation would make a new object for its result, which would then be assigned to B only. We can never overwrite a string (or number, or tuple) in-place, because strings are immutable.

Yes: A now prints as ["shrubbery"]. Technically, we haven’t really changed either A or B; instead, we’ve changed part of the object they both reference (point to) by overwriting that object in-place through the variable B. Because A references the same object as B, the update is reflected in A as well.

No: A still prints as ["spam"]. The in-place assignment through B has no effect this time because the slice expression made a copy of the list object before it was assigned to B. After the second assignment statement, there are two different list objects that have the same value (in Python, we say they are ==, but not is). The third statement changes the value of the list object pointed to by B, but not that pointed to by A.

[16] Readers with a background in C may find Python references similar to C pointers (memory addresses). In fact, references are implemented as pointers, and they often serve the same roles, especially with objects that can be changed in-place (more on this later). However, because references are always automatically dereferenced when used, you can never actually do anything useful with a reference itself; this is a feature that eliminates a vast category of C bugs. You can think of Python references as C “void*” pointers, which are automatically followed whenever used.

Chapter 7. Strings

The next major type on our built-in object tour is the Python string—an ordered collection of characters used to store and represent text-based information. We looked briefly at strings in Chapter 4. Here, we will revisit them in more depth, filling in some of the details we skipped then.

From a functional perspective, strings can be used to represent just about anything that can be encoded as text: symbols and words (e.g., your name), contents of text files loaded into memory, Internet addresses, Python programs, and so on. They can also be used to hold the absolute binary values of bytes, and multibyte Unicode text used in internationalized programs.

You may have used strings in other languages, too. Python’s strings serve the same role as character arrays in languages such as C, but they are a somewhat higher-level tool than arrays. Unlike in C, in Python, strings come with a powerful set of processing tools. Also unlike languages such as C, Python has no distinct type for individual characters; instead, you just use one-character strings.

Strictly speaking, Python strings are categorized as immutable sequences, meaning that the characters they contain have a left-to-right positional order and that they cannot be changed in-place. In fact, strings are the first representative of the larger class of objects called sequences that we will study here. Pay special attention to the sequence operations introduced in this chapter, because they will work the same on other sequence types we’ll explore later, such as lists and tuples.

Table 7-1 previews common string literals and operations we will discuss in this chapter. Empty strings are written as a pair of quotation marks (single or double) with nothing in between, and there are a variety of ways to code strings. For processing, strings support expression operations such as concatenation (combining strings), slicing (extracting sections), indexing (fetching by offset), and so on. Besides expressions, Python also provides a set of string methods that implement common string-specific tasks, as well as modules for more advanced text-processing tasks such as pattern matching. We’ll explore all of these later in the chapter.

Table 7-1. Common string literals and operations

Operation

|

Interpretation

S = ''

|

Empty string

S = "spam's"

|

Double quotes, same as single

S = 's\np\ta\x00m'

|

Escape sequences

S = """..."""

|

Triple-quoted block strings

S = r'\temp\spam'

|

Raw strings

S = b'spam'

|

Byte strings in 3.0 (Chapter 36)

S = u'spam'

|

Unicode strings in 2.6 only (Chapter 36)

S1 + S2

S * 3

|

Concatenate, repeat

S[i]

S[i:j]

len(S)

|

Index, slice, length

"a %s parrot" % kind

|

String formatting expression

"a {0} parrot".format(kind)

|

String formatting method in 2.6 and 3.0

S.find('pa')

S.rstrip()

S.replace('pa', 'xx')

S.split(',')

S.isdigit()

S.lower()

S.endswith('spam')

'spam'.join(strlist)

S.encode('latin-1')

|

String method calls: search,

remove whitespace,

replacement,

split on delimiter,

content test,

case conversion,

end test,

delimiter join,

Unicode encoding, etc.

for x in S: print(x)

'spam' in S

[c * 2 for c in S]

map(ord, S)

|

Iteration, membership

Beyond the core set of string tools in Table 7-1, Python also supports more advanced pattern-based string processing with the standard library’s re (regular expression) module, introduced in Chapter 4, and even higher-level text processing tools such as XML parsers, discussed briefly in Chapter 36. This book’s scope, though, is focused on the fundamentals represented by Table 7-1.

To cover the basics, this chapter begins with an overview of string literal forms and string expressions, then moves on to look at more advanced tools such as string methods and formatting. Python comes with many string tools, and we won’t look at them all here; the complete story is chronicled in the Python library manual. Our goal here is to explore enough commonly used tools to give you a representative sample; methods we won’t see in action here, for example, are largely analogous to those we will.

Note

Content note: Technically speaking, this chapter tells only part of the string story in Python—the part most programmers need to know. It presents the basic str string type, which handles ASCII text and works the same regardless of which version of Python you use. That is, this chapter intentionally limits its scope to the string processing essentials that are used in most Python scripts.

From a more formal perspective, ASCII is a simple form of Unicode text. Python addresses the distinction between text and binary data by including distinct object types:

In Python 3.0 there are three string types: str is used for Unicode text (ASCII or otherwise), bytes is used for binary data (including encoded text), and bytearray is a mutable variant of bytes.

In Python 2.6, unicode strings represent wide Unicode text, and str strings handle both 8-bit text and binary data.

The bytearray type is also available as a back-port in 2.6, but not earlier, and it’s not as closely bound to binary data as it is in 3.0. Because most programmers don’t need to dig into the details of Unicode encodings or binary data formats, though, I’ve moved all such details to the Advanced Topics part of this book, in Chapter 36.

If you do need to deal with more advanced string concepts such as alternative character sets or packed binary data and files, see Chapter 36 after reading the material here. For now, we’ll focus on the basic string type and its operations. As you’ll find, the basics we’ll study here also apply directly to the more advanced string types in Python’s toolset.

String Literals

By and large, strings are fairly easy to use in Python. Perhaps the most complicated thing about them is that there are so many ways to write them in your code:

Single quotes: 'spa"m'

Double quotes: "spa'm"

Triple quotes: '''... spam ...''', """... spam ..."""

Escape sequences: "s\tp\na\0m"

Raw strings: r"C:\new\test.spm"

Byte strings in 3.0 (see Chapter 36): b'sp\x01am'

Unicode strings in 2.6 only (see Chapter 36): u'eggs\u0020spam'

The single- and double-quoted forms are by far the most common; the others serve specialized roles, and we’re postponing discussion of the last two advanced forms until Chapter 36. Let’s take a quick look at all the other options in turn.

Single- and Double-Quoted Strings Are the Same

Around Python strings, single and double quote characters are interchangeable. That is, string literals can be written enclosed in either two single or two double quotes—the two forms work the same and return the same type of object. For example, the following two strings are identical, once coded:

>>> 'shrubbery', "shrubbery"
('shrubbery', 'shrubbery')

The reason for supporting both is that it allows you to embed a quote character of the other variety inside a string without escaping it with a backslash. You may embed a single quote character in a string enclosed in double quote characters, and vice versa:

>>> 'knight"s', "knight's"
('knight"s', "knight's")

Incidentally, Python automatically concatenates adjacent string literals in any expression, although it is almost as simple to add a + operator between them to invoke concatenation explicitly (as we’ll see in Chapter 12, wrapping this form in parentheses also allows it to span multiple lines):

>>> title = "Meaning " 'of' " Life"        # Implicit concatenation
>>> title
'Meaning of Life'

Notice that adding commas between these strings would result in a tuple, not a string. Also notice in all of these outputs that Python prefers to print strings in single quotes, unless they embed one. You can also embed quotes by escaping them with backslashes:

>>> 'knight\'s', "knight\"s"
("knight's", 'knight"s')

To understand why, you need to know how escapes work in general.

Escape Sequences Represent Special Bytes

The last example embedded a quote inside a string by preceding it with a backslash. This is representative of a general pattern in strings: backslashes are used to introduce special byte codings known as escape sequences.

Escape sequences let us embed byte codes in strings that cannot easily be typed on a keyboard. The character \, and one or more characters following it in the string literal, are replaced with a single character in the resulting string object, which has the binary value specified by the escape sequence. For example, here is a five-character string that embeds a newline and a tab:

>>> s = 'a\nb\tc'

The two characters \n stand for a single character—the byte containing the binary value of the newline character in your character set (usually, ASCII code 10). Similarly, the sequence \t is replaced with the tab character. The way this string looks when printed depends on how you print it. The interactive echo shows the special characters as escapes, but print interprets them instead:

>>> s
'a\nb\tc'
>>> print(s)
a
b       c

To be completely sure how many bytes are in this string, use the built-in len function—it returns the actual number of bytes in a string, regardless of how it is displayed:

>>> len(s)
5

This string is five bytes long: it contains an ASCII a byte, a newline byte, an ASCII b byte, and so on. Note that the original backslash characters are not really stored with the string in memory; they are used to tell Python to store special byte values in the string. For coding such special bytes, Python recognizes a full set of escape code sequences, listed in Table 7-2.

Table 7-2. String backslash characters

Escape

|

Meaning

\newline

|

Ignored (continuation line)

\\

|

Backslash (stores one \)

\'

|

Single quote (stores ')

\"

|

Double quote (stores ")

\a

|

Bell

\b

|

Backspace

\f

|

Formfeed

\n

|

Newline (linefeed)

\r

|

Carriage return

\t

|

Horizontal tab

\v

|

Vertical tab

\xhh

|

Character with hex value hh (at most 2 digits)

\ooo

|

Character with octal value ooo (up to 3 digits)

\0

|

Null: binary 0 character (doesn’t end string)

\N{ id }

|

Unicode database ID

\uhhhh

|

Unicode 16-bit hex

\Uhhhhhhhh

|

Unicode 32-bit hex[a]

\other

|

Not an escape (keeps both \ and other)

[a] The \Uhhhh... escape sequence takes exactly eight hexadecimal digits (h); both \u and \U can be used only in Unicode string literals.

Some escape sequences allow you to embed absolute binary values into the bytes of a string. For instance, here’s a five-character string that embeds two binary zero bytes (coded as octal escapes of one digit):

>>> s = 'a\0b\0c'
>>> s
'a\x00b\x00c'
>>> len(s)
5

In Python, the zero (null) byte does not terminate a string the way it typically does in C. Instead, Python keeps both the string’s length and text in memory. In fact, no character terminates a string in Python. Here’s a string that is all absolute binary escape codes—a binary 1 and 2 (coded in octal), followed by a binary 3 (coded in hexadecimal):

>>> s = '\001\002\x03'
>>> s
'\x01\x02\x03'
>>> len(s)
3

Notice that Python displays nonprintable characters in hex, regardless of how they were specified. You can freely combine absolute value escapes and the more symbolic escape types in Table 7-2. The following string contains the characters “spam”, a tab and newline, and an absolute zero value byte coded in hex:

>>> S = "s\tp\na\x00m"
>>> S
's\tp\na\x00m'
>>> len(S)
7
>>> print(S)
s       p
a m

This becomes more important to know when you process binary data files in Python. Because their contents are represented as strings in your scripts, it’s OK to process binary files that contain any sorts of binary byte values (more on files in Chapter 9).[17]

Finally, as the last entry in Table 7-2 implies, if Python does not recognize the character after a \ as being a valid escape code, it simply keeps the backslash in the resulting string:

>>> x = "C:\py\code"           # Keeps \ literally
>>> x
'C:\\py\\code'
>>> len(x)
10

Unless you’re able to commit all of Table 7-2 to memory, though, you probably shouldn’t rely on this behavior.[18] To code literal backslashes explicitly such that they are retained in your strings, double them up (\\ is an escape for one \) or use raw strings; the next section shows how.

Raw Strings Suppress Escapes

As we’ve seen, escape sequences are handy for embedding special byte codes within strings. Sometimes, though, the special treatment of backslashes for introducing escapes can lead to trouble. It’s surprisingly common, for instance, to see Python newcomers in classes trying to open a file with a filename argument that looks something like this:

myfile = open('C:\new\text.dat', 'w')

thinking that they will open a file called text.dat in the directory C:\new. The problem here is that \n is taken to stand for a newline character, and \t is replaced with a tab. In effect, the call tries to open a file named C:(newline)ew(tab)ext.dat, with usually less than stellar results.

This is just the sort of thing that raw strings are useful for. If the letter r (uppercase or lowercase) appears just before the opening quote of a string, it turns off the escape mechanism. The result is that Python retains your backslashes literally, exactly as you type them. Therefore, to fix the filename problem, just remember to add the letter r on Windows:

myfile = open(r'C:\new\text.dat', 'w')

Alternatively, because two backslashes are really an escape sequence for one backslash, you can keep your backslashes by simply doubling them up:

myfile = open('C:\\new\\text.dat', 'w')

In fact, Python itself sometimes uses this doubling scheme when it prints strings with embedded backslashes:

>>> path = r'C:\new\text.dat'
>>> path                          # Show as Python code
'C:\\new\\text.dat'
>>> print(path)                   # User-friendly format
C:\new\text.dat
>>> len(path)                     # String length
15

As with numeric representation, the default format at the interactive prompt prints results as if they were code, and therefore escapes backslashes in the output. The print statement provides a more user-friendly format that shows that there is actually only one backslash in each spot. To verify this is the case, you can check the result of the built-in len function, which returns the number of bytes in the string, independent of display formats. If you count the characters in the print(path) output, you’ll see that there really is just 1 character per backslash, for a total of 15.

Besides directory paths on Windows, raw strings are also commonly used for regular expressions (text pattern matching, supported with the re module introduced in Chapter 4). Also note that Python scripts can usually use forward slashes in directory paths on Windows and Unix because Python tries to interpret paths portably (i.e., 'C:/new/text.dat' works when opening files, too). Raw strings are useful if you code paths using native Windows backslashes, though.

Note

Despite its role, even a raw string cannot end in a single backslash, because the backslash escapes the following quote character—you still must escape the surrounding quote character to embed it in the string. That is, r"...\" is not a valid string literal—a raw string cannot end in an odd number of backslashes. If you need to end a raw string with a single backslash, you can use two and slice off the second (r'1\nb\tc\\'[:-1]), tack one on manually (r'1\nb\tc' + '\\'), or skip the raw string syntax and just double up the backslashes in a normal string ('1\\nb\\tc\\'). All three of these forms create the same eight-character string containing three backslashes.

Triple Quotes Code Multiline Block Strings

So far, you’ve seen single quotes, double quotes, escapes, and raw strings in action. Python also has a triple-quoted string literal format, sometimes called a block string, that is a syntactic convenience for coding multiline text data. This form begins with three quotes (of either the single or double variety), is followed by any number of lines of text, and is closed with the same triple-quote sequence that opened it. Single and double quotes embedded in the string’s text may be, but do not have to be, escaped—the string does not end until Python sees three unescaped quotes of the same kind used to start the literal. For example:

>>> mantra = """Always look
...  on the bright
... side of life."""
>>>
>>> mantra
'Always look\n on the bright\nside of life.'

This string spans three lines (in some interfaces, the interactive prompt changes to ... on continuation lines; IDLE simply drops down one line). Python collects all the triple-quoted text into a single multiline string, with embedded newline characters (\n) at the places where your code has line breaks. Notice that, as in the literal, the second line in the result has a leading space, but the third does not—what you type is truly what you get. To see the string with the newlines interpreted, print it instead of echoing:

>>> print(mantra)
Always look
 on the bright
side of life.

Triple-quoted strings are useful any time you need multiline text in your program; for example, to embed multiline error messages or HTML or XML code in your source code files. You can embed such blocks directly in your scripts without resorting to external text files or explicit concatenation and newline characters.

Triple-quoted strings are also commonly used for documentation strings, which are string literals that are taken as comments when they appear at specific points in your file (more on these later in the book). These don’t have to be triple-quoted blocks, but they usually are to allow for multiline comments.

Finally, triple-quoted strings are also sometimes used as a “horribly hackish” way to temporarily disable lines of code during development (OK, it’s not really too horrible, and it’s actually a fairly common practice). If you wish to turn off a few lines of code and run your script again, simply put three quotes above and below them, like this:

X = 1
"""
import os                            # Disable this code temporarily
print(os.getcwd())
"""
Y = 2

I said this was hackish because Python really does make a string out of the lines of code disabled this way, but this is probably not significant in terms of performance. For large sections of code, it’s also easier than manually adding hash marks before each line and later removing them. This is especially true if you are using a text editor that does not have support for editing Python code specifically. In Python, practicality often beats aesthetics.

String Methods

In addition to expression operators, strings provide a set of methods that implement more sophisticated text-processing tasks. Methods are simply functions that are associated with particular objects. Technically, they are attributes attached to objects that happen to reference callable functions. In Python, expressions and built-in functions may work across a range of types, but methods are generally specific to object types—string methods, for example, work only on string objects. The method sets of some types intersect in Python 3.0 (e.g., many types have a count method), but they are still more type-specific than other tools.

In finer-grained detail, functions are packages of code, and method calls combine two operations at once (an attribute fetch and a call):

Attribute fetches

An expression of the form object.attribute means “fetch the value of attribute in object.”

Call expressions

An expression of the form function(arguments) means “invoke the code of function, passing zero or more comma-separated argument objects to it, and return function’s result value.”

Putting these two together allows us to call a method of an object. The method call expression object.method(arguments) is evaluated from left to right—Python will first fetch the method of the object and then call it, passing in the arguments. If the method computes a result, it will come back as the result of the entire method-call expression.

As you’ll see throughout this part of the book, most objects have callable methods, and all are accessed using this same method-call syntax. To call an object method, as you’ll see in the following sections, you have to go through an existing object.

Table 7-3 summarizes the methods and call patterns for built-in string objects in Python 3.0; these change frequently, so be sure to check Python’s standard library manual for the most up-to-date list, or run a help call on any string interactively. Python 2.6’s string methods vary slightly; it includes a decode, for example, because of its different handling of Unicode data (something we’ll discuss in Chapter 36). In this table, S is a string object, and optional arguments are enclosed in square brackets. String methods in this table implement higher-level operations such as splitting and joining, case conversions, content tests, and substring searches and replacements.

Table 7-3. String method calls in Python 3.0

S.capitalize()

|

S.ljust(width [, fill])

S.center(width [, fill])

|

S.lower()

S.count(sub [, start [, end]])

|

S.lstrip([chars])

S.encode([encoding [,errors]])

|

S.maketrans(x[, y[, z]])

S.endswith(suffix [, start [, end]])

|

S.partition(sep)

S.expandtabs([tabsize])

|

S.replace(old, new [, count])

S.find(sub [, start [, end]])

|

S.rfind(sub [,start [,end]])

S.format(fmtstr, *args, **kwargs)

|

S.rindex(sub [, start [, end]])

S.index(sub [, start [, end]])

|

S.rjust(width [, fill])

S.isalnum()

|

S.rpartition(sep)

S.isalpha()

|

S.rsplit([sep[, maxsplit]])

S.isdecimal()

|

S.rstrip([chars])

S.isdigit()

|

S.split([sep [,maxsplit]])

S.isidentifier()

|

S.splitlines([keepends])

S.islower()

|

S.startswith(prefix [, start [, end]])

S.isnumeric()

|

S.strip([chars])

S.isprintable()

|

S.swapcase()

S.isspace()

|

S.title()

S.istitle()

|

S.translate(map)

S.isupper()

|

S.upper()

S.join(iterable)

|

S.zfill(width)

As you can see, there are quite a few string methods, and we don’t have space to cover them all; see Python’s library manual or reference texts for all the fine points. To help you get started, though, let’s work through some code that demonstrates some of the most commonly used methods in action, and illustrates Python text-processing basics along the way.

String Method Examples: Changing Strings

As we’ve seen, because strings are immutable, they cannot be changed in-place directly. To make a new text value from an existing string, you construct a new string with operations such as slicing and concatenation. For example, to replace two characters in the middle of a string, you can use code like this:

>>> S = 'spammy'
>>> S = S[:3] + 'xx' + S[5:]
>>> S
'spaxxy'

But, if you’re really just out to replace a substring, you can use the string replace method instead:

>>> S = 'spammy'
>>> S = S.replace('mm', 'xx')
>>> S
'spaxxy'

The replace method is more general than this code implies. It takes as arguments the original substring (of any length) and the string (of any length) to replace it with, and performs a global search and replace:

>>> 'aa$bb$cc$dd'.replace('$', 'SPAM')
'aaSPAMbbSPAMccSPAMdd'

In such a role, replace can be used as a tool to implement template replacements (e.g., in form letters). Notice that this time we simply printed the result, instead of assigning it to a name—you need to assign results to names only if you want to retain them for later use.

If you need to replace one fixed-size string that can occur at any offset, you can do a replacement again, or search for the substring with the string find method and then slice:

>>> S = 'xxxxSPAMxxxxSPAMxxxx'
>>> where = S.find('SPAM')            # Search for position
>>> where                             # Occurs at offset 4
4
>>> S = S[:where] + 'EGGS' + S[(where+4):]
>>> S
'xxxxEGGSxxxxSPAMxxxx'

The find method returns the offset where the substring appears (by default, searching from the front), or −1 if it is not found. As we saw earlier, it’s a substring search operation just like the in expression, but find returns the position of a located substring.

Another option is to use replace with a third argument to limit it to a single substitution:

>>> S = 'xxxxSPAMxxxxSPAMxxxx'
>>> S.replace('SPAM', 'EGGS')         # Replace all
'xxxxEGGSxxxxEGGSxxxx'

>>> S.replace('SPAM', 'EGGS', 1)      # Replace one
'xxxxEGGSxxxxSPAMxxxx'

Notice that replace returns a new string object each time. Because strings are immutable, methods never really change the subject strings in-place, even if they are called “replace”!

The fact that concatenation operations and the replace method generate new string objects each time they are run is actually a potential downside of using them to change strings. If you have to apply many changes to a very large string, you might be able to improve your script’s performance by converting the string to an object that does support in-place changes:

>>> S = 'spammy'
>>> L = list(S)
>>> L
['s', 'p', 'a', 'm', 'm', 'y']

The built-in list function (or an object construction call) builds a new list out of the items in any sequence—in this case, “exploding” the characters of a string into a list. Once the string is in this form, you can make multiple changes to it without generating a new copy for each change:

>>> L[3] = 'x'                        # Works for lists, not strings
>>> L[4] = 'x'
>>> L
['s', 'p', 'a', 'x', 'x', 'y']

If, after your changes, you need to convert back to a string (e.g., to write to a file), use the string join method to “implode” the list back into a string:

>>> S = ''.join(L)
>>> S
'spaxxy'

The join method may look a bit backward at first sight. Because it is a method of strings (not of lists), it is called through the desired delimiter. join puts the strings in a list (or other iterable) together, with the delimiter between list items; in this case, it uses an empty string delimiter to convert from a list back to a string. More generally, any string delimiter and iterable of strings will do:

>>> 'SPAM'.join(['eggs', 'sausage', 'ham', 'toast'])
'eggsSPAMsausageSPAMhamSPAMtoast'

In fact, joining substrings all at once this way often runs much faster than concatenating them individually. Be sure to also see the earlier note about the mutable bytearray string in Python 3.0 and 2.6, described fully in Chapter 36; because it may be changed in place, it offers an alternative to this list/join combination for some kinds of text that must be changed often.

String Method Examples: Parsing Text

Another common role for string methods is as a simple form of text parsing—that is, analyzing structure and extracting substrings. To extract substrings at fixed offsets, we can employ slicing techniques:

>>> line = 'aaa bbb ccc'
>>> col1 = line[0:3]
>>> col3 = line[8:]
>>> col1
'aaa'
>>> col3
'ccc'

Here, the columns of data appear at fixed offsets and so may be sliced out of the original string. This technique passes for parsing, as long as the components of your data have fixed positions. If instead some sort of delimiter separates the data, you can pull out its components by splitting. This will work even if the data may show up at arbitrary positions within the string:

>>> line = 'aaa bbb  ccc'
>>> cols = line.split()
>>> cols
['aaa', 'bbb', 'ccc']

The string split method chops up a string into a list of substrings, around a delimiter string. We didn’t pass a delimiter in the prior example, so it defaults to whitespace—the string is split at groups of one or more spaces, tabs, and newlines, and we get back a list of the resulting substrings. In other applications, more tangible delimiters may separate the data. This example splits (and hence parses) the string at commas, a separator common in data returned by some database tools:

>>> line = 'bob,hacker,40'
>>> line.split(',')
['bob', 'hacker', '40']

Delimiters can be longer than a single character, too:

>>> line = "i'mSPAMaSPAMlumberjack"
>>> line.split("SPAM")
["i'm", 'a', 'lumberjack']

Although there are limits to the parsing potential of slicing and splitting, both run very fast and can handle basic text-extraction chores.

Other Common String Methods in Action

Other string methods have more focused roles—for example, to strip off whitespace at the end of a line of text, perform case conversions, test content, and test for a substring at the end or front:

>>> line = "The knights who say Ni!\n"
>>> line.rstrip()
'The knights who say Ni!'
>>> line.upper()
'THE KNIGHTS WHO SAY NI!\n'
>>> line.isalpha()
False
>>> line.endswith('Ni!\n')
True
>>> line.startswith('The')
True

Alternative techniques can also sometimes be used to achieve the same results as string methods—the in membership operator can be used to test for the presence of a substring, for instance, and length and slicing operations can be used to mimic endswith:

>>> line
'The knights who say Ni!\n'

>>> line.find('Ni') != −1       # Search via method call or expression
True
>>> 'Ni' in line
True

>>> sub = 'Ni!\n'
>>> line.endswith(sub)          # End test via method call or slice
True
>>> line[-len(sub):] == sub
True

See also the format string formatting method described later in this chapter; it provides more advanced substitution tools that combine many operations in a single step.

Again, because there are so many methods available for strings, we won’t look at every one here. You’ll see some additional string examples later in this book, but for more details you can also turn to the Python library manual and other documentation sources, or simply experiment interactively on your own. You can also check the help(S.method) results for a method of any string object S for more hints.

Note that none of the string methods accepts patterns—for pattern-based text processing, you must use the Python re standard library module, an advanced tool that was introduced in Chapter 4 but is mostly outside the scope of this text (one further example appears at the end of Chapter 36). Because of this limitation, though, string methods may sometimes run more quickly than the re module’s tools.

The Original string Module (Gone in 3.0)

The history of Python’s string methods is somewhat convoluted. For roughly the first decade of its existence, Python provided a standard library module called string that contained functions that largely mirrored the current set of string object methods. In response to user requests, in Python 2.0 these functions were made available as methods of string objects. Because so many people had written so much code that relied on the original string module, however, it was retained for backward compatibility.

Today, you should use only string methods, not the original string module. In fact, the original module-call forms of today’s string methods have been removed completely from Python in Release 3.0. However, because you may still see the module in use in older Python code, a brief look is in order here.

The upshot of this legacy is that in Python 2.6, there technically are still two ways to invoke advanced string operations: by calling object methods, or by calling string module functions and passing in the objects as arguments. For instance, given a variable X assigned to a string object, calling an object method:

X.method(arguments)

is usually equivalent to calling the same operation through the string module (provided that you have already imported the module):

string.method(X, arguments)

Here’s an example of the method scheme in action:

>>> S = 'a+b+c+'
>>> x = S.replace('+', 'spam')
>>> x
'aspambspamcspam'

To access the same operation through the string module in Python 2.6, you need to import the module (at least once in your process) and pass in the object:

>>> import string
>>> y = string.replace(S, '+', 'spam')
>>> y
'aspambspamcspam'

Because the module approach was the standard for so long, and because strings are such a central component of most programs, you might see both call patterns in Python 2.X code you come across.

Again, though, today you should always use method calls instead of the older module calls. There are good reasons for this, besides the fact that the module calls have gone away in Release 3.0. For one thing, the module call scheme requires you to import the string module (methods do not require imports). For another, the module makes calls a few characters longer to type (when you load the module with import, that is, not using from). And, finally, the module runs more slowly than methods (the module maps most calls back to the methods and so incurs an extra call along the way).

The original string module itself, without its string method equivalents, is retained in Python 3.0 because it contains additional tools, including predefined string constants and a template object system (a relatively obscure tool omitted here—see the Python library manual for details on template objects). Unless you really want to have to change your 2.6 code to use 3.0, though, you should consider the basic string operation calls in it to be just ghosts from the past.

String Formatting Expressions

Although you can get a lot done with the string methods and sequence operations we’ve already met, Python also provides a more advanced way to combine string processing tasks—string formatting allows us to perform multiple type-specific substitutions on a string in a single step. It’s never strictly required, but it can be convenient, especially when formatting text to be displayed to a program’s users. Due to the wealth of new ideas in the Python world, string formatting is available in two flavors in Python today:

String formatting expressions

The original technique, available since Python’s inception; this is based upon the C language’s “printf” model and is used in much existing code.

String formatting method calls

A newer technique added in Python 2.6 and 3.0; this is more unique to Python and largely overlaps with string formatting expression functionality.

Since the method call flavor is new, there is some chance that one or the other of these may become deprecated over time. The expressions are more likely to be deprecated in later Python releases, though this should depend on the future practice of real Python programmers. As they are largely just variations on a theme, though, either technique is valid to use today. Since string formatting expressions are the original in this department, let’s start with them.

Python defines the % binary operator to work on strings (you may recall that this is also the remainder of division, or modulus, operator for numbers). When applied to strings, the % operator provides a simple way to format values as strings according to a format definition. In short, the % operator provides a compact way to code multiple string substitutions all at once, instead of building and concatenating parts individually.

To format strings:

On the left of the % operator, provide a format string containing one or more embedded conversion targets, each of which starts with a % (e.g., %d).

On the right of the % operator, provide the object (or objects, embedded in a tuple) that you want Python to insert into the format string on the left in place of the conversion target (or targets).

For instance, in the formatting example we saw earlier in this chapter, the integer 1 replaces the %d in the format string on the left, and the string 'dead' replaces the %s. The result is a new string that reflects these two substitutions:

>>> 'That is %d %s bird!' % (1, 'dead')           # Format expression
That is 1 dead bird!

Technically speaking, string formatting expressions are usually optional—you can generally do similar work with multiple concatenations and conversions. However, formatting allows us to combine many steps into a single operation. It’s powerful enough to warrant a few more examples:

>>> exclamation = "Ni"
>>> "The knights who say %s!" % exclamation
'The knights who say Ni!'

>>> "%d %s %d you" % (1, 'spam', 4)
'1 spam 4 you'

>>> "%s -- %s -- %s" % (42, 3.14159, [1, 2, 3])
'42 -- 3.14159 -- [1, 2, 3]'

The first example here plugs the string "Ni" into the target on the left, replacing the %s marker. In the second example, three values are inserted into the target string. Note that when you’re inserting more than one value, you need to group the values on the right in parentheses (i.e., put them in a tuple). The % formatting expression operator expects either a single item or a tuple of one or more items on its right side.

The third example again inserts three values—an integer, a floating-point object, and a list object—but notice that all of the targets on the left are %s, which stands for conversion to string. As every type of object can be converted to a string (the one used when printing), every object type works with the %s conversion code. Because of this, unless you will be doing some special formatting, %s is often the only code you need to remember for the formatting expression.

Again, keep in mind that formatting always makes a new string, rather than changing the string on the left; because strings are immutable, it must work this way. As before, assign the result to a variable name if you need to retain it.

Advanced String Formatting Expressions

For more advanced type-specific formatting, you can use any of the conversion type codes listed in Table 7-4 in formatting expressions; they appear after the % character in substitution targets. C programmers will recognize most of these because Python string formatting supports all the usual C printf format codes (but returns the result, instead of displaying it, like printf). Some of the format codes in the table provide alternative ways to format the same type; for instance, %e, %f, and %g provide alternative ways to format floating-point numbers.

Table 7-4. String formatting type codes

Code

|

Meaning

s

|

String (or any object’s str(X) string)

r

|

s, but uses repr, not str

c

|

Character

d

|

Decimal (integer)

i

|

Integer

u

|

Same as d (obsolete: no longer unsigned)

o

|

Octal integer

x

|

Hex integer

X

|

x, but prints uppercase

e

|

Floating-point exponent, lowercase

E

|

Same as e, but prints uppercase

f

|

Floating-point decimal

F

|

Floating-point decimal

g

|

Floating-point e or f

G

|

Floating-point E or F

%

|

Literal %

In fact, conversion targets in the format string on the expression’s left side support a variety of conversion operations with a fairly sophisticated syntax all their own. The general structure of conversion targets looks like this:

%[(name)][flags][width][.precision]typecode

The character type codes in Table 7-4 show up at the end of the target string. Between the % and the character code, you can do any of the following: provide a dictionary key; list flags that specify things like left justification (−), numeric sign (+), and zero fills (0); give a total minimum field width and the number of digits after a decimal point; and more. Both width and precision can also be coded as a * to specify that they should take their values from the next item in the input values.

Formatting target syntax is documented in full in the Python standard manuals, but to demonstrate common usage, let’s look at a few examples. This one formats integers by default, and then in a six-character field with left justification and zero padding:

>>> x = 1234
>>> res = "integers: ...%d...%−6d...%06d" % (x, x, x)
>>> res
'integers: ...1234...1234  ...001234'

The %e, %f, and %g formats display floating-point numbers in different ways, as the following interaction demonstrates (%E is the same as %e but the exponent is uppercase):

>>> x = 1.23456789
>>> x
1.2345678899999999

>>> '%e | %f | %g' % (x, x, x)
'1.234568e+00 | 1.234568 | 1.23457'

>>> '%E' % x
'1.234568E+00'

For floating-point numbers, you can achieve a variety of additional formatting effects by specifying left justification, zero padding, numeric signs, field width, and digits after the decimal point. For simpler tasks, you might get by with simply converting to strings with a format expression or the str built-in function shown earlier:

>>> '%−6.2f | %05.2f | %+06.1f' % (x, x, x)
'1.23   | 01.23 | +001.2'

>>> "%s" % x, str(x)
('1.23456789', '1.23456789')

When sizes are not known until runtime, you can have the width and precision computed by specifying them with a * in the format string to force their values to be taken from the next item in the inputs to the right of the % operator—the 4 in the tuple here gives precision:

>>> '%f, %.2f, %.*f' % (1/3.0, 1/3.0, 4, 1/3.0)
'0.333333, 0.33, 0.3333'

If you’re interested in this feature, experiment with some of these examples and operations on your own for more information.

Dictionary-Based String Formatting Expressions

String formatting also allows conversion targets on the left to refer to the keys in a dictionary on the right and fetch the corresponding values. I haven’t told you much about dictionaries yet, so here’s an example that demonstrates the basics:

>>> "%(n)d %(x)s" % {"n":1, "x":"spam"}
'1 spam'

Here, the (n) and (x) in the format string refer to keys in the dictionary literal on the right and fetch their associated values. Programs that generate text such as HTML or XML often use this technique—you can build up a dictionary of values and substitute them all at once with a single formatting expression that uses key-based references:

>>> reply = """                               # Template with substitution targets
Greetings...
Hello %(name)s!
Your age squared is %(age)s
"""
>>> values = {'name': 'Bob', 'age': 40}       # Build up values to substitute
>>> print(reply % values)                     # Perform substitutions

Greetings...
Hello Bob!
Your age squared is 40

This trick is also used in conjunction with the vars built-in function, which returns a dictionary containing all the variables that exist in the place it is called:

>>> food = 'spam'
>>> age = 40
>>> vars()
{'food': 'spam', 'age': 40, ...many more... }

When used on the right of a format operation, this allows the format string to refer to variables by name (i.e., by dictionary key):

>>> "%(age)d %(food)s" % vars()
'40 spam'

We’ll study dictionaries in more depth in Chapter 8. See also Chapter 5 for examples that convert to hexadecimal and octal number strings with the %x and %o formatting target codes.

General Type Categories

Now that we’ve explored the first of Python’s collection objects, the string, let’s pause to define a few general type concepts that will apply to most of the types we look at from here on. With regard to built-in types, it turns out that operations work the same for all the types in the same category, so we’ll only need to define most of these ideas once. We’ve only examined numbers and strings so far, but because they are representative of two of the three major type categories in Python, you already know more about several other types than you might think.

Types Share Operation Sets by Categories

As you’ve learned, strings are immutable sequences: they cannot be changed in-place (the immutable part), and they are positionally ordered collections that are accessed by offset (the sequence part). Now, it so happens that all the sequences we’ll study in this part of the book respond to the same sequence operations shown in this chapter at work on strings—concatenation, indexing, iteration, and so on. More formally, there are three major type (and operation) categories in Python:

Numbers (integer, floating-point, decimal, fraction, others)

Support addition, multiplication, etc.

Sequences (strings, lists, tuples)

Support indexing, slicing, concatenation, etc.

Mappings (dictionaries)

Support indexing by key, etc.

Sets are something of a category unto themselves (they don’t map keys to values and are not positionally ordered sequences), and we haven’t yet explored mappings on our in-depth tour (dictionaries are discussed in the next chapter). However, many of the other types we will encounter will be similar to numbers and strings. For example, for any sequence objects X and Y:

X + Y makes a new sequence object with the contents of both operands.

X * N makes a new sequence object with N copies of the sequence operand X.

In other words, these operations work the same way on any kind of sequence, including strings, lists, tuples, and some user-defined object types. The only difference is that the new result object you get back is of the same type as the operands X and Y—if you concatenate lists, you get back a new list, not a string. Indexing, slicing, and other sequence operations work the same on all sequences, too; the type of the objects being processed tells Python which flavor of the task to perform.

Mutable Types Can Be Changed In-Place

The immutable classification is an important constraint to be aware of, yet it tends to trip up new users. If an object type is immutable, you cannot change its value in-place; Python raises an error if you try. Instead, you must run code to make a new object containing the new value. The major core types in Python break down as follows:

Immutables (numbers, strings, tuples, frozensets)

None of the object types in the immutable category support in-place changes, though we can always run expressions to make new objects and assign their results to variables as needed.

Mutables (lists, dictionaries, sets, bytearray)

Conversely, the mutable types can always be changed in-place with operations that do not create new objects. Although such objects can be copied, in-place changes support direct modification.

Generally, immutable types give some degree of integrity by guaranteeing that an object won’t be changed by another part of a program. For a refresher on why this matters, see the discussion of shared object references in Chapter 6. To see how lists, dictionaries, and tuples participate in type categories, we need to move ahead to the next chapter.

Chapter Summary

In this chapter, we took an in-depth tour of the string object type. We learned about coding string literals, and we explored string operations, including sequence expressions, string method calls, and string formatting with both expressions and method calls. Along the way, we studied a variety of concepts in depth, such as slicing, method call syntax, and triple-quoted block strings. We also defined some core ideas common to a variety of types: sequences, for example, share an entire set of operations.

In the next chapter, we’ll continue our types tour with a look at the most general object collections in Python—lists and dictionaries. As you’ll find, much of what you’ve learned here will apply to those types as well. And as mentioned earlier, in the final part of this book we’ll return to Python’s string model to flesh out the details of Unicode text and binary data, which are of interest to some, but not all, Python programmers. Before moving on, though, here’s another chapter quiz to review the material covered here.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

No, because methods are always type-specific; that is, they only work on a single data type. Expressions like X+Y and built-in functions like len(X) are generic, though, and may work on a variety of types. In this case, for instance, the in membership expression has a similar effect as the string find, but it can be used to search both strings and lists. In Python 3.0, there is some attempt to group methods by categories (for example, the mutable sequence types list and bytearray have similar method sets), but methods are still more type-specific than other operation sets.

Yes. Unlike methods, expressions are generic and apply to many types. In this case, the slice expression is really a sequence operation—it works on any type of sequence object, including strings, lists, and tuples. The only difference is that when you slice a list, you get back a new list.

The built-in ord(S) function converts from a one-character string to an integer character code; chr(I) converts from the integer code back to a string.

Strings cannot be changed; they are immutable. However, you can achieve a similar effect by creating a new string—by concatenating, slicing, running formatting expressions, or using a method call like replace—and then assigning the result back to the original variable name.

You can slice the string using S[2:4], or split on the comma and index the string using S.split(',')[1]. Try these interactively to see for yourself.

Six. The string "a\nb\x1f\000d" contains the bytes a, newline (\n), b, binary 31 (a hex escape \x1f), binary 0 (an octal escape \000), and d. Pass the string to the built-in len function to verify this, and print each of its character’s ord results to see the actual byte values. See Table 7-2 for more details.

You should never use the string module instead of string object method calls today—it’s deprecated, and its calls are removed completely in Python 3.0. The only reason for using the string module at all is for its other tools, such as predefined constants. You might also see it appear in what is now very old and dusty Python code.

[17] If you need to care about binary data files, the chief distinction is that you open them in binary mode (using open mode flags with a b, such as 'rb', 'wb', and so on). In Python 3.0, binary file content is a bytes string, with an interface similar to that of normal strings; in 2.6, such content is a normal str string. See also the standard struct module introduced in Chapter 9, which can parse binary data loaded from a file, and the extended coverage of binary files and byte strings in Chapter 36.

[18] In classes, I’ve met people who have indeed committed most or all of this table to memory; I’d probably think that was really sick, but for the fact that I’m a member of the set, too.

[19] Unlike with C character arrays, you don’t need to allocate or manage storage arrays when using Python strings; you can simply create string objects as needed and let Python manage the underlying memory space. As discussed in Chapter 6, Python reclaims unused objects’ memory space automatically, using a reference-count garbage-collection strategy. Each object keeps track of the number of names, data structures, etc., that reference it; when the count reaches zero, Python frees the object’s space. This scheme means Python doesn’t have to stop and scan all the memory to find unused space to free (an additional garbage component also collects cyclic objects).

[20] More mathematically minded readers (and students in my classes) sometimes detect a small asymmetry here: the leftmost item is at offset 0, but the rightmost is at offset –1. Alas, there is no such thing as a distinct –0 value in Python.

Lists

The next stop on our built-in object tour is the Python list. Lists are Python’s most flexible ordered collection object type. Unlike strings, lists can contain any sort of object: numbers, strings, and even other lists. Also, unlike strings, lists may be changed in-place by assignment to offsets and slices, list method calls, deletion statements, and more—they are mutable objects.

Python lists do the work of most of the collection data structures you might have to implement manually in lower-level languages such as C. Here is a quick look at their main properties. Python lists are:

Ordered collections of arbitrary objects

From a functional view, lists are just places to collect other objects so you can treat them as groups. Lists also maintain a left-to-right positional ordering among the items they contain (i.e., they are sequences).

Accessed by offset

Just as with strings, you can fetch a component object out of a list by indexing the list on the object’s offset. Because items in lists are ordered by their positions, you can also do tasks such as slicing and concatenation.

Variable-length, heterogeneous, and arbitrarily nestable

Unlike strings, lists can grow and shrink in-place (their lengths can vary), and they can contain any sort of object, not just one-character strings (they’re heterogeneous). Because lists can contain other complex objects, they also support arbitrary nesting; you can create lists of lists of lists, and so on.

Of the category “mutable sequence”

In terms of our type category qualifiers, lists are mutable (i.e., can be changed in-place) and can respond to all the sequence operations used with strings, such as indexing, slicing, and concatenation. In fact, sequence operations work the same on lists as they do on strings; the only difference is that sequence operations such as concatenation and slicing return new lists instead of new strings when applied to lists. Because lists are mutable, however, they also support other operations that strings don’t (such as deletion and index assignment operations, which change the lists in-place).

Arrays of object references

Technically, Python lists contain zero or more references to other objects. Lists might remind you of arrays of pointers (addresses) if you have a background in some other languages. Fetching an item from a Python list is about as fast as indexing a C array; in fact, lists really are arrays inside the standard Python interpreter, not linked structures. As we learned in Chapter 6, though, Python always follows a reference to an object whenever the reference is used, so your program deals only with objects. Whenever you assign an object to a data structure component or variable name, Python always stores a reference to that same object, not a copy of it (unless you request a copy explicitly).

Table 8-1 summarizes common and representative list object operations. As usual, for the full story see the Python standard library manual, or run a help(list) or dir(list) call interactively for a complete list of list methods—you can pass in a real list, or the word list, which is the name of the list data type.

Table 8-1. Common list literals and operations

Operation

|

Interpretation

L = []

|

An empty list

L = [0, 1, 2, 3]

|

Four items: indexes 0..3

L = ['abc', ['def', 'ghi']]

|

Nested sublists

L = list('spam')

L = list(range(-4, 4))

|

Lists of an iterable’s items, list of successive integers

L[i]

L[i][j]

L[i:j]

len(L)

|

Index, index of index, slice, length

L1 + L2

L * 3

|

Concatenate, repeat

for x in L: print(x)

3 in L

|

Iteration, membership

L.append(4)

L.extend([5,6,7])

L.insert(I, X)

|

Methods: growing

L.index(1)

L.count(X)

|

Methods: searching

L.sort()

L.reverse()

|

Methods: sorting, reversing, etc.

del L[k]

del L[i:j]

L.pop()

L.remove(2)

L[i:j] = []

|

Methods, statement: shrinking

L[i] = 1

L[i:j] = [4,5,6]

|

Index assignment, slice assignment

L = [x**2 for x in range(5)]

list(map(ord, 'spam'))

|

List comprehensions and maps (Chapters 14, 20)

When written down as a literal expression, a list is coded as a series of objects (really, expressions that return objects) in square brackets, separated by commas. For instance, the second row in Table 8-1 assigns the variable L to a four-item list. A nested list is coded as a nested square-bracketed series (row 3), and the empty list is just a square-bracket pair with nothing inside (row 1).[21]

Many of the operations in Table 8-1 should look familiar, as they are the same sequence operations we put to work on strings—indexing, concatenation, iteration, and so on. Lists also respond to list-specific method calls (which provide utilities such as sorting, reversing, adding items to the end, etc.), as well as in-place change operations (deleting items, assignment to indexes and slices, and so forth). Lists have these tools for change operations because they are a mutable object type.

Lists in Action

Perhaps the best way to understand lists is to see them at work. Let’s once again turn to some simple interpreter interactions to illustrate the operations in Table 8-1.

Basic List Operations

Because they are sequences, lists support many of the same operations as strings. For example, lists respond to the + and * operators much like strings—they mean concatenation and repetition here too, except that the result is a new list, not a string:

% python
>>> len([1, 2, 3])                           # Length
3
>>> [1, 2, 3] + [4, 5, 6]                    # Concatenation
[1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6]
>>> ['Ni!'] * 4                              # Repetition
['Ni!', 'Ni!', 'Ni!', 'Ni!']

Although the + operator works the same for lists and strings, it’s important to know that it expects the same sort of sequence on both sides—otherwise, you get a type error when the code runs. For instance, you cannot concatenate a list and a string unless you first convert the list to a string (using tools such as str or % formatting) or convert the string to a list (the list built-in function does the trick):

>>> str([1, 2]) + "34"               # Same as "[1, 2]" + "34"
'[1, 2]34'
>>> [1, 2] + list("34")              # Same as [1, 2] + ["3", "4"]
[1, 2, '3', '4']

List Iteration and Comprehensions

More generally, lists respond to all the sequence operations we used on strings in the prior chapter, including iteration tools:

>>> 3 in [1, 2, 3]                           # Membership
True
>>> for x in [1, 2, 3]:
...     print(x, end=' ')                    # Iteration
...
1 2 3

We will talk more formally about for iteration and the range built-ins in Chapter 13, because they are related to statement syntax. In short, for loops step through items in any sequence from left to right, executing one or more statements for each item.

The last items in Table 8-1, list comprehensions and map calls, are covered in more detail in Chapter 14 and expanded on in Chapter 20. Their basic operation is straightforward, though—as introduced in Chapter 4, list comprehensions are a way to build a new list by applying an expression to each item in a sequence, and are close relatives to for loops:

>>> res = [c * 4 for c in 'SPAM']            # List comprehensions
>>> res
['SSSS', 'PPPP', 'AAAA', 'MMMM']

This expression is functionally equivalent to a for loop that builds up a list of results manually, but as we’ll learn in later chapters, list comprehensions are simpler to code and faster to run today:

>>> res = []
>>> for c in 'SPAM':                         # List comprehension equivalent
...     res.append(c * 4)
...
>>> res
['SSSS', 'PPPP', 'AAAA', 'MMMM']

As also introduced in Chapter 4, the map built-in function does similar work, but applies a function to items in a sequence and collects all the results in a new list:

>>> list(map(abs, [−1, −2, 0, 1, 2]))        # map function across sequence
[1, 2, 0, 1, 2]

Because we’re not quite ready for the full iteration story, we’ll postpone further details for now, but watch for a similar comprehension expression for dictionaries later in this chapter.

Indexing, Slicing, and Matrixes

Because lists are sequences, indexing and slicing work the same way for lists as they do for strings. However, the result of indexing a list is whatever type of object lives at the offset you specify, while slicing a list always returns a new list:

>>> L = ['spam', 'Spam', 'SPAM!']
>>> L[2]                             # Offsets start at zero
'SPAM!'
>>> L[−2]                            # Negative: count from the right
'Spam'
>>> L[1:]                            # Slicing fetches sections
['Spam', 'SPAM!']

One note here: because you can nest lists and other object types within lists, you will sometimes need to string together index operations to go deeper into a data structure. For example, one of the simplest ways to represent matrixes (multidimensional arrays) in Python is as lists with nested sublists. Here’s a basic 3 × 3 two-dimensional list-based array:

>>> matrix = [[1, 2, 3], [4, 5, 6], [7, 8, 9]]

With one index, you get an entire row (really, a nested sublist), and with two, you get an item within the row:

>>> matrix[1]
[4, 5, 6]
>>> matrix[1][1]
5
>>> matrix[2][0]
7
>>> matrix = [[1, 2, 3],
...           [4, 5, 6],
...           [7, 8, 9]]
>>> matrix[1][1]
5

Notice in the preceding interaction that lists can naturally span multiple lines if you want them to because they are contained by a pair of brackets (more on syntax in the next part of the book). Later in this chapter, you’ll also see a dictionary-based matrix representation. For high-powered numeric work, the NumPy extension mentioned in Chapter 5 provides other ways to handle matrixes.

Changing Lists In-Place

Because lists are mutable, they support operations that change a list object in-place. That is, the operations in this section all modify the list object directly, without requiring that you make a new copy, as you had to for strings. Because Python deals only in object references, this distinction between changing an object in-place and creating a new object matters—as discussed in Chapter 6, if you change an object in-place, you might impact more than one reference to it at the same time.

Index and slice assignments

When using a list, you can change its contents by assigning to either a particular item (offset) or an entire section (slice):

>>> L = ['spam', 'Spam', 'SPAM!']
>>> L[1] = 'eggs'                 # Index assignment
>>> L
['spam', 'eggs', 'SPAM!']
>>> L[0:2] = ['eat', 'more']      # Slice assignment: delete+insert
>>> L                             # Replaces items 0,1
['eat', 'more', 'SPAM!']

Both index and slice assignments are in-place changes—they modify the subject list directly, rather than generating a new list object for the result. Index assignment in Python works much as it does in C and most other languages: Python replaces the object reference at the designated offset with a new one.

Slice assignment, the last operation in the preceding example, replaces an entire section of a list in a single step. Because it can be a bit complex, it is perhaps best thought of as a combination of two steps:

Deletion. The slice you specify to the left of the = is deleted.

Insertion. The new items contained in the object to the right of the = are inserted into the list on the left, at the place where the old slice was deleted.[22]

This isn’t what really happens, but it tends to help clarify why the number of items inserted doesn’t have to match the number of items deleted. For instance, given a list L that has the value [1,2,3], the assignment L[1:2]=[4,5] sets L to the list [1,4,5,3]. Python first deletes the 2 (a one-item slice), then inserts the 4 and 5 where the deleted 2 used to be. This also explains why L[1:2]=[] is really a deletion operation—Python deletes the slice (the item at offset 1), and then inserts nothing.

In effect, slice assignment replaces an entire section, or “column,” all at once. Because the length of the sequence being assigned does not have to match the length of the slice being assigned to, slice assignment can be used to replace (by overwriting), expand (by inserting), or shrink (by deleting) the subject list. It’s a powerful operation, but frankly, one that you may not see very often in practice. There are usually more straightforward ways to replace, insert, and delete (concatenation and the insert, pop, and remove list methods, for example), which Python programmers tend to prefer in practice.

List method calls

Like strings, Python list objects also support type-specific method calls, many of which change the subject list in-place:

>>> L.append('please')                # Append method call: add item at end
>>> L
['eat', 'more', 'SPAM!', 'please']
>>> L.sort()                          # Sort list items ('S' < 'e')
>>> L
['SPAM!', 'eat', 'more', 'please']

Methods were introduced in Chapter 7. In brief, they are functions (really, attributes that reference functions) that are associated with particular objects. Methods provide type-specific tools; the list methods presented here, for instance, are generally available only for lists.

Perhaps the most commonly used list method is append, which simply tacks a single item (object reference) onto the end of the list. Unlike concatenation, append expects you to pass in a single object, not a list. The effect of L.append(X) is similar to L+[X], but while the former changes L in-place, the latter makes a new list.[23]

Another commonly seen method, sort, orders a list in-place; it uses Python standard comparison tests (here, string comparisons), and by default sorts in ascending order. You can modify sort behavior by passing in keyword arguments—a special “name=value” syntax in function calls that specifies passing by name and is often used for giving configuration options. In sorts, the key argument gives a one-argument function that returns the value to be used in sorting, and the reverse argument allows sorts to be made in descending instead of ascending order:

>>> L = ['abc', 'ABD', 'aBe']
>>> L.sort()                                # Sort with mixed case
>>> L
['ABD', 'aBe', 'abc']
>>> L = ['abc', 'ABD', 'aBe']
>>> L.sort(key=str.lower)                   # Normalize to lowercase
>>> L
['abc', 'ABD', 'aBe']
>>>
>>> L = ['abc', 'ABD', 'aBe']
>>> L.sort(key=str.lower, reverse=True)     # Change sort order
>>> L
['aBe', 'ABD', 'abc']

The sort key argument might also be useful when sorting lists of dictionaries, to pick out a sort key by indexing each dictionary. We’ll study dictionaries later in this chapter, and you’ll learn more about keyword function arguments in Part IV.

Note

Comparison and sorts in 3.0: In Python 2.6 and earlier, comparisons of differently typed objects (e.g., a string and a list) work—the language defines a fixed ordering among different types, which is deterministic, if not aesthetically pleasing. That is, the ordering is based on the names of the types involved: all integers are less than all strings, for example, because "int" is less than "str". Comparisons never automatically convert types, except when comparing numeric type objects.

In Python 3.0, this has changed: comparison of mixed types raises an exception instead of falling back on the fixed cross-type ordering. Because sorting uses comparisons internally, this means that [1, 2, 'spam'].sort() succeeds in Python 2.X but will raise an exception in Python 3.0 and later.

Python 3.0 also no longer supports passing in an arbitrary comparison function to sorts, to implement different orderings. The suggested workaround is to use the key=func keyword argument to code value transformations during the sort, and use the reverse=True keyword argument to change the sort order to descending. These were the typical uses of comparison functions in the past.

One warning here: beware that append and sort change the associated list object in-place, but don’t return the list as a result (technically, they both return a value called None). If you say something like L=L.append(X), you won’t get the modified value of L (in fact, you’ll lose the reference to the list altogether!). When you use attributes such as append and sort, objects are changed as a side effect, so there’s no reason to reassign.

Partly because of such constraints, sorting is also available in recent Pythons as a built-in function, which sorts any collection (not just lists) and returns a new list for the result (instead of in-place changes):

>>> L = ['abc', 'ABD', 'aBe']
>>> sorted(L, key=str.lower, reverse=True)          # Sorting built-in
['aBe', 'ABD', 'abc']

>>> L = ['abc', 'ABD', 'aBe']
>>> sorted([x.lower() for x in L], reverse=True)    # Pretransform items: differs!
['abe', 'abd', 'abc']

Notice the last example here—we can convert to lowercase prior to the sort with a list comprehension, but the result does not contain the original list’s values as it does with the key argument. The latter is applied temporarily during the sort, instead of changing the values to be sorted. As we move along, we’ll see contexts in which the sorted built-in can sometimes be more useful than the sort method.

Like strings, lists have other methods that perform other specialized operations. For instance, reverse reverses the list in-place, and the extend and pop methods insert multiple items at the end of and delete an item from the end of the list, respectively. There is also a reversed built-in function that works much like sorted, but it must be wrapped in a list call because it’s an iterator (more on iterators later):

>>> L = [1, 2]
>>> L.extend([3,4,5])                # Add many items at end
>>> L
[1, 2, 3, 4, 5]
>>> L.pop()                          # Delete and return last item
5
>>> L
[1, 2, 3, 4]
>>> L.reverse()                      # In-place reversal method
>>> L
[4, 3, 2, 1]
>>> list(reversed(L))                # Reversal built-in with a result
[1, 2, 3, 4]

In some types of programs, the list pop method used here is often used in conjunction with append to implement a quick last-in-first-out (LIFO) stack structure. The end of the list serves as the top of the stack:

>>> L = []
>>> L.append(1)                      # Push onto stack
>>> L.append(2)
>>> L
[1, 2]
>>> L.pop()                          # Pop off stack
2
>>> L
[1]

The pop method also accepts an optional offset of the item to be deleted and returned (the default is the last item). Other list methods remove an item by value (remove), insert an item at an offset (insert), search for an item’s offset (index), and more:

>>> L = ['spam', 'eggs', 'ham']
>>> L.index('eggs')                  # Index of an object
1
>>> L.insert(1, 'toast')             # Insert at position
>>> L
['spam', 'toast', 'eggs', 'ham']
>>> L.remove('eggs')                 # Delete by value
>>> L
['spam', 'toast', 'ham']
>>> L.pop(1)                         # Delete by position
'toast'
>>> L
['spam', 'ham']

See other documentation sources or experiment with these calls interactively on your own to learn more about list methods.

Other common list operations

Because lists are mutable, you can use the del statement to delete an item or section in-place:

>>> L
['SPAM!', 'eat', 'more', 'please']
>>> del L[0]                         # Delete one item
>>> L
['eat', 'more', 'please']
>>> del L[1:]                        # Delete an entire section
>>> L                                # Same as L[1:] = []
['eat']

Because slice assignment is a deletion plus an insertion, you can also delete a section of a list by assigning an empty list to a slice (L[i:j]=[]); Python deletes the slice named on the left, and then inserts nothing. Assigning an empty list to an index, on the other hand, just stores a reference to the empty list in the specified slot, rather than deleting it:

>>> L = ['Already', 'got', 'one']
>>> L[1:] = []
>>> L
['Already']
>>> L[0] = []
>>> L
[[]]

Although all the operations just discussed are typical, there are additional list methods and operations not illustrated here (including methods for inserting and searching). For a comprehensive and up-to-date list of type tools, you should always consult Python’s manuals, Python’s dir and help functions (which we first met in Chapter 4), or one of the reference texts mentioned in the Preface.

I’d also like to remind you one more time that all the in-place change operations discussed here work only for mutable objects: they won’t work on strings (or tuples, discussed in Chapter 9), no matter how hard you try. Mutability is an inherent property of each object type.

Dictionaries

Apart from lists, dictionaries are perhaps the most flexible built-in data type in Python. If you think of lists as ordered collections of objects, you can think of dictionaries as unordered collections; the chief distinction is that in dictionaries, items are stored and fetched by key, instead of by positional offset.

Being a built-in type, dictionaries can replace many of the searching algorithms and data structures you might have to implement manually in lower-level languages—indexing a dictionary is a very fast search operation. Dictionaries also sometimes do the work of records and symbol tables used in other languages, can represent sparse (mostly empty) data structures, and much more. Here’s a rundown of their main properties. Python dictionaries are:

Accessed by key, not offset

Dictionaries are sometimes called associative arrays or hashes. They associate a set of values with keys, so you can fetch an item out of a dictionary using the key under which you originally stored it. You use the same indexing operation to get components in a dictionary as you do in a list, but the index takes the form of a key, not a relative offset.

Unordered collections of arbitrary objects

Unlike in a list, items stored in a dictionary aren’t kept in any particular order; in fact, Python randomizes their left-to-right order to provide quick lookup. Keys provide the symbolic (not physical) locations of items in a dictionary.

Variable-length, heterogeneous, and arbitrarily nestable

Like lists, dictionaries can grow and shrink in-place (without new copies being made), they can contain objects of any type, and they support nesting to any depth (they can contain lists, other dictionaries, and so on).

Of the category “mutable mapping”

Dictionaries can be changed in-place by assigning to indexes (they are mutable), but they don’t support the sequence operations that work on strings and lists. Because dictionaries are unordered collections, operations that depend on a fixed positional order (e.g., concatenation, slicing) don’t make sense. Instead, dictionaries are the only built-in representatives of the mapping type category (objects that map keys to values).

Tables of object references (hash tables)

If lists are arrays of object references that support access by position, dictionaries are unordered tables of object references that support access by key. Internally, dictionaries are implemented as hash tables (data structures that support very fast retrieval), which start small and grow on demand. Moreover, Python employs optimized hashing algorithms to find keys, so retrieval is quick. Like lists, dictionaries store object references (not copies).

Table 8-2 summarizes some of the most common and representative dictionary operations (again, see the library manual or run a dir(dict) or help(dict) call for a complete list—dict is the name of the type). When coded as a literal expression, a dictionary is written as a series of key:value pairs, separated by commas, enclosed in curly braces.[24] An empty dictionary is an empty set of braces, and dictionaries can be nested by writing one as a value inside another dictionary, or within a list or tuple.

Table 8-2. Common dictionary literals and operations

Operation

|

Interpretation

D = {}

|

Empty dictionary

D = {'spam': 2, 'eggs': 3}

|

Two-item dictionary

D = {'food': {'ham': 1, 'egg': 2}}

|

Nesting

D = dict(name='Bob', age=40)

D = dict(zip(keyslist, valslist))

D = dict.fromkeys(['a', 'b'])

|

Alternative construction techniques:

keywords, zipped pairs, key lists

D['eggs']

D['food']['ham']

|

Indexing by key

'eggs' in D

|

Membership: key present test

D.keys()

D.values()

D.items()

D.copy()

D.get(key, default)

D.update(D2)

D.pop(key)

|

Methods: keys,

values,

keys+values,

copies,

defaults,

merge,

delete, etc.

len(D)

|

Length: number of stored entries

D[key] = 42

|

Adding/changing keys

del D[key]

|

Deleting entries by key

list(D.keys())

D1.keys() & D2.keys()

|

Dictionary views (Python 3.0)

D = {x: x*2 for x in range(10)}

|

Dictionary comprehensions (Python 3.0)

Dictionaries in Action

As Table 8-2 suggests, dictionaries are indexed by key, and nested dictionary entries are referenced by a series of indexes (keys in square brackets). When Python creates a dictionary, it stores its items in any left-to-right order it chooses; to fetch a value back, you supply the key with which it is associated, not its relative position. Let’s go back to the interpreter to get a feel for some of the dictionary operations in Table 8-2.

Basic Dictionary Operations

In normal operation, you create dictionaries with literals and store and access items by key with indexing:

% python
>>> D = {'spam': 2, 'ham': 1, 'eggs': 3}      # Make a dictionary
>>> D['spam']                                 # Fetch a value by key
2
>>> D                                         # Order is scrambled
{'eggs': 3, 'ham': 1, 'spam': 2}

Here, the dictionary is assigned to the variable D; the value of the key 'spam' is the integer 2, and so on. We use the same square bracket syntax to index dictionaries by key as we did to index lists by offset, but here it means access by key, not by position.

Notice the end of this example: the left-to-right order of keys in a dictionary will almost always be different from what you originally typed. This is on purpose: to implement fast key lookup (a.k.a. hashing), keys need to be reordered in memory. That’s why operations that assume a fixed left-to-right order (e.g., slicing, concatenation) do not apply to dictionaries; you can fetch values only by key, not by position.

The built-in len function works on dictionaries, too; it returns the number of items stored in the dictionary or, equivalently, the length of its keys list. The dictionary in membership operator allows you to test for key existence, and the keys method returns all the keys in the dictionary. The latter of these can be useful for processing dictionaries sequentially, but you shouldn’t depend on the order of the keys list. Because the keys result can be used as a normal list, however, it can always be sorted if order matters (more on sorting and dictionaries later):

>>> len(D)                                    # Number of entries in dictionary
3
>>> 'ham' in D                                # Key membership test alternative
True
>>> list(D.keys())                            # Create a new list of my keys
['eggs', 'ham', 'spam']

Notice the second expression in this listing. As mentioned earlier, the in membership test used for strings and lists also works on dictionaries—it checks whether a key is stored in the dictionary. Technically, this works because dictionaries define iterators that step through their keys lists. Other types provide iterators that reflect their common uses; files, for example, have iterators that read line by line. We’ll discuss iterators in Chapters 14 and 20.

Also note the syntax of the last example in this listing. We have to enclose it in a list call in Python 3.0 for similar reasons—keys in 3.0 returns an iterator, instead of a physical list. The list call forces it to produce all its values at once so we can print them. In 2.6, keys builds and returns an actual list, so the list call isn’t needed to display results. More on this later in this chapter.

Note

The order of keys in a dictionary is arbitrary and can change from release to release, so don’t be alarmed if your dictionaries print in a different order than shown here. In fact, the order has changed for me too—I’m running all these examples with Python 3.0, but their keys had a different order in an earlier edition when displayed. You shouldn’t depend on dictionary key ordering, in either programs or books!

Changing Dictionaries In-Place

Let’s continue with our interactive session. Dictionaries, like lists, are mutable, so you can change, expand, and shrink them in-place without making new dictionaries: simply assign a value to a key to change or create an entry. The del statement works here, too; it deletes the entry associated with the key specified as an index. Notice also the nesting of a list inside a dictionary in this example (the value of the key 'ham'). All collection data types in Python can nest inside each other arbitrarily:

>>> D
{'eggs': 3, 'ham': 1, 'spam': 2}

>>> D['ham'] = ['grill', 'bake', 'fry']           # Change entry
>>> D
{'eggs': 3, 'ham': ['grill', 'bake', 'fry'], 'spam': 2}

>>> del D['eggs']                                 # Delete entry
>>> D
{'ham': ['grill', 'bake', 'fry'], 'spam': 2}

>>> D['brunch'] = 'Bacon'                         # Add new entry
>>> D
{'brunch': 'Bacon', 'ham': ['grill', 'bake', 'fry'], 'spam': 2}

As with lists, assigning to an existing index in a dictionary changes its associated value. Unlike with lists, however, whenever you assign a new dictionary key (one that hasn’t been assigned before) you create a new entry in the dictionary, as was done in the previous example for the key 'brunch'. This doesn’t work for lists because Python considers an offset beyond the end of a list out of bounds and throws an error. To expand a list, you need to use tools such as the append method or slice assignment instead.

More Dictionary Methods

Dictionary methods provide a variety of tools. For instance, the dictionary values and items methods return the dictionary’s values and (key,value) pair tuples, respectively (as with keys, wrap them in a list call in Python 3.0 to collect their values for display):

>>> D = {'spam': 2, 'ham': 1, 'eggs': 3}
>>> list(D.values())
[3, 1, 2]
>>> list(D.items())
 [('eggs', 3), ('ham', 1), ('spam', 2)]

Such lists are useful in loops that need to step through dictionary entries one by one. Fetching a nonexistent key is normally an error, but the get method returns a default value (None, or a passed-in default) if the key doesn’t exist. It’s an easy way to fill in a default for a key that isn’t present and avoid a missing-key error:

>>> D.get('spam')                          # A key that is there
2
>>> print(D.get('toast'))                  # A key that is missing
None
>>> D.get('toast', 88)
88

The update method provides something similar to concatenation for dictionaries, though it has nothing to do with left-to-right ordering (again, there is no such thing in dictionaries). It merges the keys and values of one dictionary into another, blindly overwriting values of the same key:

>>> D
{'eggs': 3, 'ham': 1, 'spam': 2}
>>> D2 = {'toast':4, 'muffin':5}
>>> D.update(D2)
>>> D
{'toast': 4, 'muffin': 5, 'eggs': 3, 'ham': 1, 'spam': 2}

Finally, the dictionary pop method deletes a key from a dictionary and returns the value it had. It’s similar to the list pop method, but it takes a key instead of an optional position:

# pop a dictionary by key
>>> D
{'toast': 4, 'muffin': 5, 'eggs': 3, 'ham': 1, 'spam': 2}
>>> D.pop('muffin')
5
>>> D.pop('toast')                         # Delete and return from a key
4
>>> D
{'eggs': 3, 'ham': 1, 'spam': 2}

# pop a list by position
>>> L = ['aa', 'bb', 'cc', 'dd']
>>> L.pop()                                # Delete and return from the end
'dd'
>>> L
['aa', 'bb', 'cc']
>>> L.pop(1)                               # Delete from a specific position
'bb'
>>> L
['aa', 'cc']

Dictionaries also provide a copy method; we’ll discuss this in Chapter 9, as it’s a way to avoid the potential side effects of shared references to the same dictionary. In fact, dictionaries come with many more methods than those listed in Table 8-2; see the Python library manual or other documentation sources for a comprehensive list.

A Languages Table

Let’s look at a more realistic dictionary example. The following example creates a table that maps programming language names (the keys) to their creators (the values). You fetch creator names by indexing on language names:

>>> table = {'Python':  'Guido van Rossum',
...          'Perl':    'Larry Wall',
...          'Tcl':     'John Ousterhout' }
>>>
>>> language = 'Python'
>>> creator  = table[language]
>>> creator
'Guido van Rossum'

>>> for lang in table:                     # Same as: for lang in table.keys()
...     print(lang, '\t', table[lang])
...
Tcl     John Ousterhout
Python  Guido van Rossum
Perl    Larry Wall

The last command uses a for loop, which we haven’t covered in detail yet. If you aren’t familiar with for loops, this command simply iterates through each key in the table and prints a tab-separated list of keys and their values. We’ll learn more about for loops in Chapter 13.

Dictionaries aren’t sequences like lists and strings, but if you need to step through the items in a dictionary, it’s easy—calling the dictionary keys method returns all stored keys, which you can iterate through with a for. If needed, you can index from key to value inside the for loop, as was done in this code.

In fact, Python also lets you step through a dictionary’s keys list without actually calling the keys method in most for loops. For any dictionary D, saying for key in D: works the same as saying the complete for key in D.keys():. This is really just another instance of the iterators mentioned earlier, which allow the in membership operator to work on dictionaries as well (more on iterators later in this book).

Dictionary Usage Notes

Dictionaries are fairly straightforward tools once you get the hang of them, but here are a few additional pointers and reminders you should be aware of when using them:

Sequence operations don’t work. Dictionaries are mappings, not sequences; because there’s no notion of ordering among their items, things like concatenation (an ordered joining) and slicing (extracting a contiguous section) simply don’t apply. In fact, Python raises an error when your code runs if you try to do such things.

Assigning to new indexes adds entries. Keys can be created when you write a dictionary literal (in which case they are embedded in the literal itself), or when you assign values to new keys of an existing dictionary object. The end result is the same.

Keys need not always be strings. Our examples so far have used strings as keys, but any other immutable objects (i.e., not lists) work just as well. For instance, you can use integers as keys, which makes the dictionary look much like a list (when indexing, at least). Tuples are sometimes used as dictionary keys too, allowing for compound key values. Class instance objects (discussed in Part VI) can also be used as keys, as long as they have the proper protocol methods; roughly, they need to tell Python that their values are hashable and won’t change, as otherwise they would be useless as fixed keys.

Using dictionaries to simulate flexible lists

The last point in the prior list is important enough to demonstrate with a few examples. When you use lists, it is illegal to assign to an offset that is off the end of the list:

>>> L = []
>>> L[99] = 'spam'
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "<stdin>", line 1, in ?
IndexError: list assignment index out of range

Although you can use repetition to preallocate as big a list as you’ll need (e.g., [0]*100), you can also do something that looks similar with dictionaries that does not require such space allocations. By using integer keys, dictionaries can emulate lists that seem to grow on offset assignment:

>>> D = {}
>>> D[99] = 'spam'
>>> D[99]
'spam'
>>> D
{99: 'spam'}

Here, it looks as if D is a 100-item list, but it’s really a dictionary with a single entry; the value of the key 99 is the string 'spam'. You can access this structure with offsets much like a list, but you don’t have to allocate space for all the positions you might ever need to assign values to in the future. When used like this, dictionaries are like more flexible equivalents of lists.

Using dictionaries for sparse data structures

In a similar way, dictionary keys are also commonly leveraged to implement sparse data structures—for example, multidimensional arrays where only a few positions have values stored in them:

>>> Matrix = {}
>>> Matrix[(2, 3, 4)] = 88
>>> Matrix[(7, 8, 9)] = 99
>>>
>>> X = 2; Y = 3; Z = 4           # ; separates statements
>>> Matrix[(X, Y, Z)]
88
>>> Matrix
{(2, 3, 4): 88, (7, 8, 9): 99}

Here, we’ve used a dictionary to represent a three-dimensional array that is empty except for the two positions (2,3,4) and (7,8,9). The keys are tuples that record the coordinates of nonempty slots. Rather than allocating a large and mostly empty three-dimensional matrix to hold these values, we can use a simple two-item dictionary. In this scheme, accessing an empty slot triggers a nonexistent key exception, as these slots are not physically stored:

>>> Matrix[(2,3,6)]
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "<stdin>", line 1, in ?
KeyError: (2, 3, 6)

Avoiding missing-key errors

Errors for nonexistent key fetches are common in sparse matrixes, but you probably won’t want them to shut down your program. There are at least three ways to fill in a default value instead of getting such an error message—you can test for keys ahead of time in if statements, use a try statement to catch and recover from the exception explicitly, or simply use the dictionary get method shown earlier to provide a default for keys that do not exist:

>>> if (2,3,6) in Matrix:              # Check for key before fetch
...     print(Matrix[(2,3,6)])         # See Chapter 12 for if/else
... else:
...     print(0)
...
0
>>> try:
...     print(Matrix[(2,3,6)])         # Try to index
... except KeyError:                   # Catch and recover
...     print(0)                       # See Chapter 33 for try/except
...
0
>>> Matrix.get((2,3,4), 0)             # Exists; fetch and return
88
>>> Matrix.get((2,3,6), 0)             # Doesn't exist; use default arg
0

Of these, the get method is the most concise in terms of coding requirements; we’ll study the if and try statements in more detail later in this book.

Using dictionaries as “records”

As you can see, dictionaries can play many roles in Python. In general, they can replace search data structures (because indexing by key is a search operation) and can represent many types of structured information. For example, dictionaries are one of many ways to describe the properties of an item in your program’s domain; that is, they can serve the same role as “records” or “structs” in other languages.

The following, for example, fills out a dictionary by assigning to new keys over time:

>>> rec = {}
>>> rec['name'] = 'mel'
>>> rec['age']  = 45
>>> rec['job']  = 'trainer/writer'
>>>
>>> print(rec['name'])
mel

Especially when nested, Python’s built-in data types allow us to easily represent structured information. This example again uses a dictionary to capture object properties, but it codes it all at once (rather than assigning to each key separately) and nests a list and a dictionary to represent structured property values:

>>> mel = {'name': 'Mark',
...        'jobs': ['trainer', 'writer'],
...        'web':  'www.rmi.net/˜lutz',
...        'home': {'state': 'CO', 'zip':80513}}

To fetch components of nested objects, simply string together indexing operations:

>>> mel['name']
'Mark'
>>> mel['jobs']
['trainer', 'writer']
>>> mel['jobs'][1]
'writer'
>>> mel['home']['zip']
80513

Although we’ll learn in Part VI that classes (which group both data and logic) can be better in this record role, dictionaries are an easy-to-use tool for simpler requirements.

Why You Will Care: Dictionary Interfaces

Dictionaries aren’t just a convenient way to store information by key in your programs—some Python extensions also present interfaces that look like and work the same as dictionaries. For instance, Python’s interface to DBM access-by-key files looks much like a dictionary that must be opened. Strings are stored and fetched using key indexes:

import dbm
file = dbm.open("filename")    # Link to file
file['key'] = 'data'           # Store data by key
data = file['key']             # Fetch data by key

In Chapter 27, you’ll see that you can store entire Python objects this way, too, if you replace dbm in the preceding code with shelve (shelves are access-by-key databases of persistent Python objects). For Internet work, Python’s CGI script support also presents a dictionary-like interface. A call to cgi.FieldStorage yields a dictionary-like object with one entry per input field on the client’s web page:

import cgi
form = cgi.FieldStorage()      # Parse form data
if 'name' in form:
    showReply('Hello, ' + form['name'].value)

All of these, like dictionaries, are instances of mappings. Once you learn dictionary interfaces, you’ll find that they apply to a variety of built-in tools in Python.

Other Ways to Make Dictionaries

Finally, note that because dictionaries are so useful, more ways to build them have emerged over time. In Python 2.3 and later, for example, the last two calls to the dict constructor (really, type name) shown here have the same effect as the literal and key-assignment forms above them:

{'name': 'mel', 'age': 45}             # Traditional literal expression

D = {}                                 # Assign by keys dynamically
D['name'] = 'mel'
D['age']  = 45

dict(name='mel', age=45)               # dict keyword argument form

dict([('name', 'mel'), ('age', 45)])   # dict key/value tuples form

All four of these forms create the same two-key dictionary, but they are useful in differing circumstances:

The first is handy if you can spell out the entire dictionary ahead of time.

The second is of use if you need to create the dictionary one field at a time on the fly.

The third involves less typing than the first, but it requires all keys to be strings.

The last is useful if you need to build up keys and values as sequences at runtime.

We met keyword arguments earlier when sorting; the third form illustrated in this code listing has become especially popular in Python code today, since it has less syntax (and hence there is less opportunity for mistakes). As suggested previously in Table 8-2, the last form in the listing is also commonly used in conjunction with the zip function, to combine separate lists of keys and values obtained dynamically at runtime (parsed out of a data file’s columns, for instance). More on this option in the next section.

Provided all the key’s values are the same initially, you can also create a dictionary with this special form—simply pass in a list of keys and an initial value for all of the values (the default is None):

>>> dict.fromkeys(['a', 'b'], 0)
{'a': 0, 'b': 0}

Although you could get by with just literals and key assignments at this point in your Python career, you’ll probably find uses for all of these dictionary-creation forms as you start applying them in realistic, flexible, and dynamic Python programs.

The listings in this section document the various ways to create dictionaries in both Python 2.6 and 3.0. However, there is yet another way to create dictionaries, available only in Python 3.0 (and later): the dictionary comprehension expression. To see how this last form looks, we need to move on to the next section.

Dictionary Changes in Python 3.0

This chapter has so far focused on dictionary basics that span releases, but the dictionary’s functionality has mutated in Python 3.0. If you are using Python 2.X code, you may come across some dictionary tools that either behave differently or are missing altogether in 3.0. Moreover, 3.0 coders have access to additional dictionary tools not available in 2.X. Specifically, dictionaries in 3.0:

Support a new dictionary comprehension expression, a close cousin to list and set comprehensions

Return iterable views instead of lists for the methods D.keys, D.values, and D.items

Require new coding styles for scanning by sorted keys, because of the prior point

No longer support relative magnitude comparisons directly—compare manually instead

No longer have the D.has_key method—the in membership test is used instead

Let’s take a look at what’s new in 3.0 dictionaries.

Dictionary comprehensions

As mentioned at the end of the prior section, dictionaries in 3.0 can also be created with dictionary comprehensions. Like the set comprehensions we met in Chapter 5, dictionary comprehensions are available only in 3.0 (not in 2.6). Like the longstanding list comprehensions we met briefly in Chapter 4 and earlier in this chapter, they run an implied loop, collecting the key/value results of expressions on each iteration and using them to fill out a new dictionary. A loop variable allows the comprehension to use loop iteration values along the way.

For example, a standard way to initialize a dictionary dynamically in both 2.6 and 3.0 is to zip together its keys and values and pass the result to the dict call. As we’ll learn in more detail in Chapter 13, the zip function is a way to construct a dictionary from key and value lists in a single call. If you cannot predict the set of keys and values in your code, you can always build them up as lists and zip them together:

>>> list(zip(['a', 'b', 'c'], [1, 2, 3]))        # Zip together keys and values
[('a', 1), ('b', 2), ('c', 3)]

>>> D = dict(zip(['a', 'b', 'c'], [1, 2, 3]))    # Make a dict from zip result
>>> D
{'a': 1, 'c': 3, 'b': 2}

In Python 3.0, you can achieve the same effect with a dictionary comprehension expression. The following builds a new dictionary with a key/value pair for every such pair in the zip result (it reads almost the same in Python, but with a bit more formality):

C:\misc> c:\python30\python                      # Use a dict comprehension

>>> D = {k: v for (k, v) in zip(['a', 'b', 'c'], [1, 2, 3])}
>>> D
{'a': 1, 'c': 3, 'b': 2}

Comprehensions actually require more code in this case, but they are also more general than this example implies—we can use them to map a single stream of values to dictionaries as well, and keys can be computed with expressions just like values:

>>> D = {x: x ** 2 for x in [1, 2, 3, 4]}        # Or: range(1, 5)
>>> D
{1: 1, 2: 4, 3: 9, 4: 16}

>>> D = {c: c * 4 for c in 'SPAM'}               # Loop over any iterable
>>> D
{'A': 'AAAA', 'P': 'PPPP', 'S': 'SSSS', 'M': 'MMMM'}

>>> D = {c.lower(): c + '!' for c in ['SPAM', 'EGGS', 'HAM']}
>>> D
{'eggs': 'EGGS!', 'ham': 'HAM!', 'spam': 'SPAM!'}

Dictionary comprehensions are also useful for initializing dictionaries from keys lists, in much the same way as the fromkeys method we met at the end of the preceding section:

>>> D = dict.fromkeys(['a', 'b', 'c'], 0)        # Initialize dict from keys
>>> D
{'a': 0, 'c': 0, 'b': 0}

>>> D = {k:0 for k in ['a', 'b', 'c']}           # Same, but with a comprehension
>>> D
{'a': 0, 'c': 0, 'b': 0}

>>> D = dict.fromkeys('spam')                    # Other iterators, default value
>>> D
{'a': None, 'p': None, 's': None, 'm': None}

>>> D = {k: None for k in 'spam'}
>>> D
{'a': None, 'p': None, 's': None, 'm': None}

Like related tools, dictionary comprehensions support additional syntax not shown here, including nested loops and if clauses. Unfortunately, to truly understand dictionary comprehensions, we need to also know more about iteration statements and concepts in Python, and we don’t yet have enough information to address that story well. We’ll learn much more about all flavors of comprehensions (list, set, and dictionary) in Chapters 14 and 20, so we’ll defer further details until later. We’ll also study the zip built-in we used in this section in more detail in Chapter 13, when we explore for loops.

Dictionary views

In 3.0 the dictionary keys, values, and items methods all return view objects, whereas in 2.6 they return actual result lists. View objects are iterables, which simply means objects that generate result items one at a time, instead of producing the result list all at once in memory. Besides being iterable, dictionary views also retain the original order of dictionary components, reflect future changes to the dictionary, and may support set operations. On the other hand, they are not lists, and they do not support operations like indexing or the list sort method; nor do they display their items when printed.

We’ll discuss the notion of iterables more formally in Chapter 14, but for our purposes here it’s enough to know that we have to run the results of these three methods through the list built-in if we want to apply list operations or display their values:

>>> D = dict(a=1, b=2, c=3)
>>> D
{'a': 1, 'c': 3, 'b': 2}

>>> K = D.keys()                   # Makes a view object in 3.0, not a list
>>> K
<dict_keys object at 0x026D83C0>
>>> list(K)                        # Force a real list in 3.0 if needed
['a', 'c', 'b']

>>> V = D.values()                 # Ditto for values and items views
>>> V
<dict_values object at 0x026D8260>
>>> list(V)
[1, 3, 2]

>>> list(D.items())
[('a', 1), ('c', 3), ('b', 2)]

>>> K[0]                           # List operations fail unless converted
TypeError: 'dict_keys' object does not support indexing
>>> list(K)[0]
'a'

Apart from when displaying results at the interactive prompt, you will probably rarely even notice this change, because looping constructs in Python automatically force iterable objects to produce one result on each iteration:

>>> for k in D.keys(): print(k)    # Iterators used automatically in loops
...
a
c
b

In addition, 3.0 dictionaries still have iterators themselves, which return successive keys—as in 2.6, it’s still often not necessary to call keys directly:

>>> for key in D: print(key)       # Still no need to call keys() to iterate
...
a
c
b

Unlike 2.X’s list results, though, dictionary views in 3.0 are not carved in stone when created—they dynamically reflect future changes made to the dictionary after the view object has been created:

>>> D = {'a':1, 'b':2, 'c':3}
>>> D
{'a': 1, 'c': 3, 'b': 2}

>>> K = D.keys()
>>> V = D.values()
>>> list(K)                        # Views maintain same order as dictionary
['a', 'c', 'b']
>>> list(V)
[1, 3, 2]

>>> del D['b']                     # Change the dictionary in-place
>>> D
{'a': 1, 'c': 3}

>>> list(K)                        # Reflected in any current view objects
['a', 'c']
>>> list(V)                        # Not true in 2.X!
[1, 3]

Dictionary views and sets

Also unlike 2.X’s list results, 3.0’s view objects returned by the keys method are set-like and support common set operations such as intersection and union; values views are not, since they aren’t unique, but items results are if their (key, value) pairs are unique and hashable. Given that sets behave much like valueless dictionaries (and are even coded in curly braces like dictionaries in 3.0), this is a logical symmetry. Like dictionary keys, set items are unordered, unique, and immutable.

Here is what keys lists look like when used in set operations. In set operations, views may be mixed with other views, sets, and dictionaries (dictionaries are treated the same as their keys views in this context):

>>> K | {'x': 4}                   # Keys (and some items) views are set-like
{'a', 'x', 'c'}

>>> V & {'x': 4}
TypeError: unsupported operand type(s) for &: 'dict_values' and 'dict'
>>> V & {'x': 4}.values()
TypeError: unsupported operand type(s) for &: 'dict_values' and 'dict_values'

>>> D = {'a':1, 'b':2, 'c':3}
>>> D.keys() & D.keys()            # Intersect keys views
{'a', 'c', 'b'}
>>> D.keys() & {'b'}               # Intersect keys and set
{'b'}
>>> D.keys() & {'b': 1}            # Intersect keys and dict
{'b'}
>>> D.keys() | {'b', 'c', 'd'}     # Union keys and set
{'a', 'c', 'b', 'd'}

Dictionary items views are set-like too if they are hashable—that is, if they contain only immutable objects:

>>> D = {'a': 1}
>>> list(D.items())                # Items set-like if hashable
[('a', 1)]
>>> D.items() | D.keys()           # Union view and view
{('a', 1), 'a'}
>>> D.items() | D                  # dict treated same as its keys
{('a', 1), 'a'}

>>> D.items() | {('c', 3), ('d', 4)}           # Set of key/value pairs
{('a', 1), ('d', 4), ('c', 3)}
>>> dict(D.items() | {('c', 3), ('d', 4)})     # dict accepts iterable sets too
{'a': 1, 'c': 3, 'd': 4}

For more details on set operations in general, see Chapter 5. Now, let’s look at three other quick coding notes for 3.0 dictionaries.

Sorting dictionary keys

First of all, because keys does not return a list, the traditional coding pattern for scanning a dictionary by sorted keys in 2.X won’t work in 3.0. You must either convert to a list manually or use the sorted call introduced in Chapter 4 and earlier in this chapter on either a keys view or the dictionary itself:

>>> D = {'a':1, 'b':2, 'c':3}
>>> D
{'a': 1, 'c': 3, 'b': 2}

>>> Ks = D.keys()                            # Sorting a view object doesn't work!
>>> Ks.sort()
AttributeError: 'dict_keys' object has no attribute 'sort'

>>> Ks = list(Ks)                            # Force it to be a list and then sort
>>> Ks.sort()
>>> for k in Ks: print(k, D[k])
...
a 1
b 2
c 3

>>> D
{'a': 1, 'c': 3, 'b': 2}
>>> Ks = D.keys()                            # Or you can use sorted() on the keys
>>> for k in sorted(Ks): print(k, D[k])      # sorted() accepts any iterable
...                                          # sorted() returns its result
a 1
b 2
c 3

>>> D
{'a': 1, 'c': 3, 'b': 2}                     # Better yet, sort the dict directly
>>> for k in sorted(D): print(k, D[k])       # dict iterators return keys
...
a 1
b 2
c 3

Dictionary magnitude comparisons no longer work

Secondly, while in Python 2.6 dictionaries may be compared for relative magnitude directly with <, >, and so on, in Python 3.0 this no longer works. However, it can be simulated by comparing sorted keys lists manually:

sorted(D1.items()) < sorted(D2.items())      # Like 2.6 D1 < D2

Dictionary equality tests still work in 3.0, though. Since we’ll revisit this in the next chapter in the context of comparisons at large, we’ll defer further details here.

The has_key method is dead: long live in!

Finally, the widely used dictionary has_key key presence test method is gone in 3.0. Instead, use the in membership expression, or a get with a default test (of these, in is generally preferred):

>>> D
{'a': 1, 'c': 3, 'b': 2}

>>> D.has_key('c')                                        # 2.X only: True/False
AttributeError: 'dict' object has no attribute 'has_key'

>>> 'c' in D
True
>>> 'x' in D
False
>>> if 'c' in D: print('present', D['c'])                 # Preferred in 3.0
...
present 3

>>> print(D.get('c'))
3
>>> print(D.get('x'))
None
>>> if D.get('c') != None: print('present', D['c'])       # Another option
...
present 3

If you work in 2.6 and care about 3.0 compatibility, note that the first two changes (comprehensions and views) can only be coded in 3.0, but the last three (sorted, manual comparisons, and in) can be coded in 2.6 today to ease 3.0 migration in the future.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

A literal expression like [0, 0, 0, 0, 0] and a repetition expression like [0] * 5 will each create a list of five zeros. In practice, you might also build one up with a loop that starts with an empty list and appends 0 to it in each iteration:

L.append(0). A list comprehension ([0 for i in range(5)]) could work here, too, but this is more work than you need to do.

A literal expression such as {'a': 0, 'b': 0} or a series of assignments like D = {}, D['a'] = 0, and D['b'] = 0 would create the desired dictionary. You can also use the newer and simpler-to-code dict(a=0, b=0) keyword form, or the more flexible dict([('a', 0), ('b', 0)]) key/value sequences form. Or, because all the values are the same, you can use the special form dict.fromkeys('ab', 0). In 3.0, you can also use a dictionary comprehension: {k:0 for k in 'ab'}.

The append and extend methods grow a list in-place, the sort and reverse methods order and reverse lists, the insert method inserts an item at an offset, the remove and pop methods delete from a list by value and by position, the del statement deletes an item or slice, and index and slice assignment statements replace an item or entire section. Pick any four of these for the quiz.

Dictionaries are primarily changed by assignment to a new or existing key, which creates or changes the key’s entry in the table. Also, the del statement deletes a key’s entry, the dictionary update method merges one dictionary into another in-place, and D.pop(key) removes a key and returns the value it had. Dictionaries also have other, more exotic in-place change methods not listed in this chapter, such as setdefault; see reference sources for more details.

[21] In practice, you won’t see many lists written out like this in list-processing programs. It’s more common to see code that processes lists constructed dynamically (at runtime). In fact, although it’s important to master literal syntax, most data structures in Python are built by running program code at runtime.

[22] This description needs elaboration when the value and the slice being assigned overlap: L[2:5]=L[3:6], for instance, works fine because the value to be inserted is fetched before the deletion happens on the left.

[23] Unlike + concatenation, append doesn’t have to generate new objects, so it’s usually faster. You can also mimic append with clever slice assignments: L[len(L):]=[X] is like L.append(X), and L[:0]=[X] is like appending at the front of a list. Both delete an empty slice and insert X, changing L in-place quickly, like append.

[24] As with lists, you won’t often see dictionaries constructed using literals. Lists and dictionaries are grown in different ways, though. As you’ll see in the next section, dictionaries are typically built up by assigning to new keys at runtime; this approach fails for lists (lists are commonly grown with append instead).

Tuples

The last collection type in our survey is the Python tuple. Tuples construct simple groups of objects. They work exactly like lists, except that tuples can’t be changed in-place (they’re immutable) and are usually written as a series of items in parentheses, not square brackets. Although they don’t support as many methods, tuples share most of their properties with lists. Here’s a quick look at the basics. Tuples are:

Ordered collections of arbitrary objects

Like strings and lists, tuples are positionally ordered collections of objects (i.e., they maintain a left-to-right order among their contents); like lists, they can embed any kind of object.

Accessed by offset

Like strings and lists, items in a tuple are accessed by offset (not by key); they support all the offset-based access operations, such as indexing and slicing.

Of the category “immutable sequence”

Like strings and lists, tuples are sequences; they support many of the same operations. However, like strings, tuples are immutable; they don’t support any of the in-place change operations applied to lists.

Fixed-length, heterogeneous, and arbitrarily nestable

Because tuples are immutable, you cannot change the size of a tuple without making a copy. On the other hand, tuples can hold any type of object, including other compound objects (e.g., lists, dictionaries, other tuples), and so support arbitrary nesting.

Arrays of object references

Like lists, tuples are best thought of as object reference arrays; tuples store access points to other objects (references), and indexing a tuple is relatively quick.

Table 9-1 highlights common tuple operations. A tuple is written as a series of objects (technically, expressions that generate objects), separated by commas and normally enclosed in parentheses. An empty tuple is just a parentheses pair with nothing inside.

Table 9-1. Common tuple literals and operations

Operation

|

Interpretation

()

|

An empty tuple

T = (0,)

|

A one-item tuple (not an expression)

T = (0, 'Ni', 1.2, 3)

|

A four-item tuple

T = 0, 'Ni', 1.2, 3

|

Another four-item tuple (same as prior line)

T = ('abc', ('def', 'ghi'))

|

Nested tuples

T = tuple('spam')

|

Tuple of items in an iterable

T[i]

T[i][j]

T[i:j]

len(T)

|

Index, index of index, slice, length

T1 + T2

T * 3

|

Concatenate, repeat

for x in T: print(x)

'spam' in T

[x ** 2 for x in T]

|

Iteration, membership

T.index('Ni')

T.count('Ni')

|

Methods in 2.6 and 3.0: search, count

Tuples in Action

As usual, let’s start an interactive session to explore tuples at work. Notice in Table 9-1 that tuples do not have all the methods that lists have (e.g., an append call won’t work here). They do, however, support the usual sequence operations that we saw for both strings and lists:

>>> (1, 2) + (3, 4)            # Concatenation
(1, 2, 3, 4)

>>> (1, 2) * 4                 # Repetition
(1, 2, 1, 2, 1, 2, 1, 2)

>>> T = (1, 2, 3, 4)           # Indexing, slicing
>>> T[0], T[1:3]
(1, (2, 3))

Tuple syntax peculiarities: Commas and parentheses

The second and fourth entries in Table 9-1 merit a bit more explanation. Because parentheses can also enclose expressions (see Chapter 5), you need to do something special to tell Python when a single object in parentheses is a tuple object and not a simple expression. If you really want a single-item tuple, simply add a trailing comma after the single item, before the closing parenthesis:

>>> x = (40)                   # An integer!
>>> x
40
>>> y = (40,)                  # A tuple containing an integer
>>> y
(40,)

As a special case, Python also allows you to omit the opening and closing parentheses for a tuple in contexts where it isn’t syntactically ambiguous to do so. For instance, the fourth line of Table 9-1 simply lists four items separated by commas. In the context of an assignment statement, Python recognizes this as a tuple, even though it doesn’t have parentheses.

Now, some people will tell you to always use parentheses in your tuples, and some will tell you to never use parentheses in tuples (and still others have lives, and won’t tell you what to do with your tuples!). The only significant places where the parentheses are required are when a tuple is passed as a literal in a function call (where parentheses matter), and when one is listed in a Python 2.X print statement (where commas are significant).

For beginners, the best advice is that it’s probably easier to use the parentheses than it is to figure out when they are optional. Many programmers (myself included) also find that parentheses tend to aid script readability by making the tuples more explicit, but your mileage may vary.

Conversions, methods, and immutability

Apart from literal syntax differences, tuple operations (the middle rows in Table 9-1) are identical to string and list operations. The only differences worth noting are that the +, *, and slicing operations return new tuples when applied to tuples, and that tuples don’t provide the same methods you saw for strings, lists, and dictionaries. If you want to sort a tuple, for example, you’ll usually have to either first convert it to a list to gain access to a sorting method call and make it a mutable object, or use the newer sorted built-in that accepts any sequence object (and more):

>>> T = ('cc', 'aa', 'dd', 'bb')
>>> tmp = list(T)                  # Make a list from a tuple's items
>>> tmp.sort()                     # Sort the list
>>> tmp
['aa', 'bb', 'cc', 'dd']
>>> T = tuple(tmp)                 # Make a tuple from the list's items
>>> T
('aa', 'bb', 'cc', 'dd')

>>> sorted(T)                      # Or use the sorted built-in
['aa', 'bb', 'cc', 'dd']

Here, the list and tuple built-in functions are used to convert the object to a list and then back to a tuple; really, both calls make new objects, but the net effect is like a conversion.

List comprehensions can also be used to convert tuples. The following, for example, makes a list from a tuple, adding 20 to each item along the way:

>>> T = (1, 2, 3, 4, 5)
>>> L = [x + 20 for x in T]
>>> L
[21, 22, 23, 24, 25]

List comprehensions are really sequence operations—they always build new lists, but they may be used to iterate over any sequence objects, including tuples, strings, and other lists. As we’ll see later in the book, they even work on some things that are not physically stored sequences—any iterable objects will do, including files, which are automatically read line by line.

Although tuples don’t have the same methods as lists and strings, they do have two of their own as of Python 2.6 and 3.0—index and count works as they do for lists, but they are defined for tuple objects:

>>> T = (1, 2, 3, 2, 4, 2)         # Tuple methods in 2.6 and 3.0
>>> T.index(2)                     # Offset of first appearance of 2
1
>>> T.index(2, 2)                  # Offset of appearance after offset 2
3
>>> T.count(2)                     # How many 2s are there?
3

Prior to 2.6 and 3.0, tuples have no methods at all—this was an old Python convention for immutable types, which was violated years ago on grounds of practicality with strings, and more recently with both numbers and tuples.

Also, note that the rule about tuple immutability applies only to the top level of the tuple itself, not to its contents. A list inside a tuple, for instance, can be changed as usual:

>>> T = (1, [2, 3], 4)
>>> T[1] = 'spam'                  # This fails: can't change tuple itself
TypeError: object doesn't support item assignment

>>> T[1][0] = 'spam'               # This works: can change mutables inside
>>> T
(1, ['spam', 3], 4)

For most programs, this one-level-deep immutability is sufficient for common tuple roles. Which, coincidentally, brings us to the next section.

Why Lists and Tuples?

This seems to be the first question that always comes up when teaching beginners about tuples: why do we need tuples if we have lists? Some of the reasoning may be historic; Python’s creator is a mathematician by training, and he has been quoted as seeing a tuple as a simple association of objects and a list as a data structure that changes over time. In fact, this use of the word “tuple” derives from mathematics, as does its frequent use for a row in a relational database table.

The best answer, however, seems to be that the immutability of tuples provides some integrity—you can be sure a tuple won’t be changed through another reference elsewhere in a program, but there’s no such guarantee for lists. Tuples, therefore, serve a similar role to “constant” declarations in other languages, though the notion of constantness is associated with objects in Python, not variables.

Tuples can also be used in places that lists cannot—for example, as dictionary keys (see the sparse matrix example in Chapter 8). Some built-in operations may also require or imply tuples, not lists, though such operations have often been generalized in recent years. As a rule of thumb, lists are the tool of choice for ordered collections that might need to change; tuples can handle the other cases of fixed associations.

Files

You may already be familiar with the notion of files, which are named storage compartments on your computer that are managed by your operating system. The last major built-in object type that we’ll examine on our object types tour provides a way to access those files inside Python programs.

In short, the built-in open function creates a Python file object, which serves as a link to a file residing on your machine. After calling open, you can transfer strings of data to and from the associated external file by calling the returned file object’s methods.

Compared to the types you’ve seen so far, file objects are somewhat unusual. They’re not numbers, sequences, or mappings, and they don’t respond to expression operators; they export only methods for common file-processing tasks. Most file methods are concerned with performing input from and output to the external file associated with a file object, but other file methods allow us to seek to a new position in the file, flush output buffers, and so on. Table 9-2 summarizes common file operations.

Table 9-2. Common file operations

Operation

|

Interpretation

output = open(r'C:\spam', 'w')

|

Create output file ('w' means write)

input = open('data', 'r')

|

Create input file ('r' means read)

input = open('data')

|

Same as prior line ('r' is the default)

aString = input.read()

|

Read entire file into a single string

aString = input.read(N)

|

Read up to next N characters (or bytes) into a string

aString = input.readline()

|

Read next line (including \n newline) into a string

aList = input.readlines()

|

Read entire file into list of line strings (with \n)

output.write(aString)

|

Write a string of characters (or bytes) into file

output.writelines(aList)

|

Write all line strings in a list into file

output.close()

|

Manual close (done for you when file is collected)

output.flush()

|

Flush output buffer to disk without closing

anyFile.seek(N)

|

Change file position to offset N for next operation

for line in open('data'): use line

|

File iterators read line by line

open('f.txt', encoding='latin-1')

|

Python 3.0 Unicode text files (str strings)

open('f.bin', 'rb')

|

Python 3.0 binary bytes files (bytes strings)

Opening Files

To open a file, a program calls the built-in open function, with the external filename first, followed by a processing mode. The mode is typically the string 'r' to open for text input (the default), 'w' to create and open for text output, or 'a' to open for appending text to the end. The processing mode argument can specify additional options:

Adding a b to the mode string allows for binary data (end-of-line translations and 3.0 Unicode encodings are turned off).

Adding a + opens the file for both input and output (i.e., you can both read and write to the same file object, often in conjunction with seek operations to reposition in the file).

Both arguments to open must be Python strings, and an optional third argument can be used to control output buffering—passing a zero means that output is unbuffered (it is transferred to the external file immediately on a write method call). The external filename argument may include a platform-specific and absolute or relative directory path prefix; without a directory path, the file is assumed to exist in the current working directory (i.e., where the script runs). We’ll cover file fundamentals and explore some basic examples here, but we won’t go into all file-processing mode options; as usual, consult the Python library manual for additional details.

Using Files

Once you make a file object with open, you can call its methods to read from or write to the associated external file. In all cases, file text takes the form of strings in Python programs; reading a file returns its text in strings, and text is passed to the write methods as strings. Reading and writing methods come in multiple flavors; Table 9-2 lists the most common. Here are a few fundamental usage notes:

File iterators are best for reading lines

Though the reading and writing methods in the table are common, keep in mind that probably the best way to read lines from a text file today is to not read the file at all—as we’ll see in Chapter 14, files also have an iterator that automatically reads one line at a time in a for loop, list comprehension, or other iteration context.

Content is strings, not objects

Notice in Table 9-2 that data read from a file always comes back to your script as a string, so you’ll have to convert it to a different type of Python object if a string is not what you need. Similarly, unlike with the print operation, Python does not add any formatting and does not convert objects to strings automatically when you write data to a file—you must send an already formatted string. Because of this, the tools we have already met to convert objects to and from strings (e.g., int, float, str, and the string formatting expression and method) come in handy when dealing with files. Python also includes advanced standard library tools for handling generic object storage (such as the pickle module) and for dealing with packed binary data in files (such as the struct module). We’ll see both of these at work later in this chapter.

close is usually optional

Calling the file close method terminates your connection to the external file. As discussed in Chapter 6, in Python an object’s memory space is automatically reclaimed as soon as the object is no longer referenced anywhere in the program. When file objects are reclaimed, Python also automatically closes the files if they are still open (this also happens when a program shuts down). This means you don’t always need to manually close your files, especially in simple scripts that don’t run for long. On the other hand, including manual close calls can’t hurt and is usually a good idea in larger systems. Also, strictly speaking, this auto-close-on-collection feature of files is not part of the language definition, and it may change over time. Consequently, manually issuing file close method calls is a good habit to form. (For an alternative way to guarantee automatic file closes, also see this section’s later discussion of the file object’s context manager, used with the new with/as statement in Python 2.6 and 3.0.)

Files are buffered and seekable.

The prior paragraph’s notes about closing files are important, because closing both frees up operating system resources and flushes output buffers. By default, output files are always buffered, which means that text you write may not be transferred from memory to disk immediately—closing a file, or running its flush method, forces the buffered data to disk. You can avoid buffering with extra open arguments, but it may impede performance. Python files are also random-access on a byte offset basis—their seek method allows your scripts to jump around to read and write at specific locations.

Files in Action

Let’s work through a simple example that demonstrates file-processing basics. The following code begins by opening a new text file for output, writing two lines (strings terminated with a newline marker, \n), and closing the file. Later, the example opens the same file again in input mode and reads the lines back one at a time with readline. Notice that the third readline call returns an empty string; this is how Python file methods tell you that you’ve reached the end of the file (empty lines in the file come back as strings containing just a newline character, not as empty strings). Here’s the complete interaction:

>>> myfile = open('myfile.txt', 'w')        # Open for text output: create/empty
>>> myfile.write('hello text file\n')       # Write a line of text: string
16
>>> myfile.write('goodbye text file\n')
18
>>> myfile.close()                          # Flush output buffers to disk

>>> myfile = open('myfile.txt')             # Open for text input: 'r' is default
>>> myfile.readline()                       # Read the lines back
'hello text file\n'
>>> myfile.readline()
'goodbye text file\n'
>>> myfile.readline()                       # Empty string: end of file
''

Notice that file write calls return the number of characters written in Python 3.0; in 2.6 they don’t, so you won’t see these numbers echoed interactively. This example writes each line of text, including its end-of-line terminator, \n, as a string; write methods don’t add the end-of-line character for us, so we must include it to properly terminate our lines (otherwise the next write will simply extend the current line in the file).

If you want to display the file’s content with end-of-line characters interpreted, read the entire file into a string all at once with the file object’s read method and print it:

>>> open('myfile.txt').read()               # Read all at once into string
'hello text file\ngoodbye text file\n'

>>> print(open('myfile.txt').read())        # User-friendly display
hello text file
goodbye text file

And if you want to scan a text file line by line, file iterators are often your best option:

>>> for line in open('myfile.txt'):             # Use file iterators, not reads
...     print(line, end='')
...
hello text file
goodbye text file

When coded this way, the temporary file object created by open will automatically read and return one line on each loop iteration. This form is usually easiest to code, good on memory use, and may be faster than some other options (depending on many variables, of course). Since we haven’t reached statements or iterators yet, though, you’ll have to wait until Chapter 14 for a more complete explanation of this code.

Text and binary files in Python 3.0

Strictly speaking, the example in the prior section uses text files. In both Python 3.0 and 2.6, file type is determined by the second argument to open, the mode string—an included “b” means binary. Python has always supported both text and binary files, but in Python 3.0 there is a sharper distinction between the two:

Text files represent content as normal str strings, perform Unicode encoding and decoding automatically, and perform end-of-line translation by default.

Binary files represent content as a special bytes string type and allow programs to access file content unaltered.

In contrast, Python 2.6 text files handle both 8-bit text and binary data, and a special string type and file interface (unicode strings and codecs.open) handles Unicode text. The differences in Python 3.0 stem from the fact that simple and Unicode text have been merged in the normal string type—which makes sense, given that all text is Unicode, including ASCII and other 8-bit encodings.

Because most programmers deal only with ASCII text, they can get by with the basic text file interface used in the prior example, and normal strings. All strings are technically Unicode in 3.0, but ASCII users will not generally notice. In fact, files and strings work the same in 3.0 and 2.6 if your script’s scope is limited to such simple forms of text.

If you need to handle internationalized applications or byte-oriented data, though, the distinction in 3.0 impacts your code (usually for the better). In general, you must use bytes strings for binary files, and normal str strings for text files. Moreover, because text files implement Unicode encodings, you cannot open a binary data file in text mode—decoding its content to Unicode text will likely fail.

Let’s look at an example. When you read a binary data file you get back a bytes object—a sequence of small integers that represent absolute byte values (which may or may not correspond to characters), which looks and feels almost exactly like a normal string:

>>> data = open('data.bin', 'rb').read()    # Open binary file: rb=read binary
>>> data                                    # bytes string holds binary data
b'\x00\x00\x00\x07spam\x00\x08'
>>> data[4:8]                               # Act like strings
b'spam'
>>> data[4:8][0]                            # But really are small 8-bit integers
115
>>> bin(data[4:8][0])                       # Python 3.0 bin() function
'0b1110011'

In addition, binary files do not perform any end-of-line translation on data; text files by default map all forms to and from \n when written and read and implement Unicode encodings on transfers. Since Unicode and binary data is of marginal interest to many Python programmers, we’ll postpone the full story until Chapter 36. For now, let’s move on to some more substantial file examples.

Storing and parsing Python objects in files

Our next example writes a variety of Python objects into a text file on multiple lines. Notice that it must convert objects to strings using conversion tools. Again, file data is always strings in our scripts, and write methods do not do any automatic to-string formatting for us (for space, I’m omitting byte-count return values from write methods from here on):

>>> X, Y, Z = 43, 44, 45                    # Native Python objects
>>> S = 'Spam'                              # Must be strings to store in file
>>> D = {'a': 1, 'b': 2}
>>> L = [1, 2, 3]
>>>
>>> F = open('datafile.txt', 'w')           # Create output file
>>> F.write(S + '\n')                       # Terminate lines with \n
>>> F.write('%s,%s,%s\n' % (X, Y, Z))       # Convert numbers to strings
>>> F.write(str(L) + '$' + str(D) + '\n')   # Convert and separate with $
>>> F.close()

Once we have created our file, we can inspect its contents by opening it and reading it into a string (a single operation). Notice that the interactive echo gives the exact byte contents, while the print operation interprets embedded end-of-line characters to render a more user-friendly display:

>>> chars = open('datafile.txt').read()        # Raw string display
>>> chars
"Spam\n43,44,45\n[1, 2, 3]${'a': 1, 'b': 2}\n"
>>> print(chars)                               # User-friendly display
Spam
43,44,45
[1, 2, 3]${'a': 1, 'b': 2}

We now have to use other conversion tools to translate from the strings in the text file to real Python objects. As Python never converts strings to numbers (or other types of objects) automatically, this is required if we need to gain access to normal object tools like indexing, addition, and so on:

>>> F = open('datafile.txt')                  # Open again
>>> line = F.readline()                       # Read one line
>>> line
'Spam\n'
>>> line.rstrip()                             # Remove end-of-line
'Spam'

For this first line, we used the string rstrip method to get rid of the trailing end-of-line character; a line[:−1] slice would work, too, but only if we can be sure all lines end in the \n character (the last line in a file sometimes does not).

So far, we’ve read the line containing the string. Now let’s grab the next line, which contains numbers, and parse out (that is, extract) the objects on that line:

>>> line = F.readline()                       # Next line from file
>>> line                                      # It's a string here
'43,44,45\n'
>>> parts = line.split(',')                   # Split (parse) on commas
>>> parts
['43', '44', '45\n']

We used the string split method here to chop up the line on its comma delimiters; the result is a list of substrings containing the individual numbers. We still must convert from strings to integers, though, if we wish to perform math on these:

>>> int(parts[1])                             # Convert from string to int
44
>>> numbers = [int(P) for P in parts]         # Convert all in list at once
>>> numbers
[43, 44, 45]

As we have learned, int translates a string of digits into an integer object, and the list comprehension expression introduced in Chapter 4 can apply the call to each item in our list all at once (you’ll find more on list comprehensions later in this book). Notice that we didn’t have to run rstrip to delete the \n at the end of the last part; int and some other converters quietly ignore whitespace around digits.

Finally, to convert the stored list and dictionary in the third line of the file, we can run them through eval, a built-in function that treats a string as a piece of executable program code (technically, a string containing a Python expression):

>>> line = F.readline()
>>> line
"[1, 2, 3]${'a': 1, 'b': 2}\n"
>>> parts = line.split('$')                   # Split (parse) on $
>>> parts
['[1, 2, 3]', "{'a': 1, 'b': 2}\n"]
>>> eval(parts[0])                            # Convert to any object type
[1, 2, 3]
>>> objects = [eval(P) for P in parts]        # Do same for all in list
>>> objects
[[1, 2, 3], {'a': 1, 'b': 2}]

Because the end result of all this parsing and converting is a list of normal Python objects instead of strings, we can now apply list and dictionary operations to them in our script.

Storing native Python objects with pickle

Using eval to convert from strings to objects, as demonstrated in the preceding code, is a powerful tool. In fact, sometimes it’s too powerful. eval will happily run any Python expression—even one that might delete all the files on your computer, given the necessary permissions! If you really want to store native Python objects, but you can’t trust the source of the data in the file, Python’s standard library pickle module is ideal.

The pickle module is an advanced tool that allows us to store almost any Python object in a file directly, with no to- or from-string conversion requirement on our part. It’s like a super-general data formatting and parsing utility. To store a dictionary in a file, for instance, we pickle it directly:

>>> D = {'a': 1, 'b': 2}
>>> F = open('datafile.pkl', 'wb')
>>> import pickle
>>> pickle.dump(D, F)                         # Pickle any object to file
>>> F.close()

Then, to get the dictionary back later, we simply use pickle again to re-create it:

>>> F = open('datafile.pkl', 'rb')
>>> E = pickle.load(F)                        # Load any object from file
>>> E
{'a': 1, 'b': 2}

We get back an equivalent dictionary object, with no manual splitting or converting required. The pickle module performs what is known as object serialization—converting objects to and from strings of bytes—but requires very little work on our part. In fact, pickle internally translates our dictionary to a string form, though it’s not much to look at (and may vary if we pickle in other data protocol modes):

>>> open('datafile.pkl', 'rb').read()         # Format is prone to change!
b'\x80\x03}q\x00(X\x01\x00\x00\x00aq\x01K\x01X\x01\x00\x00\x00bq\x02K\x02u.'

Because pickle can reconstruct the object from this format, we don’t have to deal with that ourselves. For more on the pickle module, see the Python standard library manual, or import pickle and pass it to help interactively. While you’re exploring, also take a look at the shelve module. shelve is a tool that uses pickle to store Python objects in an access-by-key filesystem, which is beyond our scope here (though you will get to see an example of shelve in action in Chapter 27, and other pickle examples in Chapters 30 and 36).

Note

Note that I opened the file used to store the pickled object in binary mode; binary mode is always required in Python 3.0, because the pickler creates and uses a bytes string object, and these objects imply binary-mode files (text-mode files imply str strings in 3.0). In earlier Pythons it’s OK to use text-mode files for protocol 0 (the default, which creates ASCII text), as long as text mode is used consistently; higher protocols require binary-mode files. Python 3.0’s default protocol is 3 (binary), but it creates bytes even for protocol 0. See Chapter 36, Python’s library manual, or reference books for more details on this.

Python 2.6 also has a cPickle module, which is an optimized version of pickle that can be imported directly for speed. Python 3.0 renames this module _pickle and uses it automatically in pickle—scripts simply import pickle and let Python optimize itself.

Storing and parsing packed binary data in files

One other file-related note before we move on: some advanced applications also need to deal with packed binary data, created perhaps by a C language program. Python’s standard library includes a tool to help in this domain—the struct module knows how to both compose and parse packed binary data. In a sense, this is another data-conversion tool that interprets strings in files as binary data.

To create a packed binary data file, for example, open it in 'wb' (write binary) mode, and pass struct a format string and some Python objects. The format string used here means pack as a 4-byte integer, a 4-character string, and a 2-byte integer, all in big-endian form (other format codes handle padding bytes, floating-point numbers, and more):

>>> F = open('data.bin', 'wb')                     # Open binary output file
>>> import struct
>>> data = struct.pack('>i4sh', 7, 'spam', 8)      # Make packed binary data
>>> data
b'\x00\x00\x00\x07spam\x00\x08'
>>> F.write(data)                                  # Write byte string
>>> F.close()

Python creates a binary bytes data string, which we write out to the file normally—this one consists mostly of nonprintable characters printed in hexadecimal escapes, and is the same binary file we met earlier. To parse the values out to normal Python objects, we simply read the string back and unpack it using the same format string. Python extracts the values into normal Python objects—integers and a string:

>>> F = open('data.bin', 'rb')
>>> data = F.read()                                # Get packed binary data
>>> data
b'\x00\x00\x00\x07spam\x00\x08'
>>> values = struct.unpack('>i4sh', data)          # Convert to Python objects
>>> values
(7, b'spam', 8)

Binary data files are advanced and somewhat low-level tools that we won’t cover in more detail here; for more help, see Chapter 36, consult the Python library manual, or import struct and pass it to the help function interactively. Also note that the binary file-processing modes 'wb' and 'rb' can be used to process a simpler binary file such as an image or audio file as a whole without having to unpack its contents.

File context managers

You’ll also want to watch for Chapter 33’s discussion of the file’s context manager support, new in Python 3.0 and 2.6. Though more a feature of exception processing than files themselves, it allows us to wrap file-processing code in a logic layer that ensures that the file will be closed automatically on exit, instead of relying on the auto-close on garbage collection:

with open(r'C:\misc\data.txt') as myfile:        # See Chapter 33 for details
    for line in myfile:
        ...use line here...

The try/finally statement we’ll look at in Chapter 33 can provide similar functionality, but at some cost in extra code—three extra lines, to be precise (though we can often avoid both options and let Python close files for us automatically):

myfile = open(r'C:\misc\data.txt')
try:
    for line in myfile:
        ...use line here...
finally:
    myfile.close()

Since both these options require more information than we have yet obtained, we’ll postpone details until later in this book.

Other File Tools

There are additional, more advanced file methods shown in Table 9-2, and even more that are not in the table. For instance, as mentioned earlier, seek resets your current position in a file (the next read or write happens at that position), flush forces buffered output to be written out to disk (by default, files are always buffered), and so on.

The Python standard library manual and the reference books described in the Preface provide complete lists of file methods; for a quick look, run a dir or help call interactively, passing in an open file object (in Python 2.6 but not 3.0, you can pass in the name file instead). For more file-processing examples, watch for the sidebar Why You Will Care: File Scanners. It sketches common file-scanning loop code patterns with statements we have not covered enough yet to use here.

Also, note that although the open function and the file objects it returns are your main interface to external files in a Python script, there are additional file-like tools in the Python toolset. Also available, to name a few, are:

Standard streams

Preopened file objects in the sys module, such as sys.stdout (see Print Operations)

Descriptor files in the os module

Integer file handles that support lower-level tools such as file locking

Sockets, pipes, and FIFOs

File-like objects used to synchronize processes or communicate over networks

Access-by-key files known as “shelves”

Used to store unaltered Python objects directly, by key (used in Chapter 27)

Shell command streams

Tools such as os.popen and subprocess.Popen that support spawning shell commands and reading and writing to their standard streams

The third-party open source domain offers even more file-like tools, including support for communicating with serial ports in the PySerial extension and interactive programs in the pexpect system. See more advanced Python texts and the Web at large for additional information on file-like tools.

Note

Version skew note: In Python 2.5 and earlier, the built-in name open is essentially a synonym for the name file, and files may technically be opened by calling either open or file (though open is generally preferred for opening). In Python 3.0, the name file is no longer available, because of its redundancy with open.

Python 2.6 users may also use the name file as the file object type, in order to customize files with object-oriented programming (described later in this book). In Python 3.0, files have changed radically. The classes used to implement file objects live in the standard library module io. See this module’s documentation or code for the classes it makes available for customization, and run a type(F) call on open files F for hints.

Type Categories Revisited

Now that we’ve seen all of Python’s core built-in types in action, let’s wrap up our object types tour by reviewing some of the properties they share. Table 9-3 classifies all the major types we’ve seen so far according to the type categories introduced earlier. Here are some points to remember:

Objects share operations according to their category; for instance, strings, lists, and tuples all share sequence operations such as concatenation, length, and indexing.

Only mutable objects (lists, dictionaries, and sets) may be changed in-place; you cannot change numbers, strings, or tuples in-place.

Files export only methods, so mutability doesn’t really apply to them—their state may be changed when they are processed, but this isn’t quite the same as Python core type mutability constraints.

“Numbers” in Table 9-3 includes all number types: integer (and the distinct long integer in 2.6), floating-point, complex, decimal, and fraction.

“Strings” in Table 9-3 includes str, as well as bytes in 3.0 and unicode in 2.6; the bytearray string type in 3.0 is mutable.

Sets are something like the keys of a valueless dictionary, but they don’t map to values and are not ordered, so sets are neither a mapping nor a sequence type; frozenset is an immutable variant of set.

In addition to type category operations, as of Python 2.6 and 3.0 all the types in Table 9-3 have callable methods, which are generally specific to their type.

Table 9-3. Object classifications

Object type

|

Category

|

Mutable?

Numbers (all)

|

Numeric

|

No

Strings

|

Sequence

|

No

Lists

|

Sequence

|

Yes

Dictionaries

|

Mapping

|

Yes

Tuples

|

Sequence

|

No

Files

|

Extension

|

N/A

Sets

|

Set

|

Yes

frozenset

|

Set

|

No

bytearray (3.0)

|

Sequence

|

Yes

Why You Will Care: Operator Overloading

In Part VI of this book, we’ll see that objects we implement with classes can pick and choose from these categories arbitrarily. For instance, if we want to provide a new kind of specialized sequence object that is consistent with built-in sequences, we can code a class that overloads things like indexing and concatenation:

class MySequence:
     def __getitem__(self, index):
         # Called on self[index], others
     def __add__(self, other):
         # Called on self + other

and so on. We can also make the new object mutable or not by selectively implementing methods called for in-place change operations (e.g., __setitem__ is called on self[index]=value assignments). Although it’s beyond this book’s scope, it’s also possible to implement new objects in an external language like C as C extension types. For these, we fill in C function pointer slots to choose between number, sequence, and mapping operation sets.

Comparisons, Equality, and Truth

All Python objects also respond to comparisons: tests for equality, relative magnitude, and so on. Python comparisons always inspect all parts of compound objects until a result can be determined. In fact, when nested objects are present, Python automatically traverses data structures to apply comparisons recursively from left to right, and as deeply as needed. The first difference found along the way determines the comparison result.

For instance, a comparison of list objects compares all their components automatically:

>>> L1 = [1, ('a', 3)]           # Same value, unique objects
>>> L2 = [1, ('a', 3)]
>>> L1 == L2, L1 is L2           # Equivalent? Same object?
(True, False)

Here, L1 and L2 are assigned lists that are equivalent but distinct objects. Because of the nature of Python references (studied in Chapter 6), there are two ways to test for equality:

The == operator tests value equivalence. Python performs an equivalence test, comparing all nested objects recursively.

The is operator tests object identity. Python tests whether the two are really the same object (i.e., live at the same address in memory).

In the preceding example, L1 and L2 pass the == test (they have equivalent values because all their components are equivalent) but fail the is check (they reference two different objects, and hence two different pieces of memory). Notice what happens for short strings, though:

>>> S1 = 'spam'
>>> S2 = 'spam'
>>> S1 == S2, S1 is S2
(True, True)

Here, we should again have two distinct objects that happen to have the same value: == should be true, and is should be false. But because Python internally caches and reuses some strings as an optimization, there really is just a single string 'spam' in memory, shared by S1 and S2; hence, the is identity test reports a true result. To trigger the normal behavior, we need to use longer strings:

>>> S1 = 'a longer string'
>>> S2 = 'a longer string'
>>> S1 == S2, S1 is S2
(True, False)

Of course, because strings are immutable, the object caching mechanism is irrelevant to your code—strings can’t be changed in-place, regardless of how many variables refer to them. If identity tests seem confusing, see Chapter 6 for a refresher on object reference concepts.

As a rule of thumb, the == operator is what you will want to use for almost all equality checks; is is reserved for highly specialized roles. We’ll see cases where these operators are put to use later in the book.

Relative magnitude comparisons are also applied recursively to nested data structures:

>>> L1 = [1, ('a', 3)]
>>> L2 = [1, ('a', 2)]
>>> L1 < L2, L1 == L2, L1 > L2        # Less, equal, greater: tuple of results
(False, False, True)

Here, L1 is greater than L2 because the nested 3 is greater than 2. The result of the last line is really a tuple of three objects—the results of the three expressions typed (an example of a tuple without its enclosing parentheses).

In general, Python compares types as follows:

Numbers are compared by relative magnitude.

Strings are compared lexicographically, character by character ("abc" < "ac").

Lists and tuples are compared by comparing each component from left to right.

Dictionaries compare as equal if their sorted (key, value) lists are equal. Relative magnitude comparisons are not supported for dictionaries in Python 3.0, but they work in 2.6 and earlier as though comparing sorted (key, value) lists.

Nonnumeric mixed-type comparisons (e.g., 1 < 'spam') are errors in Python 3.0. They are allowed in Python 2.6, but use a fixed but arbitrary ordering rule. By proxy, this also applies to sorts, which use comparisons internally: nonnumeric mixed-type collections cannot be sorted in 3.0.

In general, comparisons of structured objects proceed as though you had written the objects as literals and compared all their parts one at a time from left to right. In later chapters, we’ll see other object types that can change the way they get compared.

Python 3.0 Dictionary Comparisons

The second to last point in the preceding section merits illustration. In Python 2.6 and earlier, dictionaries support magnitude comparisons, as though you were comparing sorted key/value lists:

C:\misc> c:\python26\python
>>> D1 = {'a':1, 'b':2}
>>> D2 = {'a':1, 'b':3}
>>> D1 == D2
False
>>> D1 < D2
True

In Python 3.0, magnitude comparisons for dictionaries are removed because they incur too much overhead when equality is desired (equality uses an optimized scheme in 3.0 that doesn’t literally compare sorted key/value lists). The alternative in 3.0 is to either write loops to compare values by key or compare the sorted key/value lists manually—the items dictionary methods and sorted built-in suffice:

C:\misc> c:\python30\python
>>> D1 = {'a':1, 'b':2}
>>> D2 = {'a':1, 'b':3}
>>> D1 == D2
False
>>> D1 < D2
TypeError: unorderable types: dict() < dict()

>>> list(D1.items())
[('a', 1), ('b', 2)]
>>> sorted(D1.items())
[('a', 1), ('b', 2)]

>>> sorted(D1.items()) < sorted(D2.items())
True
>>> sorted(D1.items()) > sorted(D2.items())
False

In practice, most programs requiring this behavior will develop more efficient ways to compare data in dictionaries than either this workaround or the original behavior in Python 2.6.

The Meaning of True and False in Python

Notice that the test results returned in the last two examples represent true and false values. They print as the words True and False, but now that we’re using logical tests like these in earnest, I should be a bit more formal about what these names really mean.

In Python, as in most programming languages, an integer 0 represents false, and an integer 1 represents true. In addition, though, Python recognizes any empty data structure as false and any nonempty data structure as true. More generally, the notions of true and false are intrinsic properties of every object in Python—each object is either true or false, as follows:

Numbers are true if nonzero.

Other objects are true if nonempty.

Table 9-4 gives examples of true and false objects in Python.

Table 9-4. Example object truth values

Object

|

Value

"spam"

|

True

""

|

False

[]

|

False

{}

|

False

1

|

True

0.0

|

False

None

|

False

As one application, because objects are true or false themselves, it’s common to see Python programmers code tests like if X:, which, assuming X is a string, is the same as if X != '':. In other words, you can test the object itself, instead of comparing it to an empty object. (More on if statements in Part III.)

The None object

As shown in the last item in Table 9-4, Python also provides a special object called None, which is always considered to be false. None was introduced in Chapter 4; it is the only value of a special data type in Python and typically serves as an empty placeholder (much like a NULL pointer in C).

For example, recall that for lists you cannot assign to an offset unless that offset already exists (the list does not magically grow if you make an out-of-bounds assignment). To preallocate a 100-item list such that you can add to any of the 100 offsets, you can fill it with None objects:

>>> L = [None] * 100
>>>
>>> L
[None, None, None, None, None, None, None, ... ]

This doesn’t limit the size of the list (it can still grow and shrink later), but simply presets an initial size to allow for future index assignments. You could initialize a list with zeros the same way, of course, but best practice dictates using None if the list’s contents are not yet known.

Keep in mind that None does not mean “undefined.” That is, None is something, not nothing (despite its name!)—it is a real object and piece of memory, given a built-in name by Python. Watch for other uses of this special object later in the book; it is also the default return value of functions, as we’ll see in Part IV.

The bool type

Also keep in mind that the Python Boolean type bool, introduced in Chapter 5, simply augments the notions of true and false in Python. As we learned in Chapter 5, the built-in words True and False are just customized versions of the integers 1 and 0—it’s as if these two words have been preassigned to 1 and 0 everywhere in Python. Because of the way this new type is implemented, this is really just a minor extension to the notions of true and false already described, designed to make truth values more explicit:

When used explicitly in truth test code, the words True and False are equivalent to 1 and 0, but they make the programmer’s intent clearer.

Results of Boolean tests run interactively print as the words True and False, instead of as 1 and 0, to make the type of result clearer.

You are not required to use only Boolean types in logical statements such as if; all objects are still inherently true or false, and all the Boolean concepts mentioned in this chapter still work as described if you use other types. Python also provides a bool built-in function that can be used to test the Boolean value of an object (i.e., whether it is True—that is, nonzero or nonempty):

>>> bool(1)
True
>>> bool('spam')
True
>>> bool({})
False

In practice, though, you’ll rarely notice the Boolean type produced by logic tests, because Boolean results are used automatically by if statements and other selection tools. We’ll explore Booleans further when we study logical statements in Chapter 12.

Built-in Type Gotchas

That’s the end of our look at core data types. We’ll wrap up this part of the book with a discussion of common problems that seem to bite new users (and the occasional expert), along with their solutions. Some of this is a review of ideas we’ve already covered, but these issues are important enough to warn about again here.

Assignment Creates References, Not Copies

Because this is such a central concept, I’ll mention it again: you need to understand what’s going on with shared references in your program. For instance, in the following example, the list object assigned to the name L is referenced from L and from inside the list assigned to the name M. Changing L in-place changes what M references, too:

>>> L = [1, 2, 3]
>>> M = ['X', L, 'Y']           # Embed a reference to L
>>> M
['X', [1, 2, 3], 'Y']

>>> L[1] = 0                    # Changes M too
>>> M
['X', [1, 0, 3], 'Y']

This effect usually becomes important only in larger programs, and shared references are often exactly what you want. If they’re not, you can avoid sharing objects by copying them explicitly. For lists, you can always make a top-level copy by using an empty-limits slice:

>>> L = [1, 2, 3]
>>> M = ['X', L[:], 'Y']        # Embed a copy of L
>>> L[1] = 0                    # Changes only L, not M
>>> L
[1, 0, 3]
>>> M
['X', [1, 2, 3], 'Y']

Remember, slice limits default to 0 and the length of the sequence being sliced; if both are omitted, the slice extracts every item in the sequence and so makes a top-level copy (a new, unshared object).

Repetition Adds One Level Deep

Repeating a sequence is like adding it to itself a number of times. However, when mutable sequences are nested, the effect might not always be what you expect. For instance, in the following example X is assigned to L repeated four times, whereas Y is assigned to a list containing L repeated four times:

>>> L = [4, 5, 6]
>>> X = L * 4                   # Like [4, 5, 6] + [4, 5, 6] + ...
>>> Y = [L] * 4                 # [L] + [L] + ... = [L, L,...]

>>> X
[4, 5, 6, 4, 5, 6, 4, 5, 6, 4, 5, 6]
>>> Y
[[4, 5, 6], [4, 5, 6], [4, 5, 6], [4, 5, 6]]

Because L was nested in the second repetition, Y winds up embedding references back to the original list assigned to L, and so is open to the same sorts of side effects noted in the last section:

>>> L[1] = 0                    # Impacts Y but not X
>>> X
[4, 5, 6, 4, 5, 6, 4, 5, 6, 4, 5, 6]
>>> Y
[[4, 0, 6], [4, 0, 6], [4, 0, 6], [4, 0, 6]]

The same solutions to this problem apply here as in the previous section, as this is really just another way to create the shared mutable object reference case. If you remember that repetition, concatenation, and slicing copy only the top level of their operand objects, these sorts of cases make much more sense.

Beware of Cyclic Data Structures

We actually encountered this concept in a prior exercise: if a collection object contains a reference to itself, it’s called a cyclic object. Python prints a [...] whenever it detects a cycle in the object, rather than getting stuck in an infinite loop:

>>> L = ['grail']                # Append reference to same object
>>> L.append(L)                  # Generates cycle in object: [...]
>>> L
['grail', [...]]

Besides understanding that the three dots in square brackets represent a cycle in the object, this case is worth knowing about because it can lead to gotchas—cyclic structures may cause code of your own to fall into unexpected loops if you don’t anticipate them. For instance, some programs keep a list or dictionary of already visited items and check it to determine whether they’re in a cycle. See the solutions to the in Appendix B for more on this problem, and check out the reloadall.py program in Chapter 24 for a solution.

Don’t use cyclic references unless you really need to. There are good reasons to create cycles, but unless you have code that knows how to handle them, you probably won’t want to make your objects reference themselves very often in practice.

Immutable Types Can’t Be Changed In-Place

You can’t change an immutable object in-place. Instead, you construct a new object with slicing, concatenation, and so on, and assign it back to the original reference, if needed:

T = (1, 2, 3)

T[2] = 4              # Error!

T = T[:2] + (4,)      # OK: (1, 2, 4)

That might seem like extra coding work, but the upside is that the previous gotchas can’t happen when you’re using immutable objects such as tuples and strings; because they can’t be changed in-place, they are not open to the sorts of side effects that lists are.

Chapter Summary

This chapter explored the last two major core object types—the tuple and the file. We learned that tuples support all the usual sequence operations, have just a few methods, and do not allow any in-place changes because they are immutable. We also learned that files are returned by the built-in open function and provide methods for reading and writing data. We explored how to translate Python objects to and from strings for storing in files, and we looked at the pickle and struct modules for advanced roles (object serialization and binary data). Finally, we wrapped up by reviewing some properties common to all object types (e.g., shared references) and went through a list of common mistakes (“gotchas”) in the object type domain.

In the next part, we’ll shift gears, turning to the topic of statement syntax in Python—we’ll explore all of Python’s basic procedural statements in the chapters that follow. The next chapter kicks off that part of the book with an introduction to Python’s general syntax model, which is applicable to all statement types. Before moving on, though, take the chapter quiz, and then work through the end-of-part lab exercises to review type concepts. Statements largely just create and process objects, so make sure you’ve mastered this domain by working through all the exercises before reading on.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

The built-in len function returns the length (number of contained items) for any container object in Python, including tuples. It is a built-in function instead of a type method because it applies to many different types of objects. In general, built-in functions and expressions may span many object types; methods are specific to a single object type, though some may be available on more than one type (index, for example, works on lists and tuples).

Because they are immutable, you can’t really change tuples in-place, but you can generate a new tuple with the desired value. Given T = (4, 5, 6), you can change the first item by making a new tuple from its parts by slicing and concatenating: T = (1,) + T[1:]. (Recall that single-item tuples require a trailing comma.) You could also convert the tuple to a list, change it in-place, and convert it back to a tuple, but this is more expensive and is rarely required in practice—simply use a list if you know that the object will require in-place changes.

The default for the processing mode argument in a file open call is 'r', for reading text input. For input text files, simply pass in the external file’s name.

The pickle module can be used to store Python objects in a file without explicitly converting them to strings. The struct module is related, but it assumes the data is to be in packed binary format in the file.

Import the copy module, and call copy.deepcopy(X) if you need to copy all parts of a nested structure X. This is also rarely seen in practice; references are usually the desired behavior, and shallow copies (e.g., aList[:], aDict.copy()) usually suffice for most copies.

An object is considered true if it is either a nonzero number or a nonempty collection object. The built-in words True and False are essentially predefined to have the same meanings as integer 1 and 0, respectively.

Acceptable answers include “To learn Python,” “To move on to the next part of the book,” or “To seek the Holy Grail.”

Test Your Knowledge: Part II Exercises

This session asks you to get your feet wet with built-in object fundamentals. As before, a few new ideas may pop up along the way, so be sure to flip to the answers in Appendix B when you’re done (or when you’re not, if necessary). If you have limited time, I suggest starting with exercises 10 and 11 (the most practical of the bunch), and then working from first to last as time allows. This is all fundamental material, though, so try to do as many of these as you can.

The basics. Experiment interactively with the common type operations found in the various operation tables in this part of the book. To get started, bring up the Python interactive interpreter, type each of the following expressions, and try to explain what’s happening in each case. Note that the semicolon in some of these is being used as a statement separator, to squeeze multiple statements onto a single line: for example, X=1;X assigns and then prints a variable (more on statement syntax in the next part of the book). Also remember that a comma between expressions usually builds a tuple, even if there are no enclosing parentheses: X,Y,Z is a three-item tuple, which Python prints back to you in parentheses.

2 ** 16
2 / 5, 2 / 5.0

"spam" + "eggs"
S = "ham"
"eggs " + S
S * 5
S[:0]
"green %s and %s" % ("eggs", S)
'green {0} and {1}'.format('eggs', S)

('x',)[0]
('x', 'y')[1]

L = [1,2,3] + [4,5,6]
L, L[:], L[:0], L[−2], L[−2:]
([1,2,3] + [4,5,6])[2:4]
[L[2], L[3]]
L.reverse(); L
L.sort(); L
L.index(4)

{'a':1, 'b':2}['b']
D = {'x':1, 'y':2, 'z':3}
D['w'] = 0
D['x'] + D['w']
D[(1,2,3)] = 4
list(D.keys()), list(D.values()), (1,2,3) in D

[[]], ["",[],(),{},None]

Indexing and slicing. At the interactive prompt, define a list named L that contains four strings or numbers (e.g., L=[0,1,2,3]). Then, experiment with some boundary cases; you may not ever see these cases in real programs, but they are intended to make you think about the underlying model, and some may be useful in less artificial forms:

What happens when you try to index out of bounds (e.g., L[4])?

What about slicing out of bounds (e.g., L[−1000:100])?

Finally, how does Python handle it if you try to extract a sequence in reverse, with the lower bound greater than the higher bound (e.g., L[3:1])? Hint: try assigning to this slice (L[3:1]=['?']), and see where the value is put. Do you think this may be the same phenomenon you saw when slicing out of bounds?

Indexing, slicing, and del. Define another list L with four items, and assign an empty list to one of its offsets (e.g., L[2]=[]). What happens? Then, assign an empty list to a slice (L[2:3]=[]). What happens now? Recall that slice assignment deletes the slice and inserts the new value where it used to be.

The del statement deletes offsets, keys, attributes, and names. Use it on your list to delete an item (e.g., del L[0]). What happens if you delete an entire slice (del L[1:])? What happens when you assign a nonsequence to a slice (L[1:2]=1)?

Tuple assignment. Type the following lines:

>>> X = 'spam'
>>> Y = 'eggs'
>>> X, Y = Y, X

What do you think is happening to X and Y when you type this sequence?

Dictionary keys. Consider the following code fragments:

>>> D = {}
>>> D[1] = 'a'
>>> D[2] = 'b'

You’ve learned that dictionaries aren’t accessed by offsets, so what’s going on here? Does the following shed any light on the subject? (Hint: strings, integers, and tuples share which type category?)

>>> D[(1, 2, 3)] = 'c'
>>> D
{1: 'a', 2: 'b', (1, 2, 3): 'c'}

Dictionary indexing. Create a dictionary named D with three entries, for keys 'a', 'b', and 'c'. What happens if you try to index a nonexistent key (D['d'])? What does Python do if you try to assign to a nonexistent key 'd' (e.g., D['d']='spam')? How does this compare to out-of-bounds assignments and references for lists? Does this sound like the rule for variable names?

Generic operations. Run interactive tests to answer the following questions:

What happens when you try to use the + operator on different/mixed types (e.g., string + list, list + tuple)?

Does + work when one of the operands is a dictionary?

Does the append method work for both lists and strings? How about using the keys method on lists? (Hint: what does append assume about its subject object?)

Finally, what type of object do you get back when you slice or concatenate two lists or two strings?

String indexing. Define a string S of four characters: S = "spam". Then type the following expression: S[0][0][0][0][0]. Any clue as to what’s happening this time? (Hint: recall that a string is a collection of characters, but Python characters are one-character strings.) Does this indexing expression still work if you apply it to a list such as ['s', 'p', 'a', 'm']? Why?

Immutable types. Define a string S of four characters again: S = "spam". Write an assignment that changes the string to "slam", using only slicing and concatenation. Could you perform the same operation using just indexing and concatenation? How about index assignment?

Nesting. Write a data structure that represents your personal information: name (first, middle, last), age, job, address, email address, and phone number. You may build the data structure with any combination of built-in object types you like (lists, tuples, dictionaries, strings, numbers). Then, access the individual components of your data structures by indexing. Do some structures make more sense than others for this object?

Files. Write a script that creates a new output file called myfile.txt and writes the string "Hello file world!" into it. Then write another script that opens myfile.txt and reads and prints its contents. Run your two scripts from the system command line. Does the new file show up in the directory where you ran your scripts? What if you add a different directory path to the filename passed to open? Note: file write methods do not add newline characters to your strings; add an explicit \n at the end of the string if you want to fully terminate the line in the file.

A Tale of Two ifs

Before we delve into the details of any of the concrete statements in Table 10-1, I want to begin our look at Python statement syntax by showing you what you are not going to type in Python code so you can compare and contrast it with other syntax models you might have seen in the past.

Consider the following if statement, coded in a C-like language:

if (x > y) {
    x = 1;
    y = 2;
}

This might be a statement in C, C++, Java, JavaScript, or Perl. Now, look at the equivalent statement in the Python language:

if x > y:
    x = 1
    y = 2

The first thing that may pop out at you is that the equivalent Python statement is less, well, cluttered—that is, there are fewer syntactic components. This is by design; as a scripting language, one of Python’s goals is to make programmers’ lives easier by requiring less typing.

More specifically, when you compare the two syntax models, you’ll notice that Python adds one new thing to the mix, and that three items that are present in the C-like language are not present in Python code.

What Python Adds

The one new syntax component in Python is the colon character (:). All Python compound statements (i.e., statements that have statements nested inside them) follow the same general pattern of a header line terminated in a colon, followed by a nested block of code usually indented underneath the header line, like this:

Header line:
    Nested statement block

The colon is required, and omitting it is probably the most common coding mistake among new Python programmers—it’s certainly one I’ve witnessed thousands of times in Python training classes. In fact, if you are new to Python, you’ll almost certainly forget the colon character very soon. Most Python-friendly editors make this mistake easy to spot, and including it eventually becomes an unconscious habit (so much so that you may start typing colons in your C++ code, too, generating many entertaining error messages from your C++ compiler!).

What Python Removes

Although Python requires the extra colon character, there are three things programmers in C-like languages must include that you don’t generally have to in Python.

Parentheses are optional

The first of these is the set of parentheses around the tests at the top of the statement:

if (x < y)

The parentheses here are required by the syntax of many C-like languages. In Python, though, they are not—we simply omit the parentheses, and the statement works the same way:

if x < y

Technically speaking, because every expression can be enclosed in parentheses, including them will not hurt in this Python code, and they are not treated as an error if present. But don’t do that: you’ll be wearing out your keyboard needlessly, and broadcasting to the world that you’re an ex-C programmer still learning Python (I was once, too). The Python way is to simply omit the parentheses in these kinds of statements altogether.

End of line is end of statement

The second and more significant syntax component you won’t find in Python code is the semicolon. You don’t need to terminate statements with semicolons in Python the way you do in C-like languages:

x = 1;

In Python, the general rule is that the end of a line automatically terminates the statement that appears on that line. In other words, you can leave off the semicolons, and it works the same way:

x = 1

There are some ways to work around this rule, as you’ll see in a moment. But, in general, you write one statement per line for the vast majority of Python code, and no semicolon is required.

Here, too, if you are pining for your C programming days (if such a state is possible...) you can continue to use semicolons at the end of each statement—the language lets you get away with them if they are present. But don’t do that either (really!); again, doing so tells the world that you’re still a C programmer who hasn’t quite made the switch to Python coding. The Pythonic style is to leave off the semicolons altogether.

End of indentation is end of block

The third and final syntax component that Python removes, and the one that may seem the most unusual to soon-to-be-ex-C programmers (until they’ve used it for 10 minutes and realize it’s actually a feature), is that you do not type anything explicit in your code to syntactically mark the beginning and end of a nested block of code. You don’t need to include begin/end, then/endif, or braces around the nested block, as you do in C-like languages:

if (x > y) {
    x = 1;
    y = 2;
}

Instead, in Python, we consistently indent all the statements in a given single nested block the same distance to the right, and Python uses the statements’ physical indentation to determine where the block starts and stops:

if x > y:
    x = 1
    y = 2

By indentation, I mean the blank whitespace all the way to the left of the two nested statements here. Python doesn’t care how you indent (you may use either spaces or tabs), or how much you indent (you may use any number of spaces or tabs). In fact, the indentation of one nested block can be totally different from that of another. The syntax rule is only that for a given single nested block, all of its statements must be indented the same distance to the right. If this is not the case, you will get a syntax error, and your code will not run until you repair its indentation to be consistent.

Why Indentation Syntax?

The indentation rule may seem unusual at first glance to programmers accustomed to C-like languages, but it is a deliberate feature of Python, and it’s one of the main ways that Python almost forces programmers to produce uniform, regular, and readable code. It essentially means that you must line up your code vertically, in columns, according to its logical structure. The net effect is to make your code more consistent and readable (unlike much of the code written in C-like languages).

To put that more strongly, aligning your code according to its logical structure is a major part of making it readable, and thus reusable and maintainable, by yourself and others. In fact, even if you never use Python after reading this book, you should get into the habit of aligning your code for readability in any block-structured language. Python forces the issue by making this a part of its syntax, but it’s an important thing to do in any programming language, and it has a huge impact on the usefulness of your code.

Your experience may vary, but when I was still doing development on a full-time basis, I was mostly paid to work on large old C++ programs that had been worked on by many programmers over the years. Almost invariably, each programmer had his or her own style for indenting code. For example, I’d often be asked to change a while loop coded in the C++ language that began like this:

while (x > 0) {

Before we even get into indentation, there are three or four ways that programmers can arrange these braces in a C-like language, and organizations often have political debates and write standards manuals to address the options (which seems more than a little off-topic for the problem to be solved by programming). Ignoring that, here’s the scenario I often encountered in C++ code. The first person who worked on the code indented the loop four spaces:

while (x > 0) {
    --------;
    --------;

That person eventually moved on to management, only to be replaced by someone who liked to indent further to the right:

while (x > 0) {
    --------;
    --------;
           --------;
           --------;

That person later moved on to other opportunities, and someone else picked up the code who liked to indent less:

while (x > 0) {
    --------;
    --------;
           --------;
           --------;
--------;
--------;
}

And so on. Eventually, the block is terminated by a closing brace (}), which of course makes this “block-structured code” (he says, sarcastically). In any block-structured language, Python or otherwise, if nested blocks are not indented consistently, they become very difficult for the reader to interpret, change, or reuse, because the code no longer visually reflects its logical meaning. Readability matters, and indentation is a major component of readability.

Here is another example that may have burned you in the past if you’ve done much programming in a C-like language. Consider the following statement in C:

if (x)
     if (y)
          statement1;
else
     statement2;

Which if does the else here go with? Surprisingly, the else is paired with the nested if statement (if (y)), even though it looks visually as though it is associated with the outer if (x). This is a classic pitfall in the C language, and it can lead to the reader completely misinterpreting the code and changing it incorrectly in ways that might not be uncovered until the Mars rover crashes into a giant rock!

This cannot happen in Python—because indentation is significant, the way the code looks is the way it will work. Consider an equivalent Python statement:

if x:
     if y:
          statement1
else:
     statement2

In this example, the if that the else lines up with vertically is the one it is associated with logically (the outer if x). In a sense, Python is a WYSIWYG language—what you see is what you get because the way code looks is the way it runs, regardless of who coded it.

If this still isn’t enough to underscore the benefits of Python’s syntax, here’s another anecdote. Early in my career, I worked at a successful company that developed systems software in the C language, where consistent indentation is not required. Even so, when we checked our code into source control at the end of the day, this company ran an automated script that analyzed the indentation used in the code. If the script noticed that we’d indented our code inconsistently, we received an automated email about it the next morning—and so did our managers!

The point is that even when a language doesn’t require it, good programmers know that consistent use of indentation has a huge impact on code readability and quality. The fact that Python promotes this to the level of syntax is seen by most as a feature of the language.

Also keep in mind that nearly every programmer-friendly text editor has built-in support for Python’s syntax model. In the IDLE Python GUI, for example, lines of code are automatically indented when you are typing a nested block; pressing the Backspace key backs up one level of indentation, and you can customize how far to the right IDLE indents statements in a nested block. There is no universal standard on this: four spaces or one tab per level is common, but it’s up to you to decide how and how much you wish to indent. Indent further to the right for further nested blocks, and less to close the prior block.

As a rule of thumb, you probably shouldn’t mix tabs and spaces in the same block in Python, unless you do so consistently; use tabs or spaces in a given block, but not both (in fact, Python 3.0 now issues an error for inconsistent use of tabs and spaces, as we’ll see in Chapter 12). But you probably shouldn’t mix tabs or spaces in indentation in any structured language—such code can cause major readability issues if the next programmer has his or her editor set to display tabs differently than yours. C-like languages might let coders get away with this, but they shouldn’t: the result can be a mangled mess.

I can’t stress enough that regardless of which language you code in, you should be indenting consistently for readability. In fact, if you weren’t taught to do this earlier in your career, your teachers did you a disservice. Most programmers—especially those who must read others’ code—consider it a major asset that Python elevates this to the level of syntax. Moreover, generating tabs instead of braces is no more difficult in practice for tools that must output Python code. In general, if you do what you should be doing in a C-like language anyhow, but get rid of the braces, your code will satisfy Python’s syntax rules.

A Few Special Cases

As mentioned previously, in Python’s syntax model:

The end of a line terminates the statement on that line (without semicolons).

Nested statements are blocked and associated by their physical indentation (without braces).

Those rules cover almost all Python code you’ll write or see in practice. However, Python also provides some special-purpose rules that allow customization of both statements and nested statement blocks.

Statement rule special cases

Although statements normally appear one per line, it is possible to squeeze more than one statement onto a single line in Python by separating them with semicolons:

a = 1; b = 2; print(a + b)               # Three statements on one line

This is the only place in Python where semicolons are required: as statement separators. This only works, though, if the statements thus combined are not themselves compound statements. In other words, you can chain together only simple statements, like assignments, prints, and function calls. Compound statements must still appear on lines of their own (otherwise, you could squeeze an entire program onto one line, which probably would not make you very popular among your coworkers!).

The other special rule for statements is essentially the inverse: you can make a single statement span across multiple lines. To make this work, you simply have to enclose part of your statement in a bracketed pair—parentheses (()), square brackets ([]), or curly braces ({}). Any code enclosed in these constructs can cross multiple lines: your statement doesn’t end until Python reaches the line containing the closing part of the pair. For instance, to continue a list literal:

mlist = [111,
         222,
         333]

Because the code is enclosed in a square brackets pair, Python simply drops down to the next line until it encounters the closing bracket. The curly braces surrounding dictionaries (as well as set literals and dictionary and set comprehensions in 3.0) allow them to span lines this way too, and parentheses handle tuples, function calls, and expressions. The indentation of the continuation lines does not matter, though common sense dictates that the lines should be aligned somehow for readability.

Parentheses are the catchall device—because any expression can be wrapped up in them, simply inserting a left parenthesis allows you to drop down to the next line and continue your statement:

X = (A + B +
     C + D)

This technique works with compound statements, too, by the way. Anywhere you need to code a large expression, simply wrap it in parentheses to continue it on the next line:

if (A == 1 and
    B == 2 and
    C == 3):
        print('spam' * 3)

An older rule also allows for continuation lines when the prior line ends in a backslash:

X = A + B + \                # An error-prone alternative
      C + D

This alternative technique is dated, though, and is frowned on today because it’s difficult to notice and maintain the backslashes, and it’s fairly brittle—there can be no spaces after the backslash, and omitting it can have unexpected effects if the next line is mistaken to be a new statement. It’s also another throwback to the C language, where it is commonly used in “#define” macros; again, when in Pythonland, do as Pythonistas do, not as C programmers do.

Block rule special case

As mentioned previously, statements in a nested block of code are normally associated by being indented the same amount to the right. As one special case here, the body of a compound statement can instead appear on the same line as the header in Python, after the colon:

if x > y: print(x)

This allows us to code single-line if statements, single-line loops, and so on. Here again, though, this will work only if the body of the compound statement itself does not contain any compound statements. That is, only simple statements—assignments, prints, function calls, and the like—are allowed after the colon. Larger statements must still appear on lines by themselves. Extra parts of compound statements (such as the else part of an if, which we’ll meet later) must also be on separate lines of their own. The body can consist of multiple simple statements separated by semicolons, but this tends to be frowned upon.

In general, even though it’s not always required, if you keep all your statements on individual lines and always indent your nested blocks, your code will be easier to read and change in the future. Moreover, some code profiling and coverage tools may not be able to distinguish between multiple statements squeezed onto a single line or the header and body of a one-line compound statement. It is almost always to your advantage to keep things simple in Python.

To see a prime and common exception to one of these rules in action, however (the use of a single-line if statement to break out of a loop), let’s move on to the next section and write some real code.

A Quick Example: Interactive Loops

We’ll see all these syntax rules in action when we tour Python’s specific compound statements in the next few chapters, but they work the same everywhere in the Python language. To get started, let’s work through a brief, realistic example that demonstrates the way that statement syntax and statement nesting come together in practice, and introduces a few statements along the way.

A Simple Interactive Loop

Suppose you’re asked to write a Python program that interacts with a user in a console window. Maybe you’re accepting inputs to send to a database, or reading numbers to be used in a calculation. Regardless of the purpose, you need to code a loop that reads one or more inputs from a user typing on a keyboard, and prints back a result for each. In other words, you need to write a classic read/evaluate/print loop program.

In Python, typical boilerplate code for such an interactive loop might look like this:

while True:
    reply = input('Enter text:')
    if reply == 'stop': break
    print(reply.upper())

This code makes use of a few new ideas:

The code leverages the Python while loop, Python’s most general looping statement. We’ll study the while statement in more detail later, but in short, it consists of the word while, followed by an expression that is interpreted as a true or false result, followed by a nested block of code that is repeated while the test at the top is true (the word True here is considered always true).

The input built-in function we met earlier in the book is used here for general console input—it prints its optional argument string as a prompt and returns the user’s typed reply as a string.

A single-line if statement that makes use of the special rule for nested blocks also appears here: the body of the if appears on the header line after the colon instead of being indented on a new line underneath it. This would work either way, but as it’s coded, we’ve saved an extra line.

Finally, the Python break statement is used to exit the loop immediately—it simply jumps out of the loop statement altogether, and the program continues after the loop. Without this exit statement, the while would loop forever, as its test is always true.

In effect, this combination of statements essentially means “read a line from the user and print it in uppercase until the user enters the word ‘stop.’” There are other ways to code such a loop, but the form used here is very common in Python code.

Notice that all three lines nested under the while header line are indented the same amount—because they line up vertically in a column this way, they are the block of code that is associated with the while test and repeated. Either the end of the source file or a lesser-indented statement will terminate the loop body block.

When run, here is the sort of interaction we get from this code:

Enter text:spam
SPAM
Enter text:42
42
Enter text:stop

Note

Version skew note: This example is coded for Python 3.0. If you are working in Python 2.6 or earlier, the code works the same, but you should use raw_input instead of input, and you can omit the outer parentheses in print statements. In 3.0 the former was renamed, and the latter is a built-in function instead of a statement (more on prints in the next chapter).

Doing Math on User Inputs

Our script works, but now suppose that instead of converting a text string to uppercase, we want to do some math with numeric input—squaring it, for example, perhaps in some misguided effort to discourage users who happen to be obsessed with youth. We might try statements like these to achieve the desired effect:

>>> reply = '20'
>>> reply ** 2
...error text omitted...
TypeError: unsupported operand type(s) for ** or pow(): 'str' and 'int'

This won’t quite work in our script, though, because (as discussed in the prior part of the book) Python won’t convert object types in expressions unless they are all numeric, and input from a user is always returned to our script as a string. We cannot raise a string of digits to a power unless we convert it manually to an integer:

>>> int(reply) ** 2
400

Armed with this information, we can now recode our loop to perform the necessary math. Type the following in a file to test it:

while True:
    reply = input('Enter text:')
    if reply == 'stop': break
    print(int(reply) ** 2)
print('Bye')

This script uses a single-line if statement to exit on “stop” as before, but it also converts inputs to perform the required math. This version also adds an exit message at the bottom. Because the print statement in the last line is not indented as much as the nested block of code, it is not considered part of the loop body and will run only once, after the loop is exited:

Enter text:2
4
Enter text:40
1600
Enter text:stop
Bye

One note here: I’m assuming that this code is stored in and run from a script file. If you are entering this code interactively, be sure to include a blank line (i.e., press Enter twice) before the final print statement, to terminate the loop. The final print doesn’t quite make sense in interactive mode, though (you’ll have to code it after interacting with the loop!).

Handling Errors by Testing Inputs

So far so good, but notice what happens when the input is invalid:

Enter text:xxx
...error text omitted...
ValueError: invalid literal for int() with base 10: 'xxx'

The built-in int function raises an exception here in the face of a mistake. If we want our script to be robust, we can check the string’s content ahead of time with the string object’s isdigit method:

>>> S = '123'
>>> T = 'xxx'
>>> S.isdigit(), T.isdigit()
(True, False)

This also gives us an excuse to further nest the statements in our example. The following new version of our interactive script uses a full-blown if statement to work around the exception on errors:

while True:
    reply = input('Enter text:')
    if reply == 'stop':
        break
    elif not reply.isdigit():
        print('Bad!' * 8)
    else:
        print(int(reply) ** 2)
print('Bye')

We’ll study the if statement in more detail in Chapter 12, but it’s a fairly lightweight tool for coding logic in scripts. In its full form, it consists of the word if followed by a test and an associated block of code, one or more optional elif (“else if”) tests and code blocks, and an optional else part, with an associated block of code at the bottom to serve as a default. Python runs the block of code associated with the first test that is true, working from top to bottom, or the else part if all tests are false.

The if, elif, and else parts in the preceding example are associated as part of the same statement because they all line up vertically (i.e., share the same level of indentation). The if statement spans from the word if to the start of the print statement on the last line of the script. In turn, the entire if block is part of the while loop because all of it is indented under the loop’s header line. Statement nesting is natural once you get the hang of it.

When we run our new script, its code catches errors before they occur and prints an (arguably silly) error message to demonstrate:

Enter text:5
25
Enter text:xyz
Bad!Bad!Bad!Bad!Bad!Bad!Bad!Bad!
Enter text:10
100
Enter text:stop

Handling Errors with try Statements

The preceding solution works, but as you’ll see later in the book, the most general way to handle errors in Python is to catch and recover from them completely using the Python try statement. We’ll explore this statement in depth in Part VII of this book, but as a preview, using a try here can lead to code that some would claim is simpler than the prior version:

while True:
    reply = input('Enter text:')
    if reply == 'stop': break
    try:
        num = int(reply)
    except:
        print('Bad!' * 8)
    else:
        print(int(reply) ** 2)
print('Bye')

This version works exactly like the previous one, but we’ve replaced the explicit error check with code that assumes the conversion will work and wraps it up in an exception handler for cases when it doesn’t. This try statement is composed of the word try, followed by the main block of code (the action we are trying to run), followed by an except part that gives the exception handler code and an else part to be run if no exception is raised in the try part. Python first runs the try part, then runs either the except part (if an exception occurs) or the else part (if no exception occurs).

In terms of statement nesting, because the words try, except, and else are all indented to the same level, they are all considered part of the same single try statement. Notice that the else part is associated with the try here, not the if. As we’ve seen, else can appear in if statements in Python, but it can also appear in try statements and loops—its indentation tells you what statement it is a part of. In this case, the try statement spans from the word try through the code indented under the word else, because the else is indented to the same level as try. The if statement in this code is a one-liner and ends after the break.

Again, we’ll come back to the try statement later in this book. For now, be aware that because try can be used to intercept any error, it reduces the amount of error-checking code you have to write, and it’s a very general approach to dealing with unusual cases. If we wanted to support input of floating-point numbers instead of just integers, for example, using try would be much easier than manual error testing—we could simply run a float call and catch its exceptions, instead of trying to analyze all possible floating-point syntax.

Nesting Code Three Levels Deep

Let’s look at one last mutation of our script. Nesting can take us even further if we need it to—we could, for example, branch to one of a set of alternatives based on the relative magnitude of a valid input:

while True:
    reply = input('Enter text:')
    if reply == 'stop':
        break
    elif not reply.isdigit():
        print('Bad!' * 8)
    else:
        num = int(reply)
        if num < 20:
            print('low')
        else:
            print(num ** 2)
print('Bye')

This version includes an if statement nested in the else clause of another if statement, which is in turn nested in the while loop. When code is conditional, or repeated like this, we simply indent it further to the right. The net effect is like that of the prior versions, but we’ll now print “low” for numbers less than 20:

Enter text:19
low
Enter text:20
400
Enter text:spam
Bad!Bad!Bad!Bad!Bad!Bad!Bad!Bad!
Enter text:stop
Bye

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

C-like languages require parentheses around the tests in some statements, semicolons at the end of each statement, and braces around a nested block of code.

The end of a line terminates the statement that appears on that line. Alternatively, if more than one statement appears on the same line, they can be terminated with semicolons; similarly, if a statement spans many lines, you must terminate it by closing a bracketed syntactic pair.

The statements in a nested block are all indented the same number of tabs or spaces.

A statement can be made to span many lines by enclosing part of it in parentheses, square brackets, or curly braces; the statement ends when Python sees a line that contains the closing part of the pair.

The body of a compound statement can be moved to the header line after the colon, but only if the body consists of only noncompound statements.

Only when you need to squeeze more than one statement onto a single line of code. Even then, this only works if all the statements are noncompound, and it’s discouraged because it can lead to code that is difficult to read.

The try statement is used to catch and recover from exceptions (errors) in a Python script. It’s usually an alternative to manually checking for errors in your code.

Forgetting to type the colon character at the end of the header line in a compound statement is the most common beginner’s mistake. If you haven’t made it yet, you probably will soon!

Assignment Statements

We’ve been using the Python assignment statement for a while to assign objects to names. In its basic form, you write the target of an assignment on the left of an equals sign, and the object to be assigned on the right. The target on the left may be a name or object component, and the object on the right can be an arbitrary expression that computes an object. For the most part, assignments are straightforward, but here are a few properties to keep in mind:

Assignments create object references. As discussed in Chapter 6, Python assignments store references to objects in names or data structure components. They always create references to objects instead of copying the objects. Because of that, Python variables are more like pointers than data storage areas.

Names are created when first assigned. Python creates a variable name the first time you assign it a value (i.e., an object reference), so there’s no need to predeclare names ahead of time. Some (but not all) data structure slots are created when assigned, too (e.g., dictionary entries, some object attributes). Once assigned, a name is replaced with the value it references whenever it appears in an expression.

Names must be assigned before being referenced. It’s an error to use a name to which you haven’t yet assigned a value. Python raises an exception if you try, rather than returning some sort of ambiguous default value; if it returned a default instead, it would be more difficult for you to spot typos in your code.

Some operations perform assignments implicitly. In this section we’re concerned with the = statement, but assignment occurs in many contexts in Python. For instance, we’ll see later that module imports, function and class definitions, for loop variables, and function arguments are all implicit assignments. Because assignment works the same everywhere it pops up, all these contexts simply bind names to object references at runtime.

Assignment Statement Forms

Although assignment is a general and pervasive concept in Python, we are primarily interested in assignment statements in this chapter. Table 11-1 illustrates the different assignment statement forms in Python.

Table 11-1. Assignment statement forms

Operation

|

Interpretation

spam = 'Spam'

|

Basic form

spam, ham = 'yum', 'YUM'

|

Tuple assignment (positional)

[spam, ham] = ['yum', 'YUM']

|

List assignment (positional)

a, b, c, d = 'spam'

|

Sequence assignment, generalized

a, *b = 'spam'

|

Extended sequence unpacking (Python 3.0)

spam = ham = 'lunch'

|

Multiple-target assignment

spams += 42

|

Augmented assignment (equivalent to spams = spams + 42)

The first form in Table 11-1 is by far the most common: binding a name (or data structure component) to a single object. In fact, you could get all your work done with this basic form alone. The other table entries represent special forms that are all optional, but that programmers often find convenient in practice:

Tuple- and list-unpacking assignments

The second and third forms in the table are related. When you code a tuple or list on the left side of the =, Python pairs objects on the right side with targets on the left by position and assigns them from left to right. For example, in the second line of Table 11-1, the name spam is assigned the string 'yum', and the name ham is bound to the string 'YUM'. In this case Python internally makes a tuple of the items on the right, which is why this is called tuple-unpacking assignment.

Sequence assignments

In recent versions of Python, tuple and list assignments have been generalized into instances of what we now call sequence assignment—any sequence of names can be assigned to any sequence of values, and Python assigns the items one at a time by position. We can even mix and match the types of the sequences involved. The fourth line in Table 11-1, for example, pairs a tuple of names with a string of characters: a is assigned 's', b is assigned 'p', and so on.

Extended sequence unpacking

In Python 3.0, a new form of sequence assignment allows us to be more flexible in how we select portions of a sequence to assign. The fifth line in Table 11-1, for example, matches a with the first character in the string on the right and b with the rest: a is assigned 's', and b is assigned 'pam'. This provides a simpler alternative to assigning the results of manual slicing operations.

Multiple-target assignments

The sixth line in Table 11-1 shows the multiple-target form of assignment. In this form, Python assigns a reference to the same object (the object farthest to the right) to all the targets on the left. In the table, the names spam and ham are both assigned references to the same string object, 'lunch'. The effect is the same as if we had coded ham = 'lunch' followed by spam = ham, as ham evaluates to the original string object (i.e., not a separate copy of that object).

Augmented assignments

The last line in Table 11-1 is an example of augmented assignment—a shorthand that combines an expression and an assignment in a concise way. Saying spam += 42, for example, has the same effect as spam = spam + 42, but the augmented form requires less typing and is generally quicker to run. In addition, if the subject is mutable and supports the operation, an augmented assignment may run even quicker by choosing an in-place update operation instead of an object copy. There is one augmented assignment statement for every binary expression operator in Python.

Sequence Assignments

We’ve already used basic assignments in this book. Here are a few simple examples of sequence-unpacking assignments in action:

% python
>>> nudge = 1
>>> wink  = 2
>>> A, B = nudge, wink             # Tuple assignment
>>> A, B                           # Like A = nudge; B = wink
(1, 2)
>>> [C, D] = [nudge, wink]         # List assignment
>>> C, D
(1, 2)

Notice that we really are coding two tuples in the third line in this interaction—we’ve just omitted their enclosing parentheses. Python pairs the values in the tuple on the right side of the assignment operator with the variables in the tuple on the left side and assigns the values one at a time.

Tuple assignment leads to a common coding trick in Python that was introduced in a solution to the exercises at the end of Part II. Because Python creates a temporary tuple that saves the original values of the variables on the right while the statement runs, unpacking assignments are also a way to swap two variables’ values without creating a temporary variable of your own—the tuple on the right remembers the prior values of the variables automatically:

>>> nudge = 1
>>> wink  = 2
>>> nudge, wink = wink, nudge      # Tuples: swaps values
>>> nudge, wink                    # Like T = nudge; nudge = wink; wink = T
(2, 1)

In fact, the original tuple and list assignment forms in Python have been generalized to accept any type of sequence on the right as long as it is of the same length as the sequence on the left. You can assign a tuple of values to a list of variables, a string of characters to a tuple of variables, and so on. In all cases, Python assigns items in the sequence on the right to variables in the sequence on the left by position, from left to right:

>>> [a, b, c] = (1, 2, 3)          # Assign tuple of values to list of names
>>> a, c
(1, 3)
>>> (a, b, c) = "ABC"              # Assign string of characters to tuple
>>> a, c
('A', 'C')

Technically speaking, sequence assignment actually supports any iterable object on the right, not just any sequence. This is a more general concept that we will explore in Chapters 14 and 20.

Advanced sequence assignment patterns

Although we can mix and match sequence types around the = symbol, we must have the same number of items on the right as we have variables on the left, or we’ll get an error. Python 3.0 allows us to be more general with extended unpacking syntax, described in the next section. But normally, and always in Python 2.X, the number of items in the assignment target and subject must match:

>>> string = 'SPAM'
>>> a, b, c, d = string                            # Same number on both sides
>>> a, d
('S', 'M')

>>> a, b, c = string                               # Error if not
...error text omitted...
ValueError: too many values to unpack

To be more general, we can slice. There are a variety of ways to employ slicing to make this last case work:

>>> a, b, c = string[0], string[1], string[2:]     # Index and slice
>>> a, b, c
('S', 'P', 'AM')

>>> a, b, c = list(string[:2]) + [string[2:]]      # Slice and concatenate
>>> a, b, c
('S', 'P', 'AM')

>>> a, b = string[:2]                              # Same, but simpler
>>> c = string[2:]
>>> a, b, c
('S', 'P', 'AM')

>>> (a, b), c = string[:2], string[2:]             # Nested sequences
>>> a, b, c
('S', 'P', 'AM')

As the last example in this interaction demonstrates, we can even assign nested sequences, and Python unpacks their parts according to their shape, as expected. In this case, we are assigning a tuple of two items, where the first item is a nested sequence (a string), exactly as though we had coded it this way:

>>> ((a, b), c) = ('SP', 'AM')                     # Paired by shape and position
>>> a, b, c
('S', 'P', 'AM')

Python pairs the first string on the right ('SP') with the first tuple on the left ((a, b)) and assigns one character at a time, before assigning the entire second string ('AM') to the variable c all at once. In this event, the sequence-nesting shape of the object on the left must match that of the object on the right. Nested sequence assignment like this is somewhat advanced, and rare to see, but it can be convenient for picking out the parts of data structures with known shapes.

For example, we’ll see in Chapter 13 that this technique also works in for loops, because loop items are assigned to the target given in the loop header:

for (a, b, c) in [(1, 2, 3), (4, 5, 6)]: ...          # Simple tuple assignment

for ((a, b), c) in [((1, 2), 3), ((4, 5), 6)]: ...    # Nested tuple assignment

In a note in Chapter 18, we’ll also see that this nested tuple (really, sequence) unpacking assignment form works for function argument lists in Python 2.6 (though not in 3.0), because function arguments are passed by assignment as well:

def f(((a, b), c)):              # For arguments too in Python 2.6, but not 3.0
f(((1, 2), 3))

Sequence-unpacking assignments also give rise to another common coding idiom in Python—assigning an integer series to a set of variables:

>>> red, green, blue = range(3)
>>> red, blue
(0, 2)

This initializes the three names to the integer codes 0, 1, and 2, respectively (it’s Python’s equivalent of the enumerated data types you may have seen in other languages). To make sense of this, you need to know that the range built-in function generates a list of successive integers:

>>> range(3)                             # Use list(range(3)) in Python 3.0
[0, 1, 2]

Because range is commonly used in for loops, we’ll say more about it in Chapter 13.

Another place you may see a tuple assignment at work is for splitting a sequence into its front and the rest in loops like this:

>>> L = [1, 2, 3, 4]
>>> while L:
...     front, L = L[0], L[1:]           # See next section for 3.0 alternative
...     print(front, L)
...
1 [2, 3, 4]
2 [3, 4]
3 [4]
4 []

The tuple assignment in the loop here could be coded as the following two lines instead, but it’s often more convenient to string them together:

...     front = L[0]
...     L = L[1:]

Notice that this code is using the list as a sort of stack data structure, which can often also be achieved with the append and pop methods of list objects; here, front = L.pop(0) would have much the same effect as the tuple assignment statement, but it would be an in-place change. We’ll learn more about while loops, and other (often better) ways to step through a sequence with for loops, in Chapter 13.

Extended Sequence Unpacking in Python 3.0

The prior section demonstrated how to use manual slicing to make sequence assignments more general. In Python 3.0 (but not 2.6), sequence assignment has been generalized to make this easier. In short, a single starred name, *X, can be used in the assignment target in order to specify a more general matching against the sequence—the starred name is assigned a list, which collects all items in the sequence not assigned to other names. This is especially handy for common coding patterns such as splitting a sequence into its “front” and “rest”, as in the preceding section’s last example.

Extended unpacking in action

Let’s look at an example. As we’ve seen, sequence assignments normally require exactly as many names in the target on the left as there are items in the subject on the right. We get an error if the lengths disagree (unless we manually sliced on the right, as shown in the prior section):

C:\misc> c:\python30\python
>>> seq = [1, 2, 3, 4]
>>> a, b, c, d = seq
>>> print(a, b, c, d)
1 2 3 4

>>> a, b = seq
ValueError: too many values to unpack

In Python 3.0, though, we can use a single starred name in the target to match more generally. In the following continuation of our interactive session, a matches the first item in the sequence, and b matches the rest:

>>> a, *b = seq
>>> a
1
>>> b
[2, 3, 4]

When a starred name is used, the number of items in the target on the left need not match the length of the subject sequence. In fact, the starred name can appear anywhere in the target. For instance, in the next interaction b matches the last item in the sequence, and a matches everything before the last:

>>> *a, b = seq
>>> a
[1, 2, 3]
>>> b
4

When the starred name appears in the middle, it collects everything between the other names listed. Thus, in the following interaction a and c are assigned the first and last items, and b gets everything in between them:

>>> a, *b, c = seq
>>> a
1
>>> b
[2, 3]
>>> c
4

More generally, wherever the starred name shows up, it will be assigned a list that collects every unassigned name at that position:

>>> a, b, *c = seq
>>> a
1
>>> b
2
>>> c
[3, 4]

Naturally, like normal sequence assignment, extended sequence unpacking syntax works for any sequence types, not just lists. Here it is unpacking characters in a string:

>>> a, *b = 'spam'
>>> a, b
('s', ['p', 'a', 'm'])

>>> a, *b, c = 'spam'
>>> a, b, c
('s', ['p', 'a'], 'm')

This is similar in spirit to slicing, but not exactly the same—a sequence unpacking assignment always returns a list for multiple matched items, whereas slicing returns a sequence of the same type as the object sliced:

>>> S = 'spam'

>>> S[0], S[1:]    # Slices are type-specific, * assignment always returns a list
('s', 'pam')

>>> S[0], S[1:3], S[3]
('s', 'pa', 'm')

Given this extension in 3.0, as long as we’re processing a list the last example of the prior section becomes even simpler, since we don’t have to manually slice to get the first and rest of the items:

>>> L = [1, 2, 3, 4]
>>> while L:
...     front, *L = L                    # Get first, rest without slicing
...     print(front, L)
...
1 [2, 3, 4]
2 [3, 4]
3 [4]
4 []

Boundary cases

Although extended sequence unpacking is flexible, some boundary cases are worth noting. First, the starred name may match just a single item, but is always assigned a list:

>>> seq
[1, 2, 3, 4]

>>> a, b, c, *d = seq
>>> print(a, b, c, d)
1 2 3 [4]

Second, if there is nothing left to match the starred name, it is assigned an empty list, regardless of where it appears. In the following, a, b, c, and d have matched every item in the sequence, but Python assigns e an empty list instead of treating this as an error case:

>>> a, b, c, d, *e = seq
>>> print(a, b, c, d, e)
1 2 3 4 []

>>> a, b, *e, c, d = seq
>>> print(a, b, c, d, e)
1 2 3 4 []

Finally, errors can still be triggered if there is more than one starred name, if there are too few values and no star (as before), and if the starred name is not itself coded inside a sequence:

>>> a, *b, c, *d = seq
SyntaxError: two starred expressions in assignment

>>> a, b = seq
ValueError: too many values to unpack

>>> *a = seq
SyntaxError: starred assignment target must be in a list or tuple

>>> *a, = seq
>>> a
[1, 2, 3, 4]

A useful convenience

Keep in mind that extended sequence unpacking assignment is just a convenience. We can usually achieve the same effects with explicit indexing and slicing (and in fact must in Python 2.X), but extended unpacking is simpler to code. The common “first, rest” splitting coding pattern, for example, can be coded either way, but slicing involves extra work:

>>> seq
[1, 2, 3, 4]

>>> a, *b = seq                        # First, rest
>>> a, b
(1, [2, 3, 4])

>>> a, b = seq[0], seq[1:]             # First, rest: traditional
>>> a, b
(1, [2, 3, 4])

The also common “rest, last” splitting pattern can similarly be coded either way, but the new extended unpacking syntax requires noticeably fewer keystrokes:

>>> *a, b = seq                        # Rest, last
>>> a, b
([1, 2, 3], 4)

>>> a, b = seq[:-1], seq[-1]           # Rest, last: traditional
>>> a, b
([1, 2, 3], 4)

Because it is not only simpler but, arguably, more natural, extended sequence unpacking syntax will likely become widespread in Python code over time.

Application to for loops

Because the loop variable in the for loop statement can be any assignment target, extended sequence assignment works here too. We met the for loop iteration tool briefly in Part II and will study it formally in Chapter 13. In Python 3.0, extended assignments may show up after the word for, where a simple variable name is more commonly used:

for (a, *b, c) in [(1, 2, 3, 4), (5, 6, 7, 8)]:
    ...

When used in this context, on each iteration Python simply assigns the next tuple of values to the tuple of names. On the first loop, for example, it’s as if we’d run the following assignment statement:

a, *b, c = (1, 2, 3, 4)                            # b gets [2, 3]

The names a, b, and c can be used within the loop’s code to reference the extracted components. In fact, this is really not a special case at all, but just an instance of general assignment at work. As we saw earlier in this chapter, we can do the same thing with simple tuple assignment in both Python 2.X and 3.X:

for (a, b, c) in [(1, 2, 3), (4, 5, 6)]:           # a, b, c = (1, 2, 3), ...

And we can always emulate 3.0’s extended assignment behavior in 2.6 by manually slicing:

for all in [(1, 2, 3, 4), (5, 6, 7, 8)]:
    a, b, c = all[0], all[1:3], all[3]

Since we haven’t learned enough to get more detailed about the syntax of for loops, we’ll return to this topic in Chapter 13.

Multiple-Target Assignments

A multiple-target assignment simply assigns all the given names to the object all the way to the right. The following, for example, assigns the three variables a, b, and c to the string 'spam':

>>> a = b = c = 'spam'
>>> a, b, c
('spam', 'spam', 'spam')

This form is equivalent to (but easier to code than) these three assignments:

>>> c = 'spam'
>>> b = c
>>> a = b

Multiple-target assignment and shared references

Keep in mind that there is just one object here, shared by all three variables (they all wind up pointing to the same object in memory). This behavior is fine for immutable types—for example, when initializing a set of counters to zero (recall that variables must be assigned before they can be used in Python, so you must initialize counters to zero before you can start adding to them):

>>> a = b = 0
>>> b = b + 1
>>> a, b
(0, 1)

Here, changing b only changes b because numbers do not support in-place changes. As long as the object assigned is immutable, it’s irrelevant if more than one name references it.

As usual, though, we have to be more cautious when initializing variables to an empty mutable object such as a list or dictionary:

>>> a = b = []
>>> b.append(42)
>>> a, b
([42], [42])

This time, because a and b reference the same object, appending to it in-place through b will impact what we see through a as well. This is really just another example of the shared reference phenomenon we first met in Chapter 6. To avoid the issue, initialize mutable objects in separate statements instead, so that each creates a distinct empty object by running a distinct literal expression:

>>> a = []
>>> b = []
>>> b.append(42)
>>> a, b
([], [42])

Augmented Assignments

Beginning with Python 2.0, the set of additional assignment statement formats listed in Table 11-2 became available. Known as augmented assignments, and borrowed from the C language, these formats are mostly just shorthand. They imply the combination of a binary expression and an assignment. For instance, the following two formats are now roughly equivalent:

X = X + Y                       # Traditional form
X += Y                          # Newer augmented form

Table 11-2. Augmented assignment statements

X += Y

|

X &= Y

|

X -= Y

|

X |= Y

X *= Y

|

X ^= Y

|

X /= Y

|

X >>= Y

X %= Y

|

X <<= Y

|

X **= Y

|

X //= Y

Augmented assignment works on any type that supports the implied binary expression. For example, here are two ways to add 1 to a name:

>>> x = 1
>>> x = x + 1                   # Traditional
>>> x
2
>>> x += 1                      # Augmented
>>> x
3

When applied to a string, the augmented form performs concatenation instead. Thus, the second line here is equivalent to typing the longer S = S + "SPAM":

>>> S = "spam"
>>> S += "SPAM"                 # Implied concatenation
>>> S
'spamSPAM'

As shown in Table 11-2, there are analogous augmented assignment forms for every Python binary expression operator (i.e., each operator with values on the left and right side). For instance, X *= Y multiplies and assigns, X >>= Y shifts right and assigns, and so on. X //= Y (for floor division) was added in version 2.2.

Augmented assignments have three advantages:[25]

There’s less for you to type. Need I say more?

The left side only has to be evaluated once. In X += Y, X may be a complicated object expression. In the augmented form, it only has to be evaluated once. However, in the long form, X = X + Y, X appears twice and must be run twice. Because of this, augmented assignments usually run faster.

The optimal technique is automatically chosen. That is, for objects that support in-place changes, the augmented forms automatically perform in-place change operations instead of slower copies.

The last point here requires a bit more explanation. For augmented assignments, in-place operations may be applied for mutable objects as an optimization. Recall that lists can be extended in a variety of ways. To add a single item to the end of a list, we can concatenate or call append:

>>> L = [1, 2]
>>> L = L + [3]                 # Concatenate: slower
>>> L
[1, 2, 3]
>>> L.append(4)                 # Faster, but in-place
>>> L
[1, 2, 3, 4]

And to add a set of items to the end, we can either concatenate again or call the list extend method:[26]

>>> L = L + [5, 6]              # Concatenate: slower
>>> L
[1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6]
>>> L.extend([7, 8])            # Faster, but in-place
>>> L
[1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8]

In both cases, concatenation is less prone to the side effects of shared object references but will generally run slower than the in-place equivalent. Concatenation operations must create a new object, copy in the list on the left, and then copy in the list on the right. By contrast, in-place method calls simply add items at the end of a memory block.

When we use augmented assignment to extend a list, we can forget these details—for example, Python automatically calls the quicker extend method instead of using the slower concatenation operation implied by +:

>>> L += [9, 10]                # Mapped to L.extend([9, 10])
>>> L
[1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10]

Augmented assignment and shared references

This behavior is usually what we want, but notice that it implies that the += is an in-place change for lists; thus, it is not exactly like + concatenation, which always makes a new object. As for all shared reference cases, this difference might matter if other names reference the object being changed:

>>> L = [1, 2]
>>> M = L                       # L and M reference the same object
>>> L = L + [3, 4]              # Concatenation makes a new object
>>> L, M                        # Changes L but not M
([1, 2, 3, 4], [1, 2])

>>> L = [1, 2]
>>> M = L
>>> L += [3, 4]                 # But += really means extend
>>> L, M                        # M sees the in-place change too!
([1, 2, 3, 4], [1, 2, 3, 4])

This only matters for mutables like lists and dictionaries, and it is a fairly obscure case (at least, until it impacts your code!). As always, make copies of your mutable objects if you need to break the shared reference structure.

Variable Name Rules

Now that we’ve explored assignment statements, it’s time to get more formal about the use of variable names. In Python, names come into existence when you assign values to them, but there are a few rules to follow when picking names for things in your programs:

Syntax: (underscore or letter) + (any number of letters, digits, or underscores)

Variable names must start with an underscore or letter, which can be followed by any number of letters, digits, or underscores. _spam, spam, and Spam_1 are legal names, but 1_Spam, spam$, and @#! are not.

Case matters: SPAM is not the same as spam

Python always pays attention to case in programs, both in names you create and in reserved words. For instance, the names X and x refer to two different variables. For portability, case also matters in the names of imported module files, even on platforms where the filesystems are case-insensitive.

Reserved words are off-limits

Names you define cannot be the same as words that mean special things in the Python language. For instance, if you try to use a variable name like class, Python will raise a syntax error, but klass and Class work fine. Table 11-3 lists the words that are currently reserved (and hence off-limits for names of your own) in Python.

Table 11-3. Python 3.0 reserved words

False

|

class

|

finally

|

is

|

return

None

|

continue

|

for

|

lambda

|

try

True

|

def

|

from

|

nonlocal

|

while

and

|

del

|

global

|

not

|

with

as

|

elif

|

if

|

or

|

yield

assert

|

else

|

import

|

pass

|

break

|

except

|

in

|

raise

|

Table 11-3 is specific to Python 3.0. In Python 2.6, the set of reserved words differs slightly:

print is a reserved word, because printing is a statement, not a built-in (more on this later in this chapter).

exec is a reserved word, because it is a statement, not a built-in function.

nonlocal is not a reserved word because this statement is not available.

In older Pythons the story is also more or less the same, with a few variations:

with and as were not reserved until 2.6, when context managers were officially enabled.

yield was not reserved until Python 2.3, when generator functions were enabled.

yield morphed from statement to expression in 2.5, but it’s still a reserved word, not a built-in function.

As you can see, most of Python’s reserved words are all lowercase. They are also all truly reserved—unlike names in the built-in scope that you will meet in the next part of this book, you cannot redefine reserved words by assignment (e.g., and = 1 results in a syntax error).[27]

Besides being of mixed case, the first three entries in Table 11-3, True, False, and None, are somewhat unusual in meaning—they also appear in the built-in scope of Python described in Chapter 17, and they are technically names assigned to objects. They are truly reserved in all other senses, though, and cannot be used for any other purpose in your script other than that of the objects they represent. All the other reserved words are hardwired into Python’s syntax and can appear only in the specific contexts for which they are intended.

Furthermore, because module names in import statements become variables in your scripts, variable name constraints extend to your module filenames too. For instance, you can code files called and.py and my-code.py and run them as top-level scripts, but you cannot import them: their names without the “.py” extension become variables in your code and so must follow all the variable rules just outlined. Reserved words are off-limits, and dashes won’t work, though underscores will. We’ll revisit this idea in Part V of this book.

Python’s Deprecation Protocol

It is interesting to note how reserved word changes are gradually phased into the language. When a new feature might break existing code, Python normally makes it an option and begins issuing “deprecation” warnings one or more releases before the feature is officially enabled. The idea is that you should have ample time to notice the warnings and update your code before migrating to the new release. This is not true for major new releases like 3.0 (which breaks existing code freely), but it is generally true in other cases.

For example, yield was an optional extension in Python 2.2, but is a standard keyword as of 2.3. It is used in conjunction with generator functions. This was one of a small handful of instances where Python broke with backward compatibility. Still, yield was phased in over time: it began generating deprecation warnings in 2.2 and was not enabled until 2.3.

Similarly, in Python 2.6, the words with and as become new reserved words for use in context managers (a newer form of exception handling). These two words are not reserved in 2.5, unless the context manager feature is turned on manually with a from__future__import (discussed later in this book). When used in 2.5, with and as generate warnings about the upcoming change—except in the version of IDLE in Python 2.5, which appears to have enabled this feature for you (that is, using these words as variable names does generate errors in 2.5, but only in its version of the IDLE GUI).

Naming conventions

Besides these rules, there is also a set of naming conventions—rules that are not required but are followed in normal practice. For instance, because names with two leading and trailing underscores (e.g., __name__) generally have special meaning to the Python interpreter, you should avoid this pattern for your own names. Here is a list of the conventions Python follows:

Names that begin with a single underscore (_X) are not imported by a from module import * statement (described in Chapter 22).

Names that have two leading and trailing underscores (__X__) are system-defined names that have special meaning to the interpreter.

Names that begin with two underscores and do not end with two more (__X) are localized (“mangled”) to enclosing classes (see the discussion of pseudoprivate attributes in Chapter 30).

The name that is just a single underscore (_) retains the result of the last expression when working interactively.

In addition to these Python interpreter conventions, there are various other conventions that Python programmers usually follow. For instance, later in the book we’ll see that class names commonly start with an uppercase letter and module names with a lowercase letter, and that the name self, though not reserved, usually has a special role in classes. In Chapter 17 we’ll also study another, larger category of names known as the built-ins, which are predefined but not reserved (and so can be reassigned: open = 42 works, though sometimes you might wish it didn’t!).

Names have no type, but objects do

This is mostly review, but remember that it’s crucial to keep Python’s distinction between names and objects clear. As described in Chapter 6, objects have a type (e.g., integer, list) and may be mutable or not. Names (a.k.a. variables), on the other hand, are always just references to objects; they have no notion of mutability and have no associated type information, apart from the type of the object they happen to reference at a given point in time.

Thus, it’s OK to assign the same name to different kinds of objects at different times:

>>> x = 0               # x bound to an integer object
>>> x = "Hello"         # Now it's a string
>>> x = [1, 2, 3]       # And now it's a list

In later examples, you’ll see that this generic nature of names can be a decided advantage in Python programming. In Chapter 17, you’ll also learn that names also live in something called a scope, which defines where they can be used; the place where you assign a name determines where it is visible.[28]

Note

For additional naming suggestions, see the discussion of naming conventions in Python’s semi-official style guide, known as PEP 8. This guide is available at http://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0008, or via a web search for “Python PEP 8.” Technically, this document formalizes coding standards for Python library code.

Though useful, the usual caveats about coding standards apply here. For one thing, PEP 8 comes with more detail than you are probably ready for at this point in the book. And frankly, it has become more complex, rigid, and subjective than it needs to be—some of its suggestions are not at all universally accepted or followed by Python programmers doing real work. Moreover, some of the most prominent companies using Python today have adopted coding standards of their own that differ.

PEP 8 does codify useful rule-of-thumb Python knowledge, though, and it’s a great read for Python beginners, as long as you take its recommendations as guidelines, not gospel.

Expression Statements

In Python, you can use an expression as a statement, too—that is, on a line by itself. But because the result of the expression won’t be saved, it usually makes sense to do so only if the expression does something useful as a side effect. Expressions are commonly used as statements in two situations:

For calls to functions and methods

Some functions and methods do lots of work without returning a value. Such functions are sometimes called procedures in other languages. Because they don’t return values that you might be interested in retaining, you can call these functions with expression statements.

For printing values at the interactive prompt

Python echoes back the results of expressions typed at the interactive command line. Technically, these are expression statements, too; they serve as a shorthand for typing print statements.

Table 11-4 lists some common expression statement forms in Python. Calls to functions and methods are coded with zero or more argument objects (really, expressions that evaluate to objects) in parentheses, after the function/method name.

Table 11-4. Common Python expression statements

Operation

|

Interpretation

spam(eggs, ham)

|

Function calls

spam.ham(eggs)

|

Method calls

spam

|

Printing variables in the interactive interpreter

print(a, b, c, sep='')

|

Printing operations in Python 3.0

yield x ** 2

|

Yielding expression statements

The last two entries in Table 11-4 are somewhat special cases—as we’ll see later in this chapter, printing in Python 3.0 is a function call usually coded on a line by itself, and the yield operation in generator functions (discussed in Chapter 20) is often coded as a statement as well. Both are really just instances of expression statements.

For instance, though you normally run a print call on a line by itself as an expression statement, it returns a value like any other function call (its return value is None, the default return value for functions that don’t return anything meaningful):

>>> x = print('spam')         # print is a function call expression in 3.0
spam
>>> print(x)                  # But it is coded as an expression statement
None

Also keep in mind that although expressions can appear as statements in Python, statements cannot be used as expressions. For example, Python doesn’t allow you to embed assignment statements (=) in other expressions. The rationale for this is that it avoids common coding mistakes; you can’t accidentally change a variable by typing = when you really mean to use the == equality test. You’ll see how to code around this when you meet the Python while loop in Chapter 13.

Expression Statements and In-Place Changes

This brings up a mistake that is common in Python work. Expression statements are often used to run list methods that change a list in-place:

>>> L = [1, 2]
>>> L.append(3)               # Append is an in-place change
>>> L
[1, 2, 3]

However, it’s not unusual for Python newcomers to code such an operation as an assignment statement instead, intending to assign L to the larger list:

>>> L = L.append(4)           # But append returns None, not L
>>> print(L)                  # So we lose our list!
None

This doesn’t quite work, though. Calling an in-place change operation such as append, sort, or reverse on a list always changes the list in-place, but these methods do not return the list they have changed; instead, they return the None object. Thus, if you assign such an operation’s result back to the variable name, you effectively lose the list (and it is probably garbage collected in the process!).

The moral of the story is, don’t do this. We’ll revisit this phenomenon in the section Common Coding Gotchas at the end of this part of the book because it can also appear in the context of some looping statements we’ll meet in later chapters.

Print Operations

In Python, print prints things—it’s simply a programmer-friendly interface to the standard output stream.

Technically, printing converts one or more objects to their textual representations, adds some minor formatting, and sends the resulting text to either standard output or another file-like stream. In a bit more detail, print is strongly bound up with the notions of files and streams in Python:

File object methods

In Chapter 9, we learned about file object methods that write text (e.g., file.write(str)). Printing operations are similar, but more focused—whereas file write methods write strings to arbitrary files, print writes objects to the stdout stream by default, with some automatic formatting added. Unlike with file methods, there is no need to convert objects to strings when using print operations.

Standard output stream

The standard output stream (often known as stdout) is simply a default place to send a program’s text output. Along with the standard input and error streams, it’s one of three data connections created when your script starts. The standard output stream is usually mapped to the window where you started your Python program, unless it’s been redirected to a file or pipe in your operating system’s shell.

Because the standard output stream is available in Python as the stdout file object in the built-in sys module (i.e., sys.stdout), it’s possible to emulate print with file write method calls. However, print is noticeably easier to use and makes it easy to print text to other files and streams.

Printing is also one of the most visible places where Python 3.0 and 2.6 have diverged. In fact, this divergence is usually the first reason that most 2.X code won’t run unchanged under 3.X. Specifically, the way you code print operations depends on which version of Python you use:

In Python 3.X, printing is a built-in function, with keyword arguments for special modes.

In Python 2.X, printing is a statement with specific syntax all its own.

Because this book covers both 3.0 and 2.6, we will look at each form in turn here. If you are fortunate enough to be able to work with code written for just one version of Python, feel free to pick the section that is relevant to you; however, as your circumstances may change, it probably won’t hurt to be familiar with both cases.

The Python 3.0 print Function

Strictly speaking, printing is not a separate statement form in 3.0. Instead, it is simply an instance of the expression statement we studied in the preceding section.

The print built-in function is normally called on a line of its own, because it doesn’t return any value we care about (technically, it returns None). Because it is a normal function, though, printing in 3.0 uses standard function-call syntax, rather than a special statement form. Because it provides special operation modes with keyword arguments, this form is both more general and supports future enhancements better.

By comparison, Python 2.6 print statements have somewhat ad-hoc syntax to support extensions such as end-of-line suppression and target files. Further, the 2.6 statement does not support separator specification at all; in 2.6, you wind up building strings ahead of time more often than you do in 3.0.

Call format

Syntactically, calls to the 3.0 print function have the following form:

print([object, ...][, sep=' '][, end='\n'][, file=sys.stdout])

In this formal notation, items in square brackets are optional and may be omitted in a given call, and values after = give argument defaults. In English, this built-in function prints the textual representation of one or more objects separated by the string sep and followed by the string end to the stream file.

The sep, end, and file parts, if present, must be given as keyword arguments—that is, you must use a special “name=value” syntax to pass the arguments by name instead of position. Keyword arguments are covered in depth in Chapter 18, but they’re straightforward to use. The keyword arguments sent to this call may appear in any left-to-right order following the objects to be printed, and they control the print operation:

sep is a string inserted between each object’s text, which defaults to a single space if not passed; passing an empty string suppresses separators altogether.

end is a string added at the end of the printed text, which defaults to a \n newline character if not passed. Passing an empty string avoids dropping down to the next output line at the end of the printed text—the next print will keep adding to the end of the current output line.

file specifies the file, standard stream, or other file-like object to which the text will be sent; it defaults to the sys.stdout standard output stream if not passed. Any object with a file-like write(string) method may be passed, but real files should be already opened for output.

The textual representation of each object to be printed is obtained by passing the object to the str built-in call; as we’ve seen, this built-in returns a “user friendly” display string for any object.[29] With no arguments at all, the print function simply prints a newline character to the standard output stream, which usually displays a blank line.

The 3.0 print function in action

Printing in 3.0 is probably simpler than some of its details may imply. To illustrate, let’s run some quick examples. The following prints a variety of object types to the default standard output stream, with the default separator and end-of-line formatting added (these are the defaults because they are the most common use case):

C:\misc> c:\python30\python
>>>
>>> print()                                      # Display a blank line

>>> x = 'spam'
>>> y = 99
>>> z = ['eggs']
>>>
>>> print(x, y, z)                               # Print 3 objects per defaults
spam 99 ['eggs']

There’s no need to convert objects to strings here, as would be required for file write methods. By default, print calls add a space between the objects printed. To suppress this, send an empty string to the sep keyword argument, or send an alternative separator of your choosing:

>>> print(x, y, z, sep='')                       # Suppress separator
spam99['eggs']
>>>
>>> print(x, y, z, sep=', ')                     # Custom separator
spam, 99, ['eggs']

Also by default, print adds an end-of-line character to terminate the output line. You can suppress this and avoid the line break altogether by passing an empty string to the end keyword argument, or you can pass a different terminator of your own (include a \n character to break the line manually):

>>> print(x, y, z, end='')                        # Suppress line break
spam 99 ['eggs']>>>
>>>
>>> print(x, y, z, end=''); print(x, y, z)        # Two prints, same output line
spam 99 ['eggs']spam 99 ['eggs']
>>> print(x, y, z, end='...\n')                   # Custom line end
spam 99 ['eggs']...
>>>

You can also combine keyword arguments to specify both separators and end-of-line strings—they may appear in any order but must appear after all the objects being printed:

>>> print(x, y, z, sep='...', end='!\n')          # Multiple keywords
spam...99...['eggs']!
>>> print(x, y, z, end='!\n', sep='...')          # Order doesn't matter
spam...99...['eggs']!

Here is how the file keyword argument is used—it directs the printed text to an open output file or other compatible object for the duration of the single print (this is really a form of stream redirection, a topic we will revisit later in this section):

>>> print(x, y, z, sep='...', file=open('data.txt', 'w'))      # Print to a file
>>> print(x, y, z)                                             # Back to stdout
spam 99 ['eggs']
>>> print(open('data.txt').read())                             # Display file text
spam...99...['eggs']

Finally, keep in mind that the separator and end-of-line options provided by print operations are just conveniences. If you need to display more specific formatting, don’t print this way, Instead, build up a more complex string ahead of time or within the print itself using the string tools we met in Chapter 7, and print the string all at once:

>>> text = '%s: %-.4f, %05d' % ('Result', 3.14159, 42)
>>> print(text)
Result: 3.1416, 00042
>>> print('%s: %-.4f, %05d' % ('Result', 3.14159, 42))
Result: 3.1416, 00042

As we’ll see in the next section, almost everything we’ve just seen about the 3.0 print function also applies directly to 2.6 print statements—which makes sense, given that the function was intended to both emulate and improve upon 2.6 printing support.

The Python 2.6 print Statement

As mentioned earlier, printing in Python 2.6 uses a statement with unique and specific syntax, rather than a built-in function. In practice, though, 2.6 printing is mostly a variation on a theme; with the exception of separator strings (which are supported in 3.0 but not 2.6), everything we can do with the 3.0 print function has a direct translation to the 2.6 print statement.

Statement forms

Table 11-5 lists the print statement’s forms in Python 2.6 and gives their Python 3.0 print function equivalents for reference. Notice that the comma is significant in print statements—it separates objects to be printed, and a trailing comma suppresses the end-of-line character normally added at the end of the printed text (not to be confused with tuple syntax!). The >> syntax, normally used as a bitwise right-shift operation, is used here as well, to specify a target output stream other than the sys.stdout default.

Table 11-5. Python 2.6 print statement forms

Python 2.6 statement

|

Python 3.0 equivalent

|

Interpretation

print x, y

|

print(x, y)

|

Print objects’ textual forms to sys.stdout; add a space between the items and an end-of-line at the end

print x, y,

|

print(x, y, end='')

|

Same, but don’t add end-of-line at end of text

print >> afile, x, y

|

print(x, y, file=afile)

|

Send text to afile.write, not to sys.stdout.write

The 2.6 print statement in action

Although the 2.6 print statement has more unique syntax than the 3.0 function, it’s similarly easy to use. Let’s turn to some basic examples again. By default, the 2.6 print statement adds a space between the items separated by commas and adds a line break at the end of the current output line:

C:\misc> c:\python26\python
>>>
>>> x = 'a'
>>> y = 'b'
>>> print x, y
a b

This formatting is just a default; you can choose to use it or not. To suppress the line break so you can add more text to the current line later, end your print statement with a comma, as shown in the second line of Table 11-5 (the following is two statements on one line, separated by a semicolon):

>>> print x, y,; print x, y
a b a b

To suppress the space between items, again, don’t print this way. Instead, build up an output string using the string concatenation and formatting tools covered in Chapter 7, and print the string all at once:

>>> print x + y
ab
>>> print '%s...%s' % (x, y)
a...b

As you can see, apart from their special syntax for usage modes, 2.6 print statements are roughly as simple to use as 3.0’s function. The next section uncovers the way that files are specified in 2.6 prints.

Print Stream Redirection

In both Python 3.0 and 2.6, printing sends text to the standard output stream by default. However, it’s often useful to send it elsewhere—to a text file, for example, to save results for later use or testing purposes. Although such redirection can be accomplished in system shells outside Python itself, it turns out to be just as easy to redirect a script’s streams from within the script.

The Python “hello world” program

Let’s start off with the usual (and largely pointless) language benchmark—the “hello world” program. To print a “hello world” message in Python, simply print the string per your version’s print operation:

>>> print('hello world')               # Print a string object in 3.0
hello world

>>> print 'hello world'                # Print a string object in 2.6
hello world

Because expression results are echoed on the interactive command line, you often don’t even need to use a print statement there—simply type the expressions you’d like to have printed, and their results are echoed back:

>>> 'hello world'                      # Interactive echoes
'hello world'

This code isn’t exactly an earth-shattering piece of software mastery, but it serves to illustrate printing behavior. Really, the print operation is just an ergonomic feature of Python—it provides a simple interface to the sys.stdout object, with a bit of default formatting. In fact, if you enjoy working harder than you must, you can also code print operations this way:

>>> import sys                         # Printing the hard way
>>> sys.stdout.write('hello world\n')
hello world

This code explicitly calls the write method of sys.stdout—an attribute preset when Python starts up to an open file object connected to the output stream. The print operation hides most of those details, providing a simple tool for simple printing tasks.

Manual stream redirection

So, why did I just show you the hard way to print? The sys.stdout print equivalent turns out to be the basis of a common technique in Python. In general, print and sys.stdout are directly related as follows. This statement:

print(X, Y)                            # Or, in 2.6: print X, Y

is equivalent to the longer:

import sys
sys.stdout.write(str(X) + ' ' + str(Y) + '\n')

which manually performs a string conversion with str, adds a separator and newline with +, and calls the output stream’s write method. Which would you rather code? (He says, hoping to underscore the programmer-friendly nature of prints....)

Obviously, the long form isn’t all that useful for printing by itself. However, it is useful to know that this is exactly what print operations do because it is possible to reassign sys.stdout to something different from the standard output stream. In other words, this equivalence provides a way of making your print operations send their text to other places. For example:

import sys
sys.stdout = open('log.txt', 'a')       # Redirects prints to a file
...
print(x, y, x)                          # Shows up in log.txt

Here, we reset sys.stdout to a manually opened file named log.txt, located in the script’s working directory and opened in append mode (so we add to its current content). After the reset, every print operation anywhere in the program will write its text to the end of the file log.txt instead of to the original output stream. The print operations are happy to keep calling sys.stdout’s write method, no matter what sys.stdout happens to refer to. Because there is just one sys module in your process, assigning sys.stdout this way will redirect every print anywhere in your program.

In fact, as this chapter’s upcoming sidebar about print and stdout will explain, you can even reset sys.stdout to an object that isn’t a file at all, as long as it has the expected interface: a method named write to receive the printed text string argument. When that object is a class, printed text can be routed and processed arbitrarily per a write method you code yourself.

This trick of resetting the output stream is primarily useful for programs originally coded with print statements. If you know that output should go to a file to begin with, you can always call file write methods instead. To redirect the output of a print-based program, though, resetting sys.stdout provides a convenient alternative to changing every print statement or using system shell-based redirection syntax.

Automatic stream redirection

This technique of redirecting printed text by assigning sys.stdout is commonly used in practice. One potential problem with the last section’s code, though, is that there is no direct way to restore the original output stream should you need to switch back after printing to a file. Because sys.stdout is just a normal file object, you can always save it and restore it if needed:[30]

C:\misc> c:\python30\python
>>> import sys
>>> temp = sys.stdout                   # Save for restoring later
>>> sys.stdout = open('log.txt', 'a')   # Redirect prints to a file
>>> print('spam')                       # Prints go to file, not here
>>> print(1, 2, 3)
>>> sys.stdout.close()                  # Flush output to disk
>>> sys.stdout = temp                   # Restore original stream

>>> print('back here')                  # Prints show up here again
back here
>>> print(open('log.txt').read())       # Result of earlier prints
spam
1 2 3

As you can see, though, manual saving and restoring of the original output stream like this involves quite a bit of extra work. Because this crops up fairly often, a print extension is available to make it unnecessary.

In 3.0, the file keyword allows a single print call to send its text to a file’s write method, without actually resetting sys.stdout. Because the redirection is temporary, normal print calls keep printing to the original output stream. In 2.6, a print statement that begins with a >> followed by an output file object (or other compatible object) has the same effect. For example, the following again sends printed text to a file named log.txt:

log =  open('log.txt', 'a')             # 3.0
print(x, y, z, file=log)                # Print to a file-like object
print(a, b, c)                          # Print to original stdout

log =  open('log.txt', 'a')             # 2.6
print >> log, x, y, z                   # Print to a file-like object
print a, b, c                           # Print to original stdout

These redirected forms of print are handy if you need to print to both files and the standard output stream in the same program. If you use these forms, however, be sure to give them a file object (or an object that has the same write method as a file object), not a file’s name string. Here is the technique in action:

C:\misc> c:\python30\python
>>> log = open('log.txt', 'w')
>>> print(1, 2, 3, file=log)            # 2.6: print >> log, 1, 2, 3
>>> print(4, 5, 6, file=log)
>>> log.close()
>>> print(7, 8, 9)                      # 2.6: print 7, 8, 9
7 8 9
>>> print(open('log.txt').read())
1 2 3
4 5 6

These extended forms of print are also commonly used to print error messages to the standard error stream, available to your script as the preopened file object sys.stderr. You can either use its file write methods and format the output manually, or print with redirection syntax:

>>> import sys
>>> sys.stderr.write(('Bad!' * 8) + '\n')
Bad!Bad!Bad!Bad!Bad!Bad!Bad!Bad!

>>> print('Bad!' * 8, file=sys.stderr)     # 2.6: print >> sys.stderr, 'Bad!' * 8
Bad!Bad!Bad!Bad!Bad!Bad!Bad!Bad!

Now that you know all about print redirections, the equivalence between printing and file write methods should be fairly obvious. The following interaction prints both ways in 3.0, then redirects the output to an external file to verify that the same text is printed:

>>> X = 1; Y = 2
>>> print(X, Y)                                            # Print: the easy way
1 2
>>> import sys                                             # Print: the hard way
>>> sys.stdout.write(str(X) + ' ' + str(Y) + '\n')
1 2
4
>>> print(X, Y, file=open('temp1', 'w'))                   # Redirect text to file

>>> open('temp2', 'w').write(str(X) + ' ' + str(Y) + '\n') # Send to file manually
4
>>> print(open('temp1', 'rb').read())                      # Binary mode for bytes
b'1 2\r\n'
>>> print(open('temp2', 'rb').read())
b'1 2\r\n'

As you can see, unless you happen to enjoy typing, print operations are usually the best option for displaying text. For another example of the equivalence between prints and file writes, watch for a 3.0 print function emulation example in Chapter 18; it uses this code pattern to provide a general 3.0 print function equivalent for use in Python 2.6.

Version-Neutral Printing

Finally, if you cannot restrict your work to Python 3.0 but still want your prints to be compatible with 3.0, you have some options. For one, you can code 2.6 print statements and let 3.0’s 2to3 conversion script translate them to 3.0 function calls automatically. See the Python 3.0 documentation for more details about this script; it attempts to translate 2.X code to run under 3.0.

Alternatively, you can code 3.0 print function calls in your 2.6 code, by enabling the function call variant with a statement like the following:

from __future__ import print_function

This statement changes 2.6 to support 3.0’s print functions exactly. This way, you can use 3.0 print features and won’t have to change your prints if you later migrate to 3.0.

Also keep in mind that simple prints, like those in the first row of Table 11-5, work in either version of Python—because any expression may be enclosed in parentheses, we can always pretend to be calling a 3.0 print function in 2.6 by adding outer parentheses. The only downside to this is that it makes a tuple out of your printed objects if there are more than one—they will print with extra enclosing parentheses. In 3.0, for example, any number of objects may be listed in the call’s parentheses:

C:\misc> c:\python30\python
>>> print('spam')                       # 3.0 print function call syntax
spam
>>> print('spam', 'ham', 'eggs')        # These are mutiple argments
spam ham eggs

The first of these works the same in 2.6, but the second generates a tuple in the output:

C:\misc> c:\python26\python
>>> print('spam')                       # 2.6 print statement, enclosing parens
spam
>>> print('spam', 'ham', 'eggs')        # This is really a tuple object!
('spam', 'ham', 'eggs')

To be truly portable, you can format the print string as a single object, using the string formatting expression or method call, or other string tools that we studied in Chapter 7:

>>> print('%s %s %s' % ('spam', 'ham', 'eggs'))
spam ham eggs
>>> print('{0} {1} {2}'.format('spam', 'ham', 'eggs'))
spam ham eggs

Of course, if you can use 3.0 exclusively you can forget such mappings entirely, but many Python programmers will at least encounter, if not write, 2.X code and systems for some time to come.

Note

I use Python 3.0 print function calls throughout this book. I’ll usually warn you that the results may have extra enclosing parentheses in 2.6 because multiple items are a tuple, but I sometimes don’t, so please consider this note a blanket warning—if you see extra parentheses in your printed text in 2.6, either drop the parentheses in your print statements, recode your prints using the version-neutral scheme outlined here, or learn to love superfluous text.

Why You Will Care: print and stdout

The equivalence between the print operation and writing to sys.stdout is important. It makes it possible to reassign sys.stdout to any user-defined object that provides the same write method as files. Because the print statement just sends text to the sys.stdout.write method, you can capture printed text in your programs by assigning sys.stdout to an object whose write method processes the text in arbitrary ways.

For instance, you can send printed text to a GUI window, or tee it off to multiple destinations, by defining an object with a write method that does the required routing. You’ll see an example of this trick when we study classes in Part VI of this book, but abstractly, it looks like this:

class FileFaker:
    def write(self, string):
        # Do something with printed text in string

import sys
sys.stdout = FileFaker()
print(someObjects)              # Sends to class write method

This works because print is what we will call in the next part of this book a polymorphic operation—it doesn’t care what sys.stdout is, only that it has a method (i.e., interface) called write. This redirection to objects is made even simpler with the file keyword argument in 3.0 and the >> extended form of print in 2.6, because we don’t need to reset sys.stdout explicitly—normal prints will still be routed to the stdout stream:

myobj = FileFaker()             # 3.0: Redirect to object for one print
print(someObjects, file=myobj)  # Does not reset sys.stdout

myobj = FileFaker()             # 2.6: same effect
print >> myobj, someObjects     # Does not reset sys.stdout

Python’s built-in input function reads from the sys.stdin file, so you can intercept read requests in a similar way, using classes that implement file-like read methods instead. See the input and while loop example in Chapter 10 for more background on this.

Notice that because printed text goes to the stdout stream, it’s the way to print HTML in CGI scripts used on the Web. It also enables you to redirect Python script input and output at the operating system’s shell command line, as usual:

python script.py < inputfile > outputfile
python script.py | filterProgram

Python’s print operation redirection tools are essentially pure-Python alternatives to these shell syntax forms.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

You can use multiple-target assignments (A = B = C = 0), sequence assignment (A, B, C = 0, 0, 0), or multiple assignment statements on three separate lines (A = 0, B = 0, and C = 0). With the latter technique, as introduced in Chapter 10, you can also string the three separate statements together on the same line by separating them with semicolons (A = 0; B = 0; C = 0).

If you assign them this way:

A = B = C = []

all three names reference the same object, so changing it in-place from one (e.g., A.append(99)) will affect the others. This is true only for in-place changes to mutable objects like lists and dictionaries; for immutable objects such as numbers and strings, this issue is irrelevant.

The list sort method is like append in that it makes an in-place change to the subject list—it returns None, not the list it changes. The assignment back to L sets L to None, not to the sorted list. As we’ll see later in this part of the book, a newer built-in function, sorted, sorts any sequence and returns a new list with the sorting result; because this is not an in-place change, its result can be meaningfully assigned to a name.

To print to a file for a single print operation, you can use 3.0’s print(X, file=F) call form, use 2.6’s extended print >> file, X statement form, or assign sys.stdout to a manually opened file before the print and restore the original after. You can also redirect all of a program’s printed text to a file with special syntax in the system shell, but this is outside Python’s scope.

[25] C/C++ programmers take note: although Python now supports statements like X += Y, it still does not have C’s auto-increment/decrement operators (e.g., X++, −−X). These don’t quite map to the Python object model because Python has no notion of in-place changes to immutable objects like numbers.

[26] As suggested in Chapter 6, we can also use slice assignment (e.g., L[len(L):] = [11,12,13]), but this works roughly the same as the simpler list extend method.

[27] In the Jython Java-based implementation of Python, though, user-defined variable names can sometimes be the same as Python reserved words. See Chapter 2 for an overview of the Jython system.

[28] If you’ve used a more restrictive language like C++, you may be interested to know that there is no notion of C++’s const declaration in Python; certain objects may be immutable, but names can always be assigned. Python also has ways to hide names in classes and modules, but they’re not the same as C++’s declarations (if hiding attributes matters to you, see the coverage of _X module names in Chapter 24, __X class names in Chapter 30, and the Private and Public class decorators example in Chapter 38).

[29] Technically, printing uses the equivalent of str in the internal implementation of Python, but the effect is the same. Besides this to-string conversion role, str is also the name of the string data type and can be used to decode Unicode strings from raw bytes with an extra encoding argument, as we’ll learn in Chapter 36; this latter role is an advanced usage that we can safely ignore here.

[30] In both 2.6 and 3.0 you may also be able to use the __stdout__ attribute in the sys module, which refers to the original value sys.stdout had at program startup time. You still need to restore sys.stdout to sys.__stdout__ to go back to this original stream value, though. See the sys module documentation for more details.

if Statements

In simple terms, the Python if statement selects actions to perform. It’s the primary selection tool in Python and represents much of the logic a Python program possesses. It’s also our first compound statement. Like all compound Python statements, the if statement may contain other statements, including other ifs. In fact, Python lets you combine statements in a program sequentially (so that they execute one after another), and in an arbitrarily nested fashion (so that they execute only under certain conditions).

General Format

The Python if statement is typical of if statements in most procedural languages. It takes the form of an if test, followed by one or more optional elif (“else if”) tests and a final optional else block. The tests and the else part each have an associated block of nested statements, indented under a header line. When the if statement runs, Python executes the block of code associated with the first test that evaluates to true, or the else block if all tests prove false. The general form of an if statement looks like this:

if <test1>:               # if test
    <statements1>         # Associated block
elif <test2>:             # Optional elifs
    <statements2>
else:                     # Optional else
    <statements3>

Basic Examples

To demonstrate, let’s look at a few simple examples of the if statement at work. All parts are optional, except the initial if test and its associated statements. Thus, in the simplest case, the other parts are omitted:

>>> if 1:
...     print('true')
...
true

Notice how the prompt changes to ... for continuation lines when typing interactively in the basic interface used here; in IDLE, you’ll simply drop down to an indented line instead (hit Backspace to back up). A blank line (which you can get by pressing Enter twice) terminates and runs the entire statement. Remember that 1 is Boolean true, so this statement’s test always succeeds. To handle a false result, code the else:

>>> if not 1:
...     print('true')
... else:
...     print('false')
...
false

Multiway Branching

Now here’s an example of a more complex if statement, with all its optional parts present:

>>> x = 'killer rabbit'
>>> if x == 'roger':
...     print("how's jessica?")
... elif x == 'bugs':
...     print("what's up doc?")
... else:
...     print('Run away! Run away!')
...
Run away! Run away!

This multiline statement extends from the if line through the else block. When it’s run, Python executes the statements nested under the first test that is true, or the else part if all tests are false (in this example, they are). In practice, both the elif and else parts may be omitted, and there may be more than one statement nested in each section. Note that the words if, elif, and else are associated by the fact that they line up vertically, with the same indentation.

If you’ve used languages like C or Pascal, you might be interested to know that there is no switch or case statement in Python that selects an action based on a variable’s value. Instead, multiway branching is coded either as a series of if/elif tests, as in the prior example, or by indexing dictionaries or searching lists. Because dictionaries and lists can be built at runtime, they’re sometimes more flexible than hardcoded if logic:

>>> choice = 'ham'
>>> print({'spam':  1.25,         # A dictionary-based 'switch'
...        'ham':   1.99,         # Use has_key or get for default
...        'eggs':  0.99,
...        'bacon': 1.10}[choice])
1.99

Although it may take a few moments for this to sink in the first time you see it, this dictionary is a multiway branch—indexing on the key choice branches to one of a set of values, much like a switch in C. An almost equivalent but more verbose Python if statement might look like this:

>>> if choice == 'spam':
...     print(1.25)
... elif choice == 'ham':
...     print(1.99)
... elif choice == 'eggs':
...     print(0.99)
... elif choice == 'bacon':
...     print(1.10)
... else:
...     print('Bad choice')
...
1.99

Notice the else clause on the if here to handle the default case when no key matches. As we saw in Chapter 8, dictionary defaults can be coded with in expressions, get method calls, or exception catching. All of the same techniques can be used here to code a default action in a dictionary-based multiway branch. Here’s the get scheme at work with defaults:

>>> branch = {'spam': 1.25,
...           'ham':  1.99,
...           'eggs': 0.99}

>>> print(branch.get('spam', 'Bad choice'))
1.25
>>> print(branch.get('bacon', 'Bad choice'))
Bad choice

An in membership test in an if statement can have the same default effect:

>>> choice = 'bacon'
>>> if choice in branch:
...     print(branch[choice])
... else:
...     print('Bad choice')
...
Bad choice

Dictionaries are good for associating values with keys, but what about the more complicated actions you can code in the statement blocks associated with if statements? In Part IV, you’ll learn that dictionaries can also contain functions to represent more complex branch actions and implement general jump tables. Such functions appear as dictionary values, may be coded as function names or lambdas, and are called by adding parentheses to trigger their actions; stay tuned for more on this topic in Chapter 19.

Although dictionary-based multiway branching is useful in programs that deal with more dynamic data, most programmers will probably find that coding an if statement is the most straightforward way to perform multiway branching. As a rule of thumb in coding, when in doubt, err on the side of simplicity and readability; it’s the “Pythonic” way.

Truth Tests

The notions of comparison, equality, and truth values were introduced in Chapter 9. Because the if statement is the first statement we’ve looked at that actually uses test results, we’ll expand on some of these ideas here. In particular, Python’s Boolean operators are a bit different from their counterparts in languages like C. In Python:

Any nonzero number or nonempty object is true.

Zero numbers, empty objects, and the special object None are considered false.

Comparisons and equality tests are applied recursively to data structures.

Comparisons and equality tests return True or False (custom versions of 1 and 0).

Boolean and and or operators return a true or false operand object.

In short, Boolean operators are used to combine the results of other tests. There are three Boolean expression operators in Python:

X and Y

Is true if both X and Y are true

X or Y

Is true if either X or Y is true

not X

Is true if X is false (the expression returns True or False)

Here, X and Y may be any truth value, or any expression that returns a truth value (e.g., an equality test, range comparison, and so on). Boolean operators are typed out as words in Python (instead of C’s &&, ||, and !). Also, Boolean and and or operators return a true or false object in Python, not the values True or False. Let’s look at a few examples to see how this works:

>>> 2 < 3, 3 < 2        # Less-than: return True or False (1 or 0)
(True, False)

Magnitude comparisons such as these return True or False as their truth results, which, as we learned in Chapters 5 and 9, are really just custom versions of the integers 1 and 0 (they print themselves differently but are otherwise the same).

On the other hand, the and and or operators always return an object—either the object on the left side of the operator or the object on the right. If we test their results in if or other statements, they will be as expected (remember, every object is inherently true or false), but we won’t get back a simple True or False.

For or tests, Python evaluates the operand objects from left to right and returns the first one that is true. Moreover, Python stops at the first true operand it finds. This is usually called short-circuit evaluation, as determining a result short-circuits (terminates) the rest of the expression:

>>> 2 or 3, 3 or 2      # Return left operand if true
(2, 3)                  # Else, return right operand (true or false)
>>> [] or 3
3
>>> [] or {}
{}

In the first line of the preceding example, both operands (2 and 3) are true (i.e., are nonzero), so Python always stops and returns the one on the left. In the other two tests, the left operand is false (an empty object), so Python simply evaluates and returns the object on the right (which may happen to have either a true or a false value when tested).

and operations also stop as soon as the result is known; however, in this case Python evaluates the operands from left to right and stops at the first false object:

>>> 2 and 3, 3 and 2    # Return left operand if false
(3, 2)                  # Else, return right operand (true or false)
>>> [] and {}
[]
>>> 3 and []
[]

Here, both operands are true in the first line, so Python evaluates both sides and returns the object on the right. In the second test, the left operand is false ([]), so Python stops and returns it as the test result. In the last test, the left side is true (3), so Python evaluates and returns the object on the right (which happens to be a false []).

The end result of all this is the same as in C and most other languages—you get a value that is logically true or false if tested in an if or while. However, in Python Booleans return either the left or the right object, not a simple integer flag.

This behavior of and and or may seem esoteric at first glance, but see this chapter’s sidebar Why You Will Care: Booleans for examples of how it is sometimes used to advantage in coding by Python programmers. The next section also shows a common way to leverage this behavior, and its replacement in more recent versions of Python.

The if/else Ternary Expression

One common role for the prior section’s Boolean operators is to code an expression that runs the same as an if statement. Consider the following statement, which sets A to either Y or Z, based on the truth value of X:

if X:
    A = Y
else:
    A = Z

Sometimes, though, the items involved in such a statement are so simple that it seems like overkill to spread them across four lines. At other times, we may want to nest such a construct in a larger statement instead of assigning its result to a variable. For these reasons (and, frankly, because the C language has a similar tool[32]), Python 2.5 introduced a new expression format that allows us to say the same thing in one expression:

A = Y if X else Z

This expression has the exact same effect as the preceding four-line if statement, but it’s simpler to code. As in the statement equivalent, Python runs expression Y only if X turns out to be true, and runs expression Z only if X turns out to be false. That is, it short-circuits, just like the Boolean operators described in the prior section. Here are some examples of it in action:

>>> A = 't' if 'spam' else 'f'      # Nonempty is true
>>> A
't'
>>> A = 't' if '' else 'f'
>>> A
'f'

Prior to Python 2.5 (and after 2.5, if you insist), the same effect can often be achieved by a careful combination of the and and or operators, because they return either the object on the left side or the object on the right:

A = ((X and Y) or Z)

This works, but there is a catch—you have to be able to assume that Y will be Boolean true. If that is the case, the effect is the same: the and runs first and returns Y if X is true; if it’s not, the or simply returns Z. In other words, we get “if X then Y else Z.”

This and/or combination also seems to require a “moment of great clarity” to understand the first time you see it, and it’s no longer required as of 2.5—use the equivalent and more robust and mnemonic Y if X else Z instead if you need this as an expression, or use a full if statement if the parts are nontrivial.

As a side note, using the following expression in Python is similar because the bool function will translate X into the equivalent of integer 1 or 0, which can then be used to pick true and false values from a list:

A = [Z, Y][bool(X)]

For example:

>>> ['f', 't'][bool('')]
'f'
>>> ['f', 't'][bool('spam')]
't'

However, this isn’t exactly the same, because Python will not short-circuit—it will always run both Z and Y, regardless of the value of X. Because of such complexities, you’re better off using the simpler and more easily understood if/else expression as of Python 2.5 and later. Again, though, you should use even that sparingly, and only if its parts are all fairly simple; otherwise, you’re better off coding the full if statement form to make changes easier in the future. Your coworkers will be happy you did.

Still, you may see the and/or version in code written prior to 2.5 (and in code written by C programmers who haven’t quite let go of their dark coding pasts...).

Why You Will Care: Booleans

One common way to use the somewhat unusual behavior of Python Boolean operators is to select from a set of objects with an or. A statement such as this:

X = A or B or C or None

sets X to the first nonempty (that is, true) object among A, B, and C, or to None if all of them are empty. This works because the or operator returns one of its two objects, and it turns out to be a fairly common coding paradigm in Python: to select a nonempty object from among a fixed-size set, simply string them together in an or expression. In simpler form, this is also commonly used to designate a default—the following sets X to A if A is true (or nonempty), and to default otherwise:

X = A or default

It’s also important to understand short-circuit evaluation because expressions on the right of a Boolean operator might call functions that perform substantial or important work, or have side effects that won’t happen if the short-circuit rule takes effect:

if f1() or f2(): ...

Here, if f1 returns a true (or nonempty) value, Python will never run f2. To guarantee that both functions will be run, call them before the or:

tmp1, tmp2 = f1(), f2()
if tmp1 or tmp2: ...

You’ve already seen another application of this behavior in this chapter: because of the way Booleans work, the expression ((A and B) or C) can be used to emulate an if/else statement—almost (see this chapter’s discussion of this form for details).

We met additional Boolean use cases in prior chapters. As we saw in Chapter 9, because all objects are inherently true or false, it’s common and easier in Python to test an object directly (if X:) than to compare it to an empty value (if X != '':). For a string, the two tests are equivalent. As we also saw in Chapter 5, the preset Booleans values True and False are the same as the integers 1 and 0 and are useful for initializing variables (X = False), for loop tests (while True:), and for displaying results at the interactive prompt.

Also watch for the discussion of operator overloading in Part VI: when we define new object types with classes, we can specify their Boolean nature with either the __bool__ or __len__ methods (__bool__ is named __nonzero__ in 2.6). The latter of these is tried if the former is absent and designates false by returning a length of zero—an empty object is considered false.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

An if statement with multiple elif clauses is often the most straightforward way to code a multiway branch, though not necessarily the most concise. Dictionary indexing can often achieve the same result, especially if the dictionary contains callable functions coded with def statements or lambda expressions.

In Python 2.5 and later, the expression form Y if X else Z returns Y if X is true, or Z otherwise; it’s the same as a four-line if statement. The and/or combination (((X and Y) or Z)) can work the same way, but it’s more obscure and requires that the Y part be true.

Wrap up the statement in an open syntactic pair ((), [], or {}), and it can span as many lines as you like; the statement ends when Python sees the closing (right) half of the pair, and lines 2 and beyond of the statement can begin at any indentation level.

True and False are just custom versions of the integers 1 and 0, respectively: they always stand for Boolean true and false values in Python. They’re available for use in truth tests and variable initialization and are printed for expression results at the interactive prompt.

[31] Frankly, it’s surprising that this wasn’t removed in Python 3.0, given some of its other changes! (See Table 2 of the Preface for a list of 3.0 removals; some seem fairly innocuous in comparison with the dangers inherent in backslash continuations.) Then again, this book’s goal is Python instruction, not populist outrage, so the best advice I can give is simply: don’t do this.

[32] In fact, Python’s X if Y else Z has a slightly different order than C’s Y ? X : Z. This was reportedly done in response to analysis of common use patterns in Python code. According to rumor, this order was also chosen in part to discourage ex-C programmers from overusing it! Remember, simple is better than complex, in Python and elsewhere.

Chapter 13. while and for Loops

This chapter concludes our tour of Python procedural statements by presenting the language’s two main looping constructs—statements that repeat an action over and over. The first of these, the while statement, provides a way to code general loops. The second, the for statement, is designed for stepping through the items in a sequence object and running a block of code for each.

We’ve seen both of these informally already, but we’ll fill in additional usage details here. While we’re at it, we’ll also study a few less prominent statements used within loops, such as break and continue, and cover some built-ins commonly used with loops, such as range, zip, and map.

Although the while and for statements covered here are the primary syntax provided for coding repeated actions, there are additional looping operations and concepts in Python. Because of that, the iteration story is continued in the next chapter, where we’ll explore the related ideas of Python’s iteration protocol (used by the for loop) and list comprehensions (a close cousin to the for loop). Later chapters explore even more exotic iteration tools such as generators, filter, and reduce. For now, though, let’s keep things simple.

while Loops

Python’s while statement is the most general iteration construct in the language. In simple terms, it repeatedly executes a block of (normally indented) statements as long as a test at the top keeps evaluating to a true value. It is called a “loop” because control keeps looping back to the start of the statement until the test becomes false. When the test becomes false, control passes to the statement that follows the while block. The net effect is that the loop’s body is executed repeatedly while the test at the top is true; if the test is false to begin with, the body never runs.

General Format

In its most complex form, the while statement consists of a header line with a test expression, a body of one or more indented statements, and an optional else part that is executed if control exits the loop without a break statement being encountered. Python keeps evaluating the test at the top and executing the statements nested in the loop body until the test returns a false value:

while <test>:                   # Loop test
    <statements1>               # Loop body
else:                           # Optional else
    <statements2>               # Run if didn't exit loop with break

Examples

To illustrate, let’s look at a few simple while loops in action. The first, which consists of a print statement nested in a while loop, just prints a message forever. Recall that True is just a custom version of the integer 1 and always stands for a Boolean true value; because the test is always true, Python keeps executing the body forever, or until you stop its execution. This sort of behavior is usually called an infinite loop:

>>> while True:
...    print('Type Ctrl-C to stop me!')

The next example keeps slicing off the first character of a string until the string is empty and hence false. It’s typical to test an object directly like this instead of using the more verbose equivalent (while x != '':). Later in this chapter, we’ll see other ways to step more directly through the items in a string with a for loop.

>>> x = 'spam'
>>> while x:                  # While x is not empty
...     print(x, end=' ')
...     x = x[1:]             # Strip first character off x
...
spam pam am m

Note the end=' ' keyword argument used here to place all outputs on the same line separated by a space; see Chapter 11 if you’ve forgotten why this works as it does. The following code counts from the value of a up to, but not including, b. We’ll see an easier way to do this with a Python for loop and the built-in range function later:

>>> a=0; b=10
>>> while a < b:              # One way to code counter loops
...     print(a, end=' ')
...     a += 1                # Or, a = a + 1
...
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9

Finally, notice that Python doesn’t have what some languages call a “do until” loop statement. However, we can simulate one with a test and break at the bottom of the loop body:

while True:
    ...loop body...
    if exitTest(): break

To fully understand how this structure works, we need to move on to the next section and learn more about the break statement.

break, continue, pass, and the Loop else

Now that we’ve seen a few Python loops in action, it’s time to take a look at two simple statements that have a purpose only when nested inside loops—the break and continue statements. While we’re looking at oddballs, we will also study the loop else clause here, because it is intertwined with break, and Python’s empty placeholder statement, the pass (which is not tied to loops per se, but falls into the general category of simple one-word statements). In Python:

break

Jumps out of the closest enclosing loop (past the entire loop statement)

continue

Jumps to the top of the closest enclosing loop (to the loop’s header line)

pass

Does nothing at all: it’s an empty statement placeholder

Loop else block

Runs if and only if the loop is exited normally (i.e., without hitting a break)

General Loop Format

Factoring in break and continue statements, the general format of the while loop looks like this:

while <test1>:
    <statements1>
    if <test2>: break              # Exit loop now, skip else
    if <test3>: continue           # Go to top of loop now, to test1
else:
    <statements2>                  # Run if we didn't hit a 'break'

break and continue statements can appear anywhere inside the while (or for) loop’s body, but they are usually coded further nested in an if test to take action in response to some condition.

Let’s turn to a few simple examples to see how these statements come together in practice.

pass

Simple things first: the pass statement is a no-operation placeholder that is used when the syntax requires a statement, but you have nothing useful to say. It is often used to code an empty body for a compound statement. For instance, if you want to code an infinite loop that does nothing each time through, do it with a pass:

while True: pass                   # Type Ctrl-C to stop me!

Because the body is just an empty statement, Python gets stuck in this loop. pass is roughly to statements as None is to objects—an explicit nothing. Notice that here the while loop’s body is on the same line as the header, after the colon; as with if statements, this only works if the body isn’t a compound statement.

This example does nothing forever. It probably isn’t the most useful Python program ever written (unless you want to warm up your laptop computer on a cold winter’s day!); frankly, though, I couldn’t think of a better pass example at this point in the book.

We’ll see other places where pass makes more sense later—for instance, to ignore exceptions caught by try statements, and to define empty class objects with attributes that behave like “structs” and “records” in other languages. A pass is also sometimes coded to mean “to be filled in later,” to stub out the bodies of functions temporarily:

def func1():
    pass                           # Add real code here later

def func2():
    pass

We can’t leave the body empty without getting a syntax error, so we say pass instead.

Note

Version skew note: Python 3.0 (but not 2.6) allows ellipses coded as ... (literally, three consecutive dots) to appear any place an expression can. Because ellipses do nothing by themselves, this can serve as an alternative to the pass statement, especially for code to be filled in later—a sort of Python “TBD”:

def func1():
    ...                   # Alternative to pass

def func2():
    ...

func1()                   # Does nothing if called

Ellipses can also appear on the same line as a statement header and may be used to initialize variable names if no specific type is required:

def func1(): ...          # Works on same line too
def func2(): ...

>>> X = ...               # Alternative to None
>>> X
Ellipsis

This notation is new in Python 3.0 (and goes well beyond the original intent of ... in slicing extensions), so time will tell if it becomes widespread enough to challenge pass and None in these roles.

continue

The continue statement causes an immediate jump to the top of a loop. It also sometimes lets you avoid statement nesting. The next example uses continue to skip odd numbers. This code prints all even numbers less than 10 and greater than or equal to 0. Remember, 0 means false and % is the remainder of division operator, so this loop counts down to 0, skipping numbers that aren’t multiples of 2 (it prints 8 6 4 2 0):

x = 10
while x:
    x = x−1                        # Or, x -= 1
    if x % 2 != 0: continue        # Odd? -- skip print
    print(x, end=' ')

Because continue jumps to the top of the loop, you don’t need to nest the print statement inside an if test; the print is only reached if the continue is not run. If this sounds similar to a “goto” in other languages, it should. Python has no “goto” statement, but because continue lets you jump about in a program, many of the warnings about readability and maintainability you may have heard about goto apply. continue should probably be used sparingly, especially when you’re first getting started with Python. For instance, the last example might be clearer if the print were nested under the if:

x = 10
while x:
    x = x−1
    if x % 2 == 0:                 # Even? -- print
        print(x, end=' ')

break

The break statement causes an immediate exit from a loop. Because the code that follows it in the loop is not executed if the break is reached, you can also sometimes avoid nesting by including a break. For example, here is a simple interactive loop (a variant of a larger example we studied in Chapter 10) that inputs data with input (known as raw_input in Python 2.6) and exits when the user enters “stop” for the name request:

>>> while True:
...     name = input('Enter name:')
...     if name == 'stop': break
...     age  = input('Enter age: ')
...     print('Hello', name, '=>', int(age) ** 2)
...
Enter name:mel
Enter age: 40
Hello mel => 1600
Enter name:bob
Enter age: 30
Hello bob => 900
Enter name:stop

Notice how this code converts the age input to an integer with int before raising it to the second power; as you’ll recall, this is necessary because input returns user input as a string. In Chapter 35, you’ll see that input also raises an exception at end-of-file (e.g., if the user types Ctrl-Z or Ctrl-D); if this matters, wrap input in try statements.

Loop else

When combined with the loop else clause, the break statement can often eliminate the need for the search status flags used in other languages. For instance, the following piece of code determines whether a positive integer y is prime by searching for factors greater than 1:

x = y // 2                                # For some y > 1
while x > 1:
    if y % x == 0:                        # Remainder
        print(y, 'has factor', x)
        break                             # Skip else
    x -= 1
else:                                     # Normal exit
    print(y, 'is prime')

Rather than setting a flag to be tested when the loop is exited, it inserts a break where a factor is found. This way, the loop else clause can assume that it will be executed only if no factor is found; if you don’t hit the break, the number is prime.

The loop else clause is also run if the body of the loop is never executed, as you don’t run a break in that event either; in a while loop, this happens if the test in the header is false to begin with. Thus, in the preceding example you still get the “is prime” message if x is initially less than or equal to 1 (for instance, if y is 2).

Note

This example determines primes, but only informally so. Numbers less than 2 are not considered prime by the strict mathematical definition. To be really picky, this code also fails for negative numbers and succeeds for floating-point numbers with no decimal digits. Also note that its code must use // instead of / in Python 3.0 because of the migration of / to “true division,” as described in Chapter 5 (we need the initial division to truncate remainders, not retain them!). If you want to experiment with this code, be sure to see the exercise at the end of Part IV, which wraps it in a function for reuse.

More on the loop else

Because the loop else clause is unique to Python, it tends to perplex some newcomers. In general terms, the loop else provides explicit syntax for a common coding scenario—it is a coding structure that lets us catch the “other” way out of a loop, without setting and checking flags or conditions.

Suppose, for instance, that we are writing a loop to search a list for a value, and we need to know whether the value was found after we exit the loop. We might code such a task this way (this code is intentionally abstract and incomplete; x is a sequence and match() is a tester function to be defined):

found = False
while x and not found:
    if match(x[0]):                  # Value at front?
        print('Ni')
        found = True
    else:
        x = x[1:]                    # Slice off front and repeat
if not found:
    print('not found')

Here, we initialize, set, and later test a flag to determine whether the search succeeded or not. This is valid Python code, and it does work; however, this is exactly the sort of structure that the loop else clause is there to handle. Here’s an else equivalent:

while x:                             # Exit when x empty
    if match(x[0]):
        print('Ni')
        break                        # Exit, go around else
    x = x[1:]
else:
    print('Not found')               # Only here if exhausted x

This version is more concise. The flag is gone, and we’ve replaced the if test at the loop end with an else (lined up vertically with the word while). Because the break inside the main part of the while exits the loop and goes around the else, this serves as a more structured way to catch the search-failure case.

Some readers might have noticed that the prior example’s else clause could be replaced with a test for an empty x after the loop (e.g., if not x:). Although that’s true in this example, the else provides explicit syntax for this coding pattern (it’s more obviously a search-failure clause here), and such an explicit empty test may not apply in some cases. The loop else becomes even more useful when used in conjunction with the for loop—the topic of the next section—because sequence iteration is not under your control.

Why You Will Care: Emulating C while Loops

The section on expression statements in Chapter 11 stated that Python doesn’t allow statements such as assignments to appear in places where it expects an expression. That means this common C language coding pattern won’t work in Python:

while ((x = next()) != NULL) {...process x...}

C assignments return the value assigned, but Python assignments are just statements, not expressions. This eliminates a notorious class of C errors (you can’t accidentally type = in Python when you mean ==). If you need similar behavior, though, there are at least three ways to get the same effect in Python while loops without embedding assignments in loop tests. You can move the assignment into the loop body with a break:

while True:
    x = next()
    if not x: break
    ...process x...

or move the assignment into the loop with tests:

x = True
while x:
    x = next()
    if x:
        ...process x...

or move the first assignment outside the loop:

x = next()
while x:
    ...process x...
    x = next()

Of these three coding patterns, the first may be considered by some to be the least structured, but it also seems to be the simplest and is the most commonly used. A simple Python for loop may replace some C loops as well.

for Loops

The for loop is a generic sequence iterator in Python: it can step through the items in any ordered sequence object. The for statement works on strings, lists, tuples, other built-in iterables, and new objects that we’ll see how to create later with classes. We met it in brief when studying sequence object types; let’s expand on its usage more formally here.

General Format

The Python for loop begins with a header line that specifies an assignment target (or targets), along with the object you want to step through. The header is followed by a block of (normally indented) statements that you want to repeat:

for <target> in <object>:             # Assign object items to target
    <statements>                      # Repeated loop body: use target
else:
    <statements>                      # If we didn't hit a 'break'

When Python runs a for loop, it assigns the items in the sequence object to the target one by one and executes the loop body for each. The loop body typically uses the assignment target to refer to the current item in the sequence as though it were a cursor stepping through the sequence.

The name used as the assignment target in a for header line is usually a (possibly new) variable in the scope where the for statement is coded. There’s not much special about it; it can even be changed inside the loop’s body, but it will automatically be set to the next item in the sequence when control returns to the top of the loop again. After the loop this variable normally still refers to the last item visited, which is the last item in the sequence unless the loop exits with a break statement.

The for statement also supports an optional else block, which works exactly as it does in a while loop—it’s executed if the loop exits without running into a break statement (i.e., if all items in the sequence have been visited). The break and continue statements introduced earlier also work the same in a for loop as they do in a while. The for loop’s complete format can be described this way:

for <target> in <object>:             # Assign object items to target
    <statements>
    if <test>: break                  # Exit loop now, skip else
    if <test>: continue               # Go to top of loop now
else:
    <statements>                      # If we didn't hit a 'break'

Examples

Let’s type a few for loops interactively now, so you can see how they are used in practice.

Basic usage

As mentioned earlier, a for loop can step across any kind of sequence object. In our first example, for instance, we’ll assign the name x to each of the three items in a list in turn, from left to right, and the print statement will be executed for each. Inside the print statement (the loop body), the name x refers to the current item in the list:

>>> for x in ["spam", "eggs", "ham"]:
...     print(x, end=' ')
...
spam eggs ham

The next two examples compute the sum and product of all the items in a list. Later in this chapter and later in the book we’ll meet tools that apply operations such as + and * to items in a list automatically, but it’s usually just as easy to use a for:

>>> sum = 0
>>> for x in [1, 2, 3, 4]:
...     sum = sum + x
...
>>> sum
10
>>> prod = 1
>>> for item in [1, 2, 3, 4]: prod *= item
...
>>> prod
24

Other data types

Any sequence works in a for, as it’s a generic tool. For example, for loops work on strings and tuples:

>>> S = "lumberjack"
>>> T = ("and", "I'm", "okay")

>>> for x in S: print(x, end=' ')     # Iterate over a string
...
l u m b e r j a c k

>>> for x in T: print(x, end=' ')     # Iterate over a tuple
...
and I'm okay

In fact, as we’ll in the next chapter when we explore the notion of “iterables,” for loops can even work on some objects that are not sequences—files and dictionaries work, too!

Tuple assignment in for loops

If you’re iterating through a sequence of tuples, the loop target itself can actually be a tuple of targets. This is just another case of the tuple-unpacking assignment we studied in Chapter 11 at work. Remember, the for loop assigns items in the sequence object to the target, and assignment works the same everywhere:

>>> T = [(1, 2), (3, 4), (5, 6)]
>>> for (a, b) in T:                   # Tuple assignment at work
...     print(a, b)
...
1 2
3 4
5 6

Here, the first time through the loop is like writing (a,b) = (1,2), the second time is like writing (a,b) = (3,4), and so on. The net effect is to automatically unpack the current tuple on each iteration.

This form is commonly used in conjunction with the zip call we’ll meet later in this chapter to implement parallel traversals. It also makes regular appearances in conjunction with SQL databases in Python, where query result tables are returned as sequences of sequences like the list used here—the outer list is the database table, the nested tuples are the rows within the table, and tuple assignment extracts columns.

Tuples in for loops also come in handy to iterate through both keys and values in dictionaries using the items method, rather than looping through the keys and indexing to fetch the values manually:

>>> D = {'a': 1, 'b': 2, 'c': 3}
>>> for key in D:
...    print(key, '=>', D[key])             # Use dict keys iterator and index
...
a => 1
c => 3
b => 2

>>> list(D.items())
[('a', 1), ('c', 3), ('b', 2)]

>>> for (key, value) in D.items():
...    print(key, '=>', value)              # Iterate over both keys and values
...
a => 1
c => 3
b => 2

It’s important to note that tuple assignment in for loops isn’t a special case; any assignment target works syntactically after the word for. Although we can always assign manually within the loop to unpack:

>>> T
[(1, 2), (3, 4), (5, 6)]

>>> for both in T:
...     a, b = both                         # Manual assignment equivalent
...     print(a, b)
...
1 2
3 4
5 6

Tuples in the loop header save us an extra step when iterating through sequences of sequences. As suggested in Chapter 11, even nested structures may be automatically unpacked this way in a for:

>>> ((a, b), c) = ((1, 2), 3)               # Nested sequences work too
>>> a, b, c
(1, 2, 3)

>>> for ((a, b), c) in [((1, 2), 3), ((4, 5), 6)]: print(a, b, c)
...
1 2 3
4 5 6

But this is no special case—the for loop simply runs the sort of assignment we ran just before it, on each iteration. Any nested sequence structure may be unpacked this way, just because sequence assignment is so generic:

>>> for ((a, b), c) in [([1, 2], 3), ['XY', 6]]: print(a, b, c)
...
1 2 3
X Y 6

Python 3.0 extended sequence assignment in for loops

In fact, because the loop variable in a for loop can really be any assignment target, we can also use Python 3.0’s extended sequence-unpacking assignment syntax here to extract items and sections of sequences within sequences. Really, this isn’t a special case either, but simply a new assignment form in 3.0 (as discussed in Chapter 11); because it works in assignment statements, it automatically works in for loops.

Consider the tuple assignment form introduced in the prior section. A tuple of values is assigned to a tuple of names on each iteration, exactly like a simple assignment statement:

>>> a, b, c = (1, 2, 3)                               # Tuple assignment
>>> a, b, c
(1, 2, 3)

>>> for (a, b, c) in [(1, 2, 3), (4, 5, 6)]:          # Used in for loop
...     print(a, b, c)
...
1 2 3
4 5 6

In Python 3.0, because a sequence can be assigned to a more general set of names with a starred name to collect multiple items, we can use the same syntax to extract parts of nested sequences in the for loop:

>>> a, *b, c = (1, 2, 3, 4)                           # Extended seq assignment
>>> a, b, c
(1, [2, 3], 4)

>>> for (a, *b, c) in [(1, 2, 3, 4), (5, 6, 7, 8)]:
...     print(a, b, c)
...
1 [2, 3] 4
5 [6, 7] 8

In practice, this approach might be used to pick out multiple columns from rows of data represented as nested sequences. In Python 2.X starred names aren’t allowed, but you can achieve similar effects by slicing. The only difference is that slicing returns a type-specific result, whereas starred names always are assigned lists:

>>> for all in [(1, 2, 3, 4), (5, 6, 7, 8)]:          # Manual slicing in 2.6
...     a, b, c = all[0], all[1:3], all[3]
...     print(a, b, c)
...
1 (2, 3) 4
5 (6, 7) 8

See Chapter 11 for more on this assignment form.

Nested for loops

Now let’s look at a for loop that’s a bit more sophisticated than those we’ve seen so far. The next example illustrates statement nesting and the loop else clause in a for. Given a list of objects (items) and a list of keys (tests), this code searches for each key in the objects list and reports on the search’s outcome:

>>> items = ["aaa", 111, (4, 5), 2.01]   # A set of objects
>>> tests = [(4, 5), 3.14]               # Keys to search for
>>>
>>> for key in tests:                    # For all keys
...     for item in items:               # For all items
...         if item == key:              # Check for match
...             print(key, "was found")
...             break
...     else:
...         print(key, "not found!")
...
(4, 5) was found
3.14 not found!

Because the nested if runs a break when a match is found, the loop else clause can assume that if it is reached, the search has failed. Notice the nesting here. When this code runs, there are two loops going at the same time: the outer loop scans the keys list, and the inner loop scans the items list for each key. The nesting of the loop else clause is critical; it’s indented to the same level as the header line of the inner for loop, so it’s associated with the inner loop, not the if or the outer for.

Note that this example is easier to code if we employ the in operator to test membership. Because in implicitly scans an object looking for a match (at least logically), it replaces the inner loop:

>>> for key in tests:                    # For all keys
...     if key in items:                 # Let Python check for a match
...         print(key, "was found")
...     else:
...         print(key, "not found!")
...
(4, 5) was found
3.14 not found!

In general, it’s a good idea to let Python do as much of the work as possible (as in this solution) for the sake of brevity and performance.

The next example performs a typical data-structure task with a for—collecting common items in two sequences (strings). It’s roughly a simple set intersection routine; after the loop runs, res refers to a list that contains all the items found in seq1 and seq2:

>>> seq1 = "spam"
>>> seq2 = "scam"
>>>
>>> res = []                             # Start empty
>>> for x in seq1:                       # Scan first sequence
...     if x in seq2:                    # Common item?
...         res.append(x)                # Add to result end
...
>>> res
['s', 'a', 'm']

Unfortunately, this code is equipped to work only on two specific variables: seq1 and seq2. It would be nice if this loop could somehow be generalized into a tool you could use more than once. As you’ll see, that simple idea leads us to functions, the topic of the next part of the book.

Why You Will Care: File Scanners

In general, loops come in handy anywhere you need to repeat an operation or process something more than once. Because files contain multiple characters and lines, they are one of the more typical use cases for loops. To load a file’s contents into a string all at once, you simply call the file object’s read method:

file = open('test.txt', 'r')   # Read contents into a string
print(file.read())

But to load a file in smaller pieces, it’s common to code either a while loop with breaks on end-of-file, or a for loop. To read by characters, either of the following codings will suffice:

file = open('test.txt')
while True:
    char = file.read(1)         # Read by character
    if not char: break
    print(char)

for char in open('test.txt').read():
    print(char)

The for loop here also processes each character, but it loads the file into memory all at once (and assumes it fits!). To read by lines or blocks instead, you can use while loop code like this:

file = open('test.txt')
while True:
    line = file.readline()      # Read line by line
    if not line: break
    print(line, end='')         # Line already has a \n

file = open('test.txt', 'rb')
while True:
    chunk = file.read(10)       # Read byte chunks: up to 10 bytes
    if not chunk: break
    print(chunk)

You typically read binary data in blocks. To read text files line by line, though, the for loop tends to be easiest to code and the quickest to run:

for line in open('test.txt').readlines():
    print(line, end='')

for line in open('test.txt'):   # Use iterators: best text input mode
    print(line, end='')

The file readlines method loads a file all at once into a line-string list, and the last example here relies on file iterators to automatically read one line on each loop iteration (iterators are covered in detail in Chapter 14). See the library manual for more on the calls used here. The last example here is generally the best option for text files—besides its simplicity, it works for arbitrarily large files and doesn’t load the entire file into memory all at once. The iterator version may be the quickest, but I/O performance is less clear-cut in Python 3.0.

In some 2.X Python code, you may also see the name open replaced with file and the file object’s older xreadlines method used to achieve the same effect as the file’s automatic line iterator (it’s like readlines but doesn’t load the file into memory all at once). Both file and xreadlines are removed in Python 3.0, because they are redundant; you shouldn’t use them in 2.6 either, but they may pop up in older code and resources. Watch for more on reading files in Chapter 36; as we’ll see there, text and binary files have slightly different semantics in 3.0.

Loop Coding Techniques

The for loop subsumes most counter-style loops. It’s generally simpler to code and quicker to run than a while, so it’s the first tool you should reach for whenever you need to step through a sequence. But there are also situations where you will need to iterate in more specialized ways. For example, what if you need to visit every second or third item in a list, or change the list along the way? How about traversing more than one sequence in parallel, in the same for loop?

You can always code such unique iterations with a while loop and manual indexing, but Python provides two built-ins that allow you to specialize the iteration in a for:

The built-in range function produces a series of successively higher integers, which can be used as indexes in a for.

The built-in zip function returns a series of parallel-item tuples, which can be used to traverse multiple sequences in a for.

Because for loops typically run quicker than while-based counter loops, it’s to your advantage to use tools like these that allow you to use for when possible. Let’s look at each of these built-ins in turn.

Counter Loops: while and range

The range function is really a general tool that can be used in a variety of contexts. Although it’s used most often to generate indexes in a for, you can use it anywhere you need a list of integers. In Python 3.0, range is an iterator that generates items on demand, so we need to wrap it in a list call to display its results all at once (more on iterators in Chapter 14):

>>> list(range(5)), list(range(2, 5)), list(range(0, 10, 2))
([0, 1, 2, 3, 4], [2, 3, 4], [0, 2, 4, 6, 8])

With one argument, range generates a list of integers from zero up to but not including the argument’s value. If you pass in two arguments, the first is taken as the lower bound. An optional third argument can give a step; if it is used, Python adds the step to each successive integer in the result (the step defaults to 1). Ranges can also be nonpositive and nonascending, if you want them to be:

>>> list(range(−5, 5))
[−5, −4, −3, −2, −1, 0, 1, 2, 3, 4]

>>> list(range(5, −5, −1))
[5, 4, 3, 2, 1, 0, −1, −2, −3, −4]

Although such range results may be useful all by themselves, they tend to come in most handy within for loops. For one thing, they provide a simple way to repeat an action a specific number of times. To print three lines, for example, use a range to generate the appropriate number of integers; for loops force results from range automatically in 3.0, so we don’t need list here:

>>> for i in range(3):
...     print(i, 'Pythons')
...
0 Pythons
1 Pythons
2 Pythons

range is also commonly used to iterate over a sequence indirectly. The easiest and fastest way to step through a sequence exhaustively is always with a simple for, as Python handles most of the details for you:

>>> X = 'spam'
>>> for item in X: print(item, end=' ')           # Simple iteration
...
s p a m

Internally, the for loop handles the details of the iteration automatically when used this way. If you really need to take over the indexing logic explicitly, you can do it with a while loop:

>>> i = 0
>>> while i < len(X):                             # while loop iteration
...     print(X[i], end=' ')
...     i += 1
...
s p a m

You can also do manual indexing with a for, though, if you use range to generate a list of indexes to iterate through. It’s a multistep process, but it’s sufficient to generate offsets, rather than the items at those offsets:

>>> X
'spam'
>>> len(X)                                        # Length of string
4
>>> list(range(len(X)))                           # All legal offsets into X
[0, 1, 2, 3]
>>>
>>> for i in range(len(X)): print(X[i], end=' ')  # Manual for indexing
...
s p a m

Note that because this example is stepping over a list of offsets into X, not the actual items of X, we need to index back into X within the loop to fetch each item.

Nonexhaustive Traversals: range and Slices

The last example in the prior section works, but it’s not the fastest option. It’s also more work than we need to do. Unless you have a special indexing requirement, you’re always better off using the simple for loop form in Python—as a general rule, use for instead of while whenever possible, and don’t use range calls in for loops except as a last resort. This simpler solution is better:

>>> for item in X: print(item)                    # Simple iteration
...

However, the coding pattern used in the prior example does allow us to do more specialized sorts of traversals. For instance, we can skip items as we go:

>>> S = 'abcdefghijk'
>>> list(range(0, len(S), 2))
[0, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10]

>>> for i in range(0, len(S), 2): print(S[i], end=' ')
...
a c e g i k

Here, we visit every second item in the string S by stepping over the generated range list. To visit every third item, change the third range argument to be 3, and so on. In effect, using range this way lets you skip items in loops while still retaining the simplicity of the for loop construct.

Still, this is probably not the ideal best-practice technique in Python today. If you really want to skip items in a sequence, the extended three-limit form of the slice expression, presented in Chapter 7, provides a simpler route to the same goal. To visit every second character in S, for example, slice with a stride of 2:

>>> S = 'abcdefghijk'
>>> for c in S[::2]: print(c, end=' ')
...
a c e g i k

The result is the same, but substantially easier for you to write and for others to read. The only real advantage to using range here instead is that it does not copy the string and does not create a list in 3.0; for very large strings, it may save memory.

Changing Lists: range

Another common place where you may use the range and for combination is in loops that change a list as it is being traversed. Suppose, for example, that you need to add 1 to every item in a list. You can try this with a simple for loop, but the result probably won’t be exactly what you want:

>>> L = [1, 2, 3, 4, 5]

>>> for x in L:
...     x += 1
...
>>> L
[1, 2, 3, 4, 5]
>>> x
6

This doesn’t quite work—it changes the loop variable x, not the list L. The reason is somewhat subtle. Each time through the loop, x refers to the next integer already pulled out of the list. In the first iteration, for example, x is integer 1. In the next iteration, the loop body sets x to a different object, integer 2, but it does not update the list where 1 originally came from.

To really change the list as we march across it, we need to use indexes so we can assign an updated value to each position as we go. The range/len combination can produce the required indexes for us:

>>> L = [1, 2, 3, 4, 5]

>>> for i in range(len(L)):          # Add one to each item in L
...     L[i] += 1                    # Or L[i] = L[i] + 1
...
>>> L
[2, 3, 4, 5, 6]

When coded this way, the list is changed as we proceed through the loop. There is no way to do the same with a simple for x in L:-style loop, because such a loop iterates through actual items, not list positions. But what about the equivalent while loop? Such a loop requires a bit more work on our part, and likely runs more slowly:

>>> i = 0
>>> while i < len(L):
...     L[i] += 1
...     i += 1
...
>>> L
[3, 4, 5, 6, 7]

Here again, though, the range solution may not be ideal either. A list comprehension expression of the form:

[x+1 for x in L]

would do similar work, albeit without changing the original list in-place (we could assign the expression’s new list object result back to L, but this would not update any other references to the original list). Because this is such a central looping concept, we’ll save a complete exploration of list comprehensions for the next chapter.

Parallel Traversals: zip and map

As we’ve seen, the range built-in allows us to traverse sequences with for in a nonexhaustive fashion. In the same spirit, the built-in zip function allows us to use for loops to visit multiple sequences in parallel. In basic operation, zip takes one or more sequences as arguments and returns a series of tuples that pair up parallel items taken from those sequences. For example, suppose we’re working with two lists:

>>> L1 = [1,2,3,4]
>>> L2 = [5,6,7,8]

To combine the items in these lists, we can use zip to create a list of tuple pairs (like range, zip is an iterable object in 3.0, so we must wrap it in a list call to display all its results at once—more on iterators in the next chapter):

>>> zip(L1, L2)
<zip object at 0x026523C8>
>>> list(zip(L1, L2))                       # list() required in 3.0, not 2.6
[(1, 5), (2, 6), (3, 7), (4, 8)]

Such a result may be useful in other contexts as well, but when wedded with the for loop, it supports parallel iterations:

>>> for (x, y) in zip(L1, L2):
...     print(x, y, '--', x+y)
...
1 5 -- 6
2 6 -- 8
3 7 -- 10
4 8 -- 12

Here, we step over the result of the zip call—that is, the pairs of items pulled from the two lists. Notice that this for loop again uses the tuple assignment form we met earlier to unpack each tuple in the zip result. The first time through, it’s as though we ran the assignment statement (x, y) = (1, 5).

The net effect is that we scan both L1 and L2 in our loop. We could achieve a similar effect with a while loop that handles indexing manually, but it would require more typing and would likely run more slowly than the for/zip approach.

Strictly speaking, the zip function is more general than this example suggests. For instance, it accepts any type of sequence (really, any iterable object, including files), and it accepts more than two arguments. With three arguments, as in the following example, it builds a list of three-item tuples with items from each sequence, essentially projecting by columns (technically, we get an N-ary tuple for N arguments):

>>> T1, T2, T3 = (1,2,3), (4,5,6), (7,8,9)
>>> T3
(7, 8, 9)
>>> list(zip(T1, T2, T3))
[(1, 4, 7), (2, 5, 8), (3, 6, 9)]

Moreover, zip truncates result tuples at the length of the shortest sequence when the argument lengths differ. In the following, we zip together two strings to pick out characters in parallel, but the result has only as many tuples as the length of the shortest sequence:

>>> S1 = 'abc'
>>> S2 = 'xyz123'
>>>
>>> list(zip(S1, S2))
[('a', 'x'), ('b', 'y'), ('c', 'z')]

map equivalence in Python 2.6

In Python 2.X, the related built-in map function pairs items from sequences in a similar fashion, but it pads shorter sequences with None if the argument lengths differ instead of truncating to the shortest length:

>>> S1 = 'abc'
>>> S2 = 'xyz123'

>>> map(None, S1, S2)                        # 2.X only
[('a', 'x'), ('b', 'y'), ('c', 'z'), (None, '1'), (None, '2'), (None,'3')]

This example is using a degenerate form of the map built-in, which is no longer supported in 3.0. Normally, map takes a function and one or more sequence arguments and collects the results of calling the function with parallel items taken from the sequence(s). We’ll study map in detail in Chapters 19 and 20, but as a brief example, the following maps the built-in ord function across each item in a string and collects the results (like zip, map is a value generator in 3.0 and so must be passed to list to collect all its results at once):

>>> list(map(ord, 'spam'))
[115, 112, 97, 109]

This works the same as the following loop statement, but is often quicker:

>>> res = []
>>> for c in 'spam': res.append(ord(c))
>>> res
[115, 112, 97, 109]

Note

Version skew note: The degenerate form of map using a function argument of None is no longer supported in Python 3.0, because it largely overlaps with zip (and was, frankly, a bit at odds with map’s function-application purpose). In 3.0, either use zip or write loop code to pad results yourself. We’ll see how to do this in Chapter 20, after we’ve had a chance to study some additional iteration concepts.

Dictionary construction with zip

In Chapter 8, I suggested that the zip call used here can also be handy for generating dictionaries when the sets of keys and values must be computed at runtime. Now that we’re becoming proficient with zip, I’ll explain how it relates to dictionary construction. As you’ve learned, you can always create a dictionary by coding a dictionary literal, or by assigning to keys over time:

>>> D1 = {'spam':1, 'eggs':3, 'toast':5}
>>> D1
{'toast': 5, 'eggs': 3, 'spam': 1}

>>> D1 = {}
>>> D1['spam']  = 1
>>> D1['eggs']  = 3
>>> D1['toast'] = 5

What to do, though, if your program obtains dictionary keys and values in lists at runtime, after you’ve coded your script? For example, say you had the following keys and values lists:

>>> keys = ['spam', 'eggs', 'toast']
>>> vals = [1, 3, 5]

One solution for turning those lists into a dictionary would be to zip the lists and step through them in parallel with a for loop:

>>> list(zip(keys, vals))
[('spam', 1), ('eggs', 3), ('toast', 5)]

>>> D2 = {}
>>> for (k, v) in zip(keys, vals): D2[k] = v
...
>>> D2
{'toast': 5, 'eggs': 3, 'spam': 1}

It turns out, though, that in Python 2.2 and later you can skip the for loop altogether and simply pass the zipped keys/values lists to the built-in dict constructor call:

>>> keys = ['spam', 'eggs', 'toast']
>>> vals = [1, 3, 5]

>>> D3 = dict(zip(keys, vals))
>>> D3
{'toast': 5, 'eggs': 3, 'spam': 1}

The built-in name dict is really a type name in Python (you’ll learn more about type names, and subclassing them, in Chapter 31). Calling it achieves something like a list-to-dictionary conversion, but it’s really an object construction request. In the next chapter we’ll explore a related but richer concept, the list comprehension, which builds lists in a single expression; we’ll also revisit 3.0 dictionary comprehensions, an alternative to the dict call for zipped key/value pairs.

Generating Both Offsets and Items: enumerate

Earlier, we discussed using range to generate the offsets of items in a string, rather than the items at those offsets. In some programs, though, we need both: the item to use, plus an offset as we go. Traditionally, this was coded with a simple for loop that also kept a counter of the current offset:

>>> S = 'spam'
>>> offset = 0
>>> for item in S:
...     print(item, 'appears at offset', offset)
...     offset += 1
...
s appears at offset 0
p appears at offset 1
a appears at offset 2
m appears at offset 3

This works, but in recent Python releases a new built-in named enumerate does the job for us:

>>> S = 'spam'
>>> for (offset, item) in enumerate(S):
...     print(item, 'appears at offset', offset)
...
s appears at offset 0
p appears at offset 1
a appears at offset 2
m appears at offset 3

The enumerate function returns a generator object—a kind of object that supports the iteration protocol that we will study in the next chapter and will discuss in more detail in the next part of the book. In short, it has a __next__ method called by the next built-in function, which returns an (index, value) tuple each time through the loop. We can unpack these tuples with tuple assignment in the for loop (much like using zip):

>>> E = enumerate(S)
>>> E
<enumerate object at 0x02765AA8>
>>> next(E)
(0, 's')
>>> next(E)
(1, 'p')
>>> next(E)
(2, 'a')

As usual, we don’t normally see this machinery because iteration contexts—including list comprehensions, the subject of Chapter 14—run the iteration protocol automatically:

>>> [c * i for (i, c) in enumerate(S)]
['', 'p', 'aa', 'mmm']

To fully understand iteration concepts like enumerate, zip, and list comprehensions, we need to move on to the next chapter for a more formal dissection.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

The while loop is a general looping statement, but the for is designed to iterate across items in a sequence (really, iterable). Although the while can imitate the for with counter loops, it takes more code and might run slower.

The break statement exits a loop immediately (you wind up below the entire while or for loop statement), and continue jumps back to the top of the loop (you wind up positioned just before the test in while or the next item fetch in for).

The else clause in a while or for loop will be run once as the loop is exiting, if the loop exits normally (without running into a break statement). A break exits the loop immediately, skipping the else part on the way out (if there is one).

Counter loops can be coded with a while statement that keeps track of the index manually, or with a for loop that uses the range built-in function to generate successive integer offsets. Neither is the preferred way to work in Python, if you need to simply step across all the items in a sequence. Instead, use a simple for loop instead, without range or counters, whenever possible; it will be easier to code and usually quicker to run.

The range built-in can be used in a for to implement a fixed number of repetitions, to scan by offsets instead of items at offsets, to skip successive items as you go, and to change a list while stepping across it. None of these roles requires range, and most have alternatives—scanning actual items, three-limit slices, and list comprehensions are often better solutions today (despite the natural inclinations of ex-C programmers to want to count things!).

Chapter 14. Iterations and Comprehensions, Part 1

In the prior chapter we met Python’s two looping statements, while and for. Although they can handle most repetitive tasks programs need to perform, the need to iterate over sequences is so common and pervasive that Python provides additional tools to make it simpler and more efficient. This chapter begins our exploration of these tools. Specifically, it presents the related concepts of Python’s iteration protocol—a method-call model used by the for loop—and fills in some details on list comprehensions—a close cousin to the for loop that applies an expression to items in an iterable.

Because both of these tools are related to both the for loop and functions, we’ll take a two-pass approach to covering them in this book: this chapter introduces the basics in the context of looping tools, serving as something of continuation of the prior chapter, and a later chapter (Chapter 20) revisits them in the context of function-based tools. In this chapter, we’ll also sample additional iteration tools in Python and touch on the new iterators available in Python 3.0.

One note up front: some of the concepts presented in these chapters may seem advanced at first glance. With practice, though, you’ll find that these tools are useful and powerful. Although never strictly required, because they’ve become commonplace in Python code, a basic understanding can also help if you must read programs written by others.

Iterators: A First Look

In the preceding chapter, I mentioned that the for loop can work on any sequence type in Python, including lists, tuples, and strings, like this:

>>> for x in [1, 2, 3, 4]: print(x ** 2, end=' ')
...
1 4 9 16

>>> for x in (1, 2, 3, 4): print(x ** 3, end=' ')
...
1 8 27 64

>>> for x in 'spam': print(x * 2, end=' ')
...
ss pp aa mm

Actually, the for loop turns out to be even more generic than this—it works on any iterable object. In fact, this is true of all iteration tools that scan objects from left to right in Python, including for loops, the list comprehensions we’ll study in this chapter, in membership tests, the map built-in function, and more.

The concept of “iterable objects” is relatively recent in Python, but it has come to permeate the language’s design. It’s essentially a generalization of the notion of sequences—an object is considered iterable if it is either a physically stored sequence or an object that produces one result at a time in the context of an iteration tool like a for loop. In a sense, iterable objects include both physical sequences and virtual sequences computed on demand.[33]

The Iteration Protocol: File Iterators

One of the easiest ways to understand what this means is to look at how it works with a built-in type such as the file. Recall from Chapter 9 that open file objects have a method called readline, which reads one line of text from a file at a time—each time we call the readline method, we advance to the next line. At the end of the file, an empty string is returned, which we can detect to break out of the loop:

>>> f = open('script1.py')     # Read a 4-line script file in this directory
>>> f.readline()               # readline loads one line on each call
'import sys\n'
>>> f.readline()
'print(sys.path)\n'
>>> f.readline()
'x = 2\n'
>>> f.readline()
'print(2 ** 33)\n'
>>> f.readline()               # Returns empty string at end-of-file
''

However, files also have a method named __next__ that has a nearly identical effect—it returns the next line from a file each time it is called. The only noticeable difference is that __next__ raises a built-in StopIteration exception at end-of-file instead of returning an empty string:

>>> f = open('script1.py')     # __next__ loads one line on each call too
>>> f.__next__()               # But raises an exception at end-of-file
'import sys\n'
>>> f.__next__()
'print(sys.path)\n'
>>> f.__next__()
'x = 2\n'
>>> f.__next__()
'print(2 ** 33)\n'
>>> f.__next__()
Traceback (most recent call last):
...more exception text omitted...
StopIteration

This interface is exactly what we call the iteration protocol in Python. Any object with a __next__ method to advance to a next result, which raises StopIteration at the end of the series of results, is considered iterable in Python. Any such object may also be stepped through with a for loop or other iteration tool, because all iteration tools normally work internally by calling __next__ on each iteration and catching the StopIteration exception to determine when to exit.

The net effect of this magic is that, as mentioned in Chapter 9, the best way to read a text file line by line today is to not read it at all—instead, allow the for loop to automatically call __next__ to advance to the next line on each iteration. The file object’s iterator will do the work of automatically loading lines as you go. The following, for example, reads a file line by line, printing the uppercase version of each line along the way, without ever explicitly reading from the file at all:

>>> for line in open('script1.py'):       # Use file iterators to read by lines
...     print(line.upper(), end='')       # Calls __next__, catches StopIteration
...
IMPORT SYS
PRINT(SYS.PATH)
X = 2
PRINT(2 ** 33)

Notice that the print uses end='' here to suppress adding a \n, because line strings already have one (without this, our output would be double-spaced). This is considered the best way to read text files line by line today, for three reasons: it’s the simplest to code, might be the quickest to run, and is the best in terms of memory usage. The older, original way to achieve the same effect with a for loop is to call the file readlines method to load the file’s content into memory as a list of line strings:

>>> for line in open('script1.py').readlines():
...     print(line.upper(), end='')
...
IMPORT SYS
PRINT(SYS.PATH)
X = 2
PRINT(2 ** 33)

This readlines technique still works, but it is not considered the best practice today and performs poorly in terms of memory usage. In fact, because this version really does load the entire file into memory all at once, it will not even work for files too big to fit into the memory space available on your computer. By contrast, because it reads one line at a time, the iterator-based version is immune to such memory-explosion issues. The iterator version might run quicker too, though this can vary per release (Python 3.0 made this advantage less clear-cut by rewriting I/O libraries to support Unicode text and be less system-dependent).

As mentioned in the prior chapter’s sidebar, Why You Will Care: File Scanners, it’s also possible to read a file line by line with a while loop:

>>> f = open('script1.py')
>>> while True:
...     line = f.readline()
...     if not line: break
...     print(line.upper(), end='')
...
...same output...

However, this may run slower than the iterator-based for loop version, because iterators run at C language speed inside Python, whereas the while loop version runs Python byte code through the Python virtual machine. Any time we trade Python code for C code, speed tends to increase. This is not an absolute truth, though, especially in Python 3.0; we’ll see timing techniques later in this book for measuring the relative speed of alternatives like these.

Manual Iteration: iter and next

To support manual iteration code (with less typing), Python 3.0 also provides a built-in function, next, that automatically calls an object’s __next__ method. Given an iterable object X, the call next(X) is the same as X.__next__(), but noticeably simpler. With files, for instance, either form may be used:

>>> f = open('script1.py')
>>> f.__next__()                   # Call iteration method directly
'import sys\n'
>>> f.__next__()
'print(sys.path)\n'

>>> f = open('script1.py')
>>> next(f)                        # next built-in calls __next__
'import sys\n'
>>> next(f)
'print(sys.path)\n'

Technically, there is one more piece to the iteration protocol. When the for loop begins, it obtains an iterator from the iterable object by passing it to the iter built-in function; the object returned by iter has the required next method. This becomes obvious if we look at how for loops internally process built-in sequence types such as lists:

>>> L = [1, 2, 3]
>>> I = iter(L)                    # Obtain an iterator object
>>> I.__next__()                   # Call next to advance to next item
1
>>> I.__next__()
2
>>> I.__next__()
3
>>> I.__next__()
Traceback (most recent call last):
...more omitted...
StopIteration

This initial step is not required for files, because a file object is its own iterator. That is, files have their own __next__ method and so do not need to return a different object that does:

>>> f = open('script1.py')
>>> iter(f) is f
True
>>> f.__next__()
'import sys\n'

Lists, and many other built-in objects, are not their own iterators because they support multiple open iterations. For such objects, we must call iter to start iterating:

>>> L = [1, 2, 3]
>>> iter(L) is L
False
>>> L.__next__()
AttributeError: 'list' object has no attribute '__next__'

>>> I = iter(L)
>>> I.__next__()
1
>>> next(I)                # Same as I.__next__()
2

Although Python iteration tools call these functions automatically, we can use them to apply the iteration protocol manually, too. The following interaction demonstrates the equivalence between automatic and manual iteration:[34]

>>> L = [1, 2, 3]
>>>
>>> for X in L:                 # Automatic iteration
...     print(X ** 2, end=' ')  # Obtains iter, calls __next__, catches exceptions
...
1 4 9

>>> I = iter(L)                 # Manual iteration: what for loops usually do
>>> while True:
...     try:                    # try statement catches exceptions
...         X = next(I)         # Or call I.__next__
...     except StopIteration:
...         break
...     print(X ** 2, end=' ')
...
1 4 9

To understand this code, you need to know that try statements run an action and catch exceptions that occur while the action runs (we’ll explore exceptions in depth in Part VII). I should also note that for loops and other iteration contexts can sometimes work differently for user-defined classes, repeatedly indexing an object instead of running the iteration protocol. We’ll defer that story until we study class operator overloading in Chapter 29.

Note

Version skew note: In Python 2.6, the iteration method is named X.next() instead of X.__next__(). For portability, the next(X) built-in function is available in Python 2.6 too (but not earlier), and calls 2.6’s X.next() instead of 3.0’s X.__next__(). Iteration works the same in 2.6 in all other ways, though; simply use X.next() or next(X) for manual iterations, instead of 3.0’s X.__next__(). Prior to 2.6, use manual X.next() calls instead of next(X).

Other Built-in Type Iterators

Besides files and physical sequences like lists, other types have useful iterators as well. The classic way to step through the keys of a dictionary, for example, is to request its keys list explicitly:

>>> D = {'a':1, 'b':2, 'c':3}
>>> for key in D.keys():
...     print(key, D[key])
...
a 1
c 3
b 2

In recent versions of Python, though, dictionaries have an iterator that automatically returns one key at a time in an iteration context:

>>> I = iter(D)
>>> next(I)
'a'
>>> next(I)
'c'
>>> next(I)
'b'
>>> next(I)
Traceback (most recent call last):
...more omitted...
StopIteration

The net effect is that we no longer need to call the keys method to step through dictionary keys—the for loop will use the iteration protocol to grab one key each time through:

>>> for key in D:
...     print(key, D[key])
...
a 1
c 3
b 2

We can’t delve into their details here, but other Python object types also support the iterator protocol and thus may be used in for loops too. For instance, shelves (an access-by-key filesystem for Python objects) and the results from os.popen (a tool for reading the output of shell commands) are iterable as well:

>>> import os
>>> P = os.popen('dir')
>>> P.__next__()
' Volume in drive C is SQ004828V03\n'
>>> P.__next__()
' Volume Serial Number is 08BE-3CD4\n'
>>> next(P)
TypeError: _wrap_close object is not an iterator

Notice that popen objects support a P.next() method in Python 2.6. In 3.0, they support the P.__next__() method, but not the next(P) built-in; since the latter is defined to call the former, it’s not clear if this behavior will endure in future releases (as described in an earlier footnote, this appears to be an implementation issue). This is only an issue for manual iteration, though; if you iterate over these objects automatically with for loops and other iteration contexts (described in the next sections), they return successive lines in either Python version.

The iteration protocol also is the reason that we’ve had to wrap some results in a list call to see their values all at once. Objects that are iterable return results one at a time, not in a physical list:

>>> R = range(5)
>>> R                            # Ranges are iterables in 3.0
range(0, 5)
>>> I = iter(R)                  # Use iteration protocol to produce results
>>> next(I)
0
>>> next(I)
1
>>> list(range(5))               # Or use list to collect all results at once
[0, 1, 2, 3, 4]

Now that you have a better understanding of this protocol, you should be able to see how it explains why the enumerate tool introduced in the prior chapter works the way it does:

>>> E = enumerate('spam')        # enumerate is an iterable too
>>> E
<enumerate object at 0x0253F508>
>>> I = iter(E)
>>> next(I)                      # Generate results with iteration protocol
(0, 's')
>>> next(I)                      # Or use list to force generation to run
(1, 'p')
>>> list(enumerate('spam'))
[(0, 's'), (1, 'p'), (2, 'a'), (3, 'm')]

We don’t normally see this machinery because for loops run it for us automatically to step through results. In fact, everything that scans left-to-right in Python employs the iteration protocol in the same way—including the topic of the next section.

List Comprehensions: A First Look

Now that we’ve seen how the iteration protocol works, let’s turn to a very common use case. Together with for loops, list comprehensions are one of the most prominent contexts in which the iteration protocol is applied.

In the previous chapter, we learned how to use range to change a list as we step across it:

>>> L = [1, 2, 3, 4, 5]

>>> for i in range(len(L)):
...     L[i] += 10
...
>>> L
[11, 12, 13, 14, 15]

This works, but as I mentioned there, it may not be the optimal “best-practice” approach in Python. Today, the list comprehension expression makes many such prior use cases obsolete. Here, for example, we can replace the loop with a single expression that produces the desired result list:

>>> L = [x + 10 for x in L]
>>> L
[21, 22, 23, 24, 25]

The net result is the same, but it requires less coding on our part and is likely to run substantially faster. The list comprehension isn’t exactly the same as the for loop statement version because it makes a new list object (which might matter if there are multiple references to the original list), but it’s close enough for most applications and is a common and convenient enough approach to merit a closer look here.

List Comprehension Basics

We met the list comprehension briefly in Chapter 4. Syntactically, its syntax is derived from a construct in set theory notation that applies an operation to each item in a set, but you don’t have to know set theory to use this tool. In Python, most people find that a list comprehension simply looks like a backward for loop.

To get a handle on the syntax, let’s dissect the prior section’s example in more detail:

>>> L = [x + 10 for x in L]

List comprehensions are written in square brackets because they are ultimately a way to construct a new list. They begin with an arbitrary expression that we make up, which uses a loop variable that we make up (x + 10). That is followed by what you should now recognize as the header of a for loop, which names the loop variable, and an iterable object (for x in L).

To run the expression, Python executes an iteration across L inside the interpreter, assigning x to each item in turn, and collects the results of running the items through the expression on the left side. The result list we get back is exactly what the list comprehension says—a new list containing x + 10, for every x in L.

Technically speaking, list comprehensions are never really required because we can always build up a list of expression results manually with for loops that append results as we go:

>>> res = []
>>> for x in L:
...     res.append(x + 10)
...
>>> res
[21, 22, 23, 24, 25]

In fact, this is exactly what the list comprehension does internally.

However, list comprehensions are more concise to write, and because this code pattern of building up result lists is so common in Python work, they turn out to be very handy in many contexts. Moreover, list comprehensions can run much faster than manual for loop statements (often roughly twice as fast) because their iterations are performed at C language speed inside the interpreter, rather than with manual Python code; especially for larger data sets, there is a major performance advantage to using them.

Using List Comprehensions on Files

Let’s work through another common use case for list comprehensions to explore them in more detail. Recall that the file object has a readlines method that loads the file into a list of line strings all at once:

>>> f = open('script1.py')
>>> lines = f.readlines()
>>> lines
['import sys\n', 'print(sys.path)\n', 'x = 2\n', 'print(2 ** 33)\n']

This works, but the lines in the result all include the newline character (\n) at the end. For many programs, the newline character gets in the way—we have to be careful to avoid double-spacing when printing, and so on. It would be nice if we could get rid of these newlines all at once, wouldn’t it?

Any time we start thinking about performing an operation on each item in a sequence, we’re in the realm of list comprehensions. For example, assuming the variable lines is as it was in the prior interaction, the following code does the job by running each line in the list through the string rstrip method to remove whitespace on the right side (a line[:−1] slice would work, too, but only if we can be sure all lines are properly terminated):

>>> lines = [line.rstrip() for line in lines]
>>> lines
['import sys', 'print(sys.path)', 'x = 2', 'print(2 ** 33)']

This works as planned. Because list comprehensions are an iteration context just like for loop statements, though, we don’t even have to open the file ahead of time. If we open it inside the expression, the list comprehension will automatically use the iteration protocol we met earlier in this chapter. That is, it will read one line from the file at a time by calling the file’s next method, run the line through the rstrip expression, and add it to the result list. Again, we get what we ask for—the rstrip result of a line, for every line in the file:

>>> lines = [line.rstrip() for line in open('script1.py')]
>>> lines
['import sys', 'print(sys.path)', 'x = 2', 'print(2 ** 33)']

This expression does a lot implicitly, but we’re getting a lot of work for free here—Python scans the file and builds a list of operation results automatically. It’s also an efficient way to code this operation: because most of this work is done inside the Python interpreter, it is likely much faster than an equivalent for statement. Again, especially for large files, the speed advantages of list comprehensions can be significant.

Besides their efficiency, list comprehensions are also remarkably expressive. In our example, we can run any string operation on a file’s lines as we iterate. Here’s the list comprehension equivalent to the file iterator uppercase example we met earlier, along with a few others (the method chaining in the second of these examples works because string methods return a new string, to which we can apply another string method):

>>> [line.upper() for line in open('script1.py')]
['IMPORT SYS\n', 'PRINT(SYS.PATH)\n', 'X = 2\n', 'PRINT(2 ** 33)\n']

>>> [line.rstrip().upper() for line in open('script1.py')]
['IMPORT SYS', 'PRINT(SYS.PATH)', 'X = 2', 'PRINT(2 ** 33)']

>>> [line.split() for line in open('script1.py')]
[['import', 'sys'], ['print(sys.path)'], ['x', '=', '2'], ['print(2', '**','33)']]

>>> [line.replace(' ', '!') for line in open('script1.py')]
['import!sys\n', 'print(sys.path)\n', 'x!=!2\n', 'print(2!**!33)\n']

>>> [('sys' in line, line[0]) for line in open('script1.py')]
[(True, 'i'), (True, 'p'), (False, 'x'), (False, 'p')]

Extended List Comprehension Syntax

In fact, list comprehensions can be even more advanced in practice. As one particularly useful extension, the for loop nested in the expression can have an associated if clause to filter out of the result items for which the test is not true.

For example, suppose we want to repeat the prior section’s file-scanning example, but we need to collect only lines that begin with the letter p (perhaps the first character on each line is an action code of some sort). Adding an if filter clause to our expression does the trick:

>>> lines = [line.rstrip() for line in open('script1.py') if line[0] == 'p']
>>> lines
['print(sys.path)', 'print(2 ** 33)']

Here, the if clause checks each line read from the file to see whether its first character is p; if not, the line is omitted from the result list. This is a fairly big expression, but it’s easy to understand if we translate it to its simple for loop statement equivalent. In general, we can always translate a list comprehension to a for statement by appending as we go and further indenting each successive part:

>>> res = []
>>> for line in open('script1.py'):
...     if line[0] == 'p':
...         res.append(line.rstrip())
...
>>> res
['print(sys.path)', 'print(2 ** 33)']

This for statement equivalent works, but it takes up four lines instead of one and probably runs substantially slower.

List comprehensions can become even more complex if we need them to—for instance, they may contain nested loops, coded as a series of for clauses. In fact, their full syntax allows for any number of for clauses, each of which can have an optional associated if clause (we’ll be more formal about their syntax in Chapter 20).

For example, the following builds a list of the concatenation of x + y for every x in one string and every y in another. It effectively collects the permutation of the characters in two strings:

>>> [x + y for x in 'abc' for y in 'lmn']
['al', 'am', 'an', 'bl', 'bm', 'bn', 'cl', 'cm', 'cn']

Again, one way to understand this expression is to convert it to statement form by indenting its parts. The following is an equivalent, but likely slower, alternative way to achieve the same effect:

>>> res = []
>>> for x in 'abc':
...     for y in 'lmn':
...         res.append(x + y)
...
>>> res
['al', 'am', 'an', 'bl', 'bm', 'bn', 'cl', 'cm', 'cn']

Beyond this complexity level, though, list comprehension expressions can often become too compact for their own good. In general, they are intended for simple types of iterations; for more involved work, a simpler for statement structure will probably be easier to understand and modify in the future. As usual in programming, if something is difficult for you to understand, it’s probably not a good idea.

We’ll revisit list comprehensions in Chapter 20, in the context of functional programming tools; as we’ll see, they turn out to be just as related to functions as they are to looping statements.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

The for loop uses the iteration protocol to step through items in the object across which it is iterating. It calls the object’s __next__ method (run by the next built-in) on each iteration and catches the StopIteration exception to determine when to stop looping. Any object that supports this model works in a for loop and in other iteration contexts.

Both are iteration tools. List comprehensions are a concise and efficient way to perform a common for loop task: collecting the results of applying an expression to all items in an iterable object. It’s always possible to translate a list comprehension to a for loop, and part of the list comprehension expression looks like the header of a for loop syntactically.

Iteration contexts in Python include the for loop; list comprehensions; the map built-in function; the in membership test expression; and the built-in functions sorted, sum, any, and all. This category also includes the list and tuple built-ins, string join methods, and sequence assignments, all of which use the iteration protocol (the __next__ method) to step across iterable objects one item at a time.

The best way to read lines from a text file today is to not read it explicitly at all: instead, open the file within an iteration context such as a for loop or list comprehension, and let the iteration tool automatically scan one line at a time by running the file’s next method on each iteration. This approach is generally best in terms of coding simplicity, execution speed, and memory space requirements.

I’ll accept any of the following as correct answers: fear, intimidation, nice red uniforms, a comfy chair, and soft pillows.

[33] Terminology in this topic tends to be a bit loose. This text uses the terms “iterable” and “iterator” interchangeably to refer to an object that supports iteration in general. Sometimes the term “iterable” refers to an object that supports iter and “iterator” refers to an object return by iter that supports next(I), but that convention is not universal in either the Python world or this book.

[34] Technically speaking, the for loop calls the internal equivalent of I.__next__, instead of the next(I) used here. There is rarely any difference between the two, but as we’ll see in the next section, there are some built-in objects in 3.0 (such as os.popen results) that support the former and not the latter, but may be still be iterated across in for loops. Your manual iterations can generally use either call scheme. If you care for the full story, in 3.0 os.popen results have been reimplemented with the subprocess module and a wrapper class, whose __getattr__ method is no longer called in 3.0 for implicit __next__ fetches made by the next built-in, but is called for explicit fetches by name—a 3.0 change issue we’ll confront in Chapters 37 and 38, which apparently burns some standard library code too! Also in 3.0, the related 2.6 calls os.popen2/3/4 are no longer available; use subprocess.Popen with appropriate arguments instead (see the Python 3.0 library manual for the new required code).

Common Coding Gotchas

Before the programming exercises for this part of the book, let’s run through some of the most common mistakes beginners make when coding Python statements and programs. Many of these are warnings I’ve thrown out earlier in this part of the book, collected here for ease of reference. You’ll learn to avoid these pitfalls once you’ve gained a bit of Python coding experience, but a few words now might help you avoid falling into some of these traps initially:

Don’t forget the colons. Always remember to type a : at the end of compound statement headers (the first line of an if, while, for, etc.). You’ll probably forget at first (I did, and so have most of my 3,000 Python students over the years), but you can take some comfort from the fact that it will soon become an unconscious habit.

Start in column 1. Be sure to start top-level (unnested) code in column 1. That includes unnested code typed into module files, as well as unnested code typed at the interactive prompt.

Blank lines matter at the interactive prompt. Blank lines in compound statements are always ignored in module files, but when you’re typing code at the interactive prompt, they end the statement. In other words, blank lines tell the interactive command line that you’ve finished a compound statement; if you want to continue, don’t hit the Enter key at the ... prompt (or in IDLE) until you’re really done.

Indent consistently. Avoid mixing tabs and spaces in the indentation of a block, unless you know what your text editor does with tabs. Otherwise, what you see in your editor may not be what Python sees when it counts tabs as a number of spaces. This is true in any block-structured language, not just Python—if the next programmer has her tabs set differently, she will not understand the structure of your code. It’s safer to use all tabs or all spaces for each block.

Don’t code C in Python. A reminder for C/C++ programmers: you don’t need to type parentheses around tests in if and while headers (e.g., if (X==1):). You can, if you like (any expression can be enclosed in parentheses), but they are fully superfluous in this context. Also, do not terminate all your statements with semicolons; it’s technically legal to do this in Python as well, but it’s totally useless unless you’re placing more than one statement on a single line (the end of a line normally terminates a statement). And remember, don’t embed assignment statements in while loop tests, and don’t use {} around blocks (indent your nested code blocks consistently instead).

Use simple for loops instead of while or range. Another reminder: a simple for loop (e.g., for x in seq:) is almost always simpler to code and quicker to run than a while- or range-based counter loop. Because Python handles indexing internally for a simple for, it can sometimes be twice as fast as the equivalent while. Avoid the temptation to count things in Python!

Beware of mutables in assignments. I mentioned this in Chapter 11: you need to be careful about using mutables in a multiple-target assignment (a = b = []), as well as in an augmented assignment (a += [1, 2]). In both cases, in-place changes may impact other variables. See Chapter 11 for details.

Don’t expect results from functions that change objects in-place. We encountered this one earlier, too: in-place change operations like the list.append and list.sort methods introduced in Chapter 8 do not return values (other than None), so you should call them without assigning the result. It’s not uncommon for beginners to say something like mylist = mylist.append(X) to try to get the result of an append, but what this actually does is assign mylist to None, not to the modified list (in fact, you’ll lose your reference to the list altogether).

A more devious example of this pops up in Python 2.X code when trying to step through dictionary items in a sorted fashion. It’s fairly common to see code like for k in D.keys().sort():. This almost works—the keys method builds a keys list, and the sort method orders it—but because the sort method returns None, the loop fails because it is ultimately a loop over None (a nonsequence). This fails even sooner in Python 3.0, because dictionary keys are views, not lists! To code this correctly, either use the newer sorted built-in function, which returns the sorted list, or split the method calls out to statements: Ks = list(D.keys()), then Ks.sort(), and finally, for k in Ks:. This, by the way, is one case where you’ll still want to call the keys method explicitly for looping, instead of relying on the dictionary iterators—iterators do not sort.

Always use parentheses to call a function. You must add parentheses after a function name to call it, whether it takes arguments or not (e.g., use function(), not function). In Part IV, we’ll see that functions are simply objects that have a special operation—a call that you trigger with the parentheses.

In classes, this problem seems to occur most often with files; it’s common to see beginners type file.close to close a file, rather than file.close(). Because it’s legal to reference a function without calling it, the first version with no parentheses succeeds silently, but it does not close the file!

Don’t use extensions or paths in imports and reloads. Omit directory paths and file suffixes in import statements (e.g., say import mod, not import mod.py). (We discussed module basics in Chapter 3 and will continue studying modules in Part V.) Because modules may have other suffixes besides .py (.pyc, for instance), hardcoding a particular suffix is not only illegal syntax, but doesn’t make sense. Any platform-specific directory path syntax comes from module search path settings, not the import statement.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

Documentation strings (docstrings) are considered best for larger, functional documentation, describing the use of modules, functions, classes, and methods in your code. Hash-mark comments are today best limited to micro-documentation about arcane expressions or statements. This is partly because docstrings are easier to find in a source file, but also because they can be extracted and displayed by the PyDoc system.

You can see docstrings by printing an object’s __doc__ attribute, by passing it to PyDoc’s help function, and by selecting modules in PyDoc’s GUI search engine in client/server mode. Additionally, PyDoc can be run to save a module’s documentation in an HTML file for later viewing or printing.

The built-in dir(X) function returns a list of all the attributes attached to any object.

Run the PyDoc GUI interface, leave the module name blank, and select “open browser”; this opens a web page containing a link to every module available to your programs.

Mine, of course. (Seriously, the Preface lists a few recommended follow-up books, both for reference and for application tutorials.)

Test Your Knowledge: Part III Exercises

Now that you know how to code basic program logic, the following exercises will ask you to implement some simple tasks with statements. Most of the work is in exercise 4, which lets you explore coding alternatives. There are always many ways to arrange statements, and part of learning Python is learning which arrangements work better than others.

See Part III in Appendix B for the solutions.

Coding basic loops.

Write a for loop that prints the ASCII code of each character in a string named S. Use the built-in function ord(character) to convert each character to an ASCII integer. (Test it interactively to see how it works.)

Next, change your loop to compute the sum of the ASCII codes of all the characters in a string.

Finally, modify your code again to return a new list that contains the ASCII codes of each character in the string. Does the expression map(ord, S) have a similar effect? (Hint: see Chapter 14.)

Backslash characters. What happens on your machine when you type the following code interactively?

for i in range(50):
    print('hello %d\n\a' % i)

Beware that if it’s run outside of the IDLE interface this example may beep at you, so you may not want to run it in a crowded lab. IDLE prints odd characters instead of beeping (see the backslash escape characters in Table 7-2).

Sorting dictionaries. In Chapter 8, we saw that dictionaries are unordered collections. Write a for loop that prints a dictionary’s items in sorted (ascending) order. (Hint: use the dictionary keys and list sort methods, or the newer sorted built-in function.)

Program logic alternatives. Consider the following code, which uses a while loop and found flag to search a list of powers of 2 for the value of 2 raised to the fifth power (32). It’s stored in a module file called power.py.

L = [1, 2, 4, 8, 16, 32, 64]
X = 5

found = False
i = 0
while not found and i < len(L):
   if 2 ** X == L[i]:
       found = True
   else:
       i = i+1

if found:
    print('at index', i)
else:
    print(X, 'not found')

C:\book\tests> python power.py
at index 5

As is, the example doesn’t follow normal Python coding techniques. Follow the steps outlined here to improve it (for all the transformations, you may either type your code interactively or store it in a script file run from the system command line—using a file makes this exercise much easier):

First, rewrite this code with a while loop else clause to eliminate the found flag and final if statement.

Next, rewrite the example to use a for loop with an else clause, to eliminate the explicit list-indexing logic. (Hint: to get the index of an item, use the list index method—L.index(X) returns the offset of the first X in list L.)

Next, remove the loop completely by rewriting the example with a simple in operator membership expression. (See Chapter 8 for more details, or type this to test: 2 in [1,2,3].)

Finally, use a for loop and the list append method to generate the powers-of-2 list (L) instead of hardcoding a list literal.

Deeper thoughts:

Do you think it would improve performance to move the 2 ** X expression outside the loops? How would you code that?

As we saw in exercise 1, Python includes a map(function, list) tool that can generate a powers-of-2 list, too: map(lambda x: 2 ** x, range(7)). Try typing this code interactively; we’ll meet lambda more formally in Chapter 19.

Why Use Functions?

Before we get into the details, let’s establish a clear picture of what functions are all about. Functions are a nearly universal program-structuring device. You may have come across them before in other languages, where they may have been called subroutines or procedures. As a brief introduction, functions serve two primary development roles:

Maximizing code reuse and minimizing redundancy

As in most programming languages, Python functions are the simplest way to package logic you may wish to use in more than one place and more than one time. Up until now, all the code we’ve been writing has run immediately. Functions allow us to group and generalize code to be used arbitrarily many times later. Because they allow us to code an operation in a single place and use it in many places, Python functions are the most basic factoring tool in the language: they allow us to reduce code redundancy in our programs, and thereby reduce maintenance effort.

Procedural decomposition

Functions also provide a tool for splitting systems into pieces that have well-defined roles. For instance, to make a pizza from scratch, you would start by mixing the dough, rolling it out, adding toppings, baking it, and so on. If you were programming a pizza-making robot, functions would help you divide the overall “make pizza” task into chunks—one function for each subtask in the process. It’s easier to implement the smaller tasks in isolation than it is to implement the entire process at once. In general, functions are about procedure—how to do something, rather than what you’re doing it to. We’ll see why this distinction matters in Part VI, when we start making new object with classes.

In this part of the book, we’ll explore the tools used to code functions in Python: function basics, scope rules, and argument passing, along with a few related concepts such as generators and functional tools. Because its importance begins to become more apparent at this level of coding, we’ll also revisit the notion of polymorphism introduced earlier in the book. As you’ll see, functions don’t imply much new syntax, but they do lead us to some bigger programming ideas.

Coding Functions

Although it wasn’t made very formal, we’ve already used some functions in earlier chapters. For instance, to make a file object, we called the built-in open function; similarly, we used the len built-in function to ask for the number of items in a collection object.

In this chapter, we will explore how to write new functions in Python. Functions we write behave the same way as the built-ins we’ve already seen: they are called in expressions, are passed values, and return results. But writing new functions requires the application of a few additional ideas that haven’t yet been introduced. Moreover, functions behave very differently in Python than they do in compiled languages like C. Here is a brief introduction to the main concepts behind Python functions, all of which we will study in this part of the book:

def is executable code. Python functions are written with a new statement, the def. Unlike functions in compiled languages such as C, def is an executable statement—your function does not exist until Python reaches and runs the def. In fact, it’s legal (and even occasionally useful) to nest def statements inside if statements, while loops, and even other defs. In typical operation, def statements are coded in module files and are naturally run to generate functions when a module file is first imported.

def creates an object and assigns it to a name. When Python reaches and runs a def statement, it generates a new function object and assigns it to the function’s name. As with all assignments, the function name becomes a reference to the function object. There’s nothing magic about the name of a function—as you’ll see, the function object can be assigned to other names, stored in a list, and so on. Function objects may also have arbitrary user-defined attributes attached to them to record data.

lambda creates an object but returns it as a result. Functions may also be created with the lambda expression, a feature that allows us to in-line function definitions in places where a def statement won’t work syntactically (this is a more advanced concept that we’ll defer until Chapter 19).

return sends a result object back to the caller. When a function is called, the caller stops until the function finishes its work and returns control to the caller. Functions that compute a value send it back to the caller with a return statement; the returned value becomes the result of the function call.

yield sends a result object back to the caller, but remembers where it left off. Functions known as generators may also use the yield statement to send back a value and suspend their state such that they may be resumed later, to produce a series of results over time. This is another advanced topic covered later in this part of the book.

global declares module-level variables that are to be assigned. By default, all names assigned in a function are local to that function and exist only while the function runs. To assign a name in the enclosing module, functions need to list it in a global statement. More generally, names are always looked up in scopes—places where variables are stored—and assignments bind names to scopes.

nonlocal declares enclosing function variables that are to be assigned. Similarly, the nonlocal statement added in Python 3.0 allows a function to assign a name that exists in the scope of a syntactically enclosing def statement. This allows enclosing functions to serve as a place to retain state—information remembered when a function is called—without using shared global names.

Arguments are passed by assignment (object reference). In Python, arguments are passed to functions by assignment (which, as we’ve learned, means by object reference). As you’ll see, in Python’s model the caller and function share objects by references, but there is no name aliasing. Changing an argument name within a function does not also change the corresponding name in the caller, but changing passed-in mutable objects can change objects shared by the caller.

Arguments, return values, and variables are not declared. As with everything in Python, there are no type constraints on functions. In fact, nothing about a function needs to be declared ahead of time: you can pass in arguments of any type, return any kind of object, and so on. As one consequence, a single function can often be applied to a variety of object types—any objects that sport a compatible interface (methods and expressions) will do, regardless of their specific types.

If some of the preceding words didn’t sink in, don’t worry—we’ll explore all of these concepts with real code in this part of the book. Let’s get started by expanding on some of these ideas and looking at a few examples.

def Statements

The def statement creates a function object and assigns it to a name. Its general format is as follows:

def <name>(arg1, arg2,... argN):
    <statements>

As with all compound Python statements, def consists of a header line followed by a block of statements, usually indented (or a simple statement after the colon). The statement block becomes the function’s body—that is, the code Python executes each time the function is called.

The def header line specifies a function name that is assigned the function object, along with a list of zero or more arguments (sometimes called parameters) in parentheses. The argument names in the header are assigned to the objects passed in parentheses at the point of call.

Function bodies often contain a return statement:

def <name>(arg1, arg2,... argN):
    ...
    return <value>

The Python return statement can show up anywhere in a function body; it ends the function call and sends a result back to the caller. The return statement consists of an object expression that gives the function’s result. The return statement is optional; if it’s not present, the function exits when the control flow falls off the end of the function body. Technically, a function without a return statement returns the None object automatically, but this return value is usually ignored.

Functions may also contain yield statements, which are designed to produce a series of values over time, but we’ll defer discussion of these until we survey generator topics in Chapter 20.

def Executes at Runtime

The Python def is a true executable statement: when it runs, it creates a new function object and assigns it to a name. (Remember, all we have in Python is runtime; there is no such thing as a separate compile time.) Because it’s a statement, a def can appear anywhere a statement can—even nested in other statements. For instance, although defs normally are run when the module enclosing them is imported, it’s also completely legal to nest a function def inside an if statement to select between alternative definitions:

if test:
    def func():            # Define func this way
        ...
else:
    def func():            # Or else this way
        ...
...
func()                     # Call the version selected and built

One way to understand this code is to realize that the def is much like an = statement: it simply assigns a name at runtime. Unlike in compiled languages such as C, Python functions do not need to be fully defined before the program runs. More generally, defs are not evaluated until they are reached and run, and the code inside defs is not evaluated until the functions are later called.

Because function definition happens at runtime, there’s nothing special about the function name. What’s important is the object to which it refers:

othername = func           # Assign function object
othername()                # Call func again

Here, the function was assigned to a different name and called through the new name. Like everything else in Python, functions are just objects; they are recorded explicitly in memory at program execution time. In fact, besides calls, functions allow arbitrary attributes to be attached to record information for later use:

def func(): ...            # Create function object
func()                     # Call object
func.attr = value          # Attach attributes

A First Example: Definitions and Calls

Apart from such runtime concepts (which tend to seem most unique to programmers with backgrounds in traditional compiled languages), Python functions are straightforward to use. Let’s code a first real example to demonstrate the basics. As you’ll see, there are two sides to the function picture: a definition (the def that creates a function) and a call (an expression that tells Python to run the function’s body).

Definition

Here’s a definition typed interactively that defines a function called times, which returns the product of its two arguments:

>>> def times(x, y):       # Create and assign function
...     return x * y       # Body executed when called
...

When Python reaches and runs this def, it creates a new function object that packages the function’s code and assigns the object to the name times. Typically, such a statement is coded in a module file and runs when the enclosing file is imported; for something this small, though, the interactive prompt suffices.

Calls

After the def has run, you can call (run) the function in your program by adding parentheses after the function’s name. The parentheses may optionally contain one or more object arguments, to be passed (assigned) to the names in the function’s header:

>>> times(2, 4)            # Arguments in parentheses
8

This expression passes two arguments to times. As mentioned previously, arguments are passed by assignment, so in this case the name x in the function header is assigned the value 2, y is assigned the value 4, and the function’s body is run. For this function, the body is just a return statement that sends back the result as the value of the call expression. The returned object was printed here interactively (as in most languages, 2 * 4 is 8 in Python), but if we needed to use it later we could instead assign it to a variable. For example:

>>> x = times(3.14, 4)     # Save the result object
>>> x
12.56

Now, watch what happens when the function is called a third time, with very different kinds of objects passed in:

>>> times('Ni', 4)         # Functions are "typeless"
'NiNiNiNi'

This time, our function means something completely different (Monty Python reference again intended). In this third call, a string and an integer are passed to x and y, instead of two numbers. Recall that * works on both numbers and sequences; because we never declare the types of variables, arguments, or return values in Python, we can use times to either multiply numbers or repeat sequences.

In other words, what our times function means and does depends on what we pass into it. This is a core idea in Python (and perhaps the key to using the language well), which we’ll explore in the next section.

Polymorphism in Python

As we just saw, the very meaning of the expression x * y in our simple times function depends completely upon the kinds of objects that x and y are—thus, the same function can perform multiplication in one instance and repetition in another. Python leaves it up to the objects to do something reasonable for the syntax. Really, * is just a dispatch mechanism that routes control to the objects being processed.

This sort of type-dependent behavior is known as polymorphism, a term we first met in Chapter 4 that essentially means that the meaning of an operation depends on the objects being operated upon. Because it’s a dynamically typed language, polymorphism runs rampant in Python. In fact, every operation is a polymorphic operation in Python: printing, indexing, the * operator, and much more.

This is deliberate, and it accounts for much of the language’s conciseness and flexibility. A single function, for instance, can generally be applied to a whole category of object types automatically. As long as those objects support the expected interface (a.k.a. protocol), the function can process them. That is, if the objects passed into a function have the expected methods and expression operators, they are plug-and-play compatible with the function’s logic.

Even in our simple times function, this means that any two objects that support a * will work, no matter what they may be, and no matter when they are coded. This function will work on two numbers (performing multiplication), or a string and a number (performing repetition), or any other combination of objects supporting the expected interface—even class-based objects we have not even coded yet.

Moreover, if the objects passed in do not support this expected interface, Python will detect the error when the * expression is run and raise an exception automatically. It’s therefore pointless to code error checking ourselves. In fact, doing so would limit our function’s utility, as it would be restricted to work only on objects whose types we test for.

This turns out to be a crucial philosophical difference between Python and statically typed languages like C++ and Java: in Python, your code is not supposed to care about specific data types. If it does, it will be limited to working on just the types you anticipated when you wrote it, and it will not support other compatible object types that may be coded in the future. Although it is possible to test for types with tools like the type built-in function, doing so breaks your code’s flexibility. By and large, we code to object interfaces in Python, not data types.

Of course, this polymorphic model of programming means we have to test our code to detect errors, rather than providing type declarations a compiler can use to detect some types of errors for us ahead of time. In exchange for an initial bit of testing, though, we radically reduce the amount of code we have to write and radically increase our code’s flexibility. As you’ll learn, it’s a net win in practice.

A Second Example: Intersecting Sequences

Let’s look at a second function example that does something a bit more useful than multiplying arguments and further illustrates function basics.

In Chapter 13, we coded a for loop that collected items held in common in two strings. We noted there that the code wasn’t as useful as it could be because it was set up to work only on specific variables and could not be rerun later. Of course, we could copy the code and paste it into each place where it needs to be run, but this solution is neither good nor general—we’d still have to edit each copy to support different sequence names, and changing the algorithm would then require changing multiple copies.

Definition

By now, you can probably guess that the solution to this dilemma is to package the for loop inside a function. Doing so offers a number of advantages:

Putting the code in a function makes it a tool that you can run as many times as you like.

Because callers can pass in arbitrary arguments, functions are general enough to work on any two sequences (or other iterables) you wish to intersect.

When the logic is packaged in a function, you only have to change code in one place if you ever need to change the way the intersection works.

Coding the function in a module file means it can be imported and reused by any program run on your machine.

In effect, wrapping the code in a function makes it a general intersection utility:

def intersect(seq1, seq2):
    res = []                     # Start empty
    for x in seq1:               # Scan seq1
        if x in seq2:            # Common item?
            res.append(x)        # Add to end
    return res

The transformation from the simple code of Chapter 13 to this function is straightforward; we’ve just nested the original logic under a def header and made the objects on which it operates passed-in parameter names. Because this function computes a result, we’ve also added a return statement to send a result object back to the caller.

Calls

Before you can call a function, you have to make it. To do this, run its def statement, either by typing it interactively or by coding it in a module file and importing the file. Once you’ve run the def, you can call the function by passing any two sequence objects in parentheses:

>>> s1 = "SPAM"
>>> s2 = "SCAM"
>>> intersect(s1, s2)            # Strings
['S', 'A', 'M']

Here, we’ve passed in two strings, and we get back a list containing the characters in common. The algorithm the function uses is simple: “for every item in the first argument, if that item is also in the second argument, append the item to the result.” It’s a little shorter to say that in Python than in English, but it works out the same.

To be fair, our intersect function is fairly slow (it executes nested loops), isn’t really mathematical intersection (there may be duplicates in the result), and isn’t required at all (as we’ve seen, Python’s set data type provides a built-in intersection operation). Indeed, the function could be replaced with a single list comprehension expression, as it exhibits the classic loop collector code pattern:

>>> [x for x in s1 if x in s2]
['S', 'A', 'M']

As a function basics example, though, it does the job—this single piece of code can apply to an entire range of object types, as the next section explains.

Polymorphism Revisited

Like all functions in Python, intersect is polymorphic. That is, it works on arbitrary types, as long as they support the expected object interface:

>>> x = intersect([1, 2, 3], (1, 4))      # Mixed types
>>> x                                     # Saved result object
[1]

This time, we passed in different types of objects to our function—a list and a tuple (mixed types)—and it still picked out the common items. Because you don’t have to specify the types of arguments ahead of time, the intersect function happily iterates through any kind of sequence objects you send it, as long as they support the expected interfaces.

For intersect, this means that the first argument has to support the for loop, and the second has to support the in membership test. Any two such objects will work, regardless of their specific types—that includes physically stored sequences like strings and lists; all the iterable objects we met in Chapter 14, including files and dictionaries; and even any class-based objects we code that apply operator overloading techniques (we’ll discuss these later in the book).[35]

Here again, if we pass in objects that do not support these interfaces (e.g., numbers), Python will automatically detect the mismatch and raise an exception for us—which is exactly what we want, and the best we could do on our own if we coded explicit type tests. By not coding type tests and allowing Python to detect the mismatches for us, we both reduce the amount of code we need to write and increase our code’s flexibility.

Local Variables

Probably the most interesting part of this example is its names. It turns out that the variable res inside intersect is what in Python is called a local variable—a name that is visible only to code inside the function def and that exists only while the function runs. In fact, because all names assigned in any way inside a function are classified as local variables by default, nearly all the names in intersect are local variables:

res is obviously assigned, so it is a local variable.

Arguments are passed by assignment, so seq1 and seq2 are, too.

The for loop assigns items to a variable, so the name x is also local.

All these local variables appear when the function is called and disappear when the function exits—the return statement at the end of intersect sends back the result object, but the name res goes away. To fully explore the notion of locals, though, we need to move on to Chapter 17.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

Functions are the most basic way of avoiding code redundancy in Python—factoring code into functions means that we have only one copy of an operation’s code to update in the future. Functions are also the basic unit of code reuse in Python—wrapping code in functions makes it a reusable tool, callable in a variety of programs. Finally, functions allow us to divide a complex system into manageable parts, each of which may be developed individually.

A function is created when Python reaches and runs the def statement; this statement creates a function object and assigns it the function’s name. This normally happens when the enclosing module file is imported by another module (recall that imports run the code in a file from top to bottom, including any defs), but it can also occur when a def is typed interactively or nested in other statements, such as ifs.

A function returns the None object by default if the control flow falls off the end of the function body without running into a return statement. Such functions are usually called with expression statements, as assigning their None results to variables is generally pointless.

The function body (the code nested inside the function definition statement) is run when the function is later called with a call expression. The body runs anew each time the function is called.

Checking the types of objects passed into a function effectively breaks the function’s flexibility, constraining the function to work on specific types only. Without such checks, the function would likely be able to process an entire range of object types—any objects that support the interface expected by the function will work. (The term interface means the set of methods and expression operators the function’s code runs.)

[35] This code will always work if we intersect files’ contents obtained with file.readlines(). It may not work to intersect lines in open input files directly, though, depending on the file object’s implementation of the in operator or general iteration. Files must generally be rewound (e.g., with a file.seek(0) or another open) after they have been read to end-of-file once. As we’ll see in Chapter 29 when we study operator overloading, classes implement the in operator either by providing the specific __contains__ method or by supporting the general iteration protocol with the __iter__ or older __getitem__ methods; if coded, classes can define what iteration means for their data.

The global Statement

The global statement and its nonlocal cousin are the only things that are remotely like declaration statements in Python. They are not type or size declarations, though; they are namespace declarations. The global statement tells Python that a function plans to change one or more global names—i.e., names that live in the enclosing module’s scope (namespace).

We’ve talked about global in passing already. Here’s a summary:

Global names are variables assigned at the top level of the enclosing module file.

Global names must be declared only if they are assigned within a function.

Global names may be referenced within a function without being declared.

In other words, global allows us to change names that live outside a def at the top level of a module file. As we’ll see later, the nonlocal statement is almost identical but applies to names in the enclosing def’s local scope, rather than names in the enclosing module.

The global statement consists of the keyword global, followed by one or more names separated by commas. All the listed names will be mapped to the enclosing module’s scope when assigned or referenced within the function body. For instance:

X = 88                         # Global X

def func():
    global X
    X = 99                     # Global X: outside def

func()
print(X)                       # Prints 99

We’ve added a global declaration to the example here, such that the X inside the def now refers to the X outside the def; they are the same variable this time. Here is a slightly more involved example of global at work:

y, z = 1, 2                    # Global variables in module
def all_global():
    global x                   # Declare globals assigned
    x = y + z                  # No need to declare y, z: LEGB rule

Here, x, y, and z are all globals inside the function all_global. y and z are global because they aren’t assigned in the function; x is global because it was listed in a global statement to map it to the module’s scope explicitly. Without the global here, x would be considered local by virtue of the assignment.

Notice that y and z are not declared global; Python’s LEGB lookup rule finds them in the module automatically. Also, notice that x might not exist in the enclosing module before the function runs; in this case, the assignment in the function creates x in the module.

Minimize Global Variables

By default, names assigned in functions are locals, so if you want to change names outside functions you have to write extra code (e.g., global statements). This is by design—as is common in Python, you have to say more to do the potentially “wrong” thing. Although there are times when globals are useful, variables assigned in a def are local by default because that is normally the best policy. Changing globals can lead to well-known software engineering problems: because the variables’ values are dependent on the order of calls to arbitrarily distant functions, programs can become difficult to debug.

Consider this module file, for example:

X = 99
def func1():
    global X
    X = 88

def func2():
    global X
    X = 77

Now, imagine that it is your job to modify or reuse this module file. What will the value of X be here? Really, that question has no meaning unless it’s qualified with a point of reference in time—the value of X is timing-dependent, as it depends on which function was called last (something we can’t tell from this file alone).

The net effect is that to understand this code, you have to trace the flow of control through the entire program. And, if you need to reuse or modify the code, you have to keep the entire program in your head all at once. In this case, you can’t really use one of these functions without bringing along the other. They are dependent on (that is, coupled with) the global variable. This is the problem with globals—they generally make code more difficult to understand and use than code consisting of self-contained functions that rely on locals.

On the other hand, short of using object-oriented programming and classes, global variables are probably the most straightforward way to retain shared state information (information that a function needs to remember for use the next time it is called) in Python—local variables disappear when the function returns, but globals do not. Other techniques, such as default mutable arguments and enclosing function scopes, can achieve this, too, but they are more complex than pushing values out to the global scope for retention.

Some programs designate a single module to collect globals; as long as this is expected, it is not as harmful. In addition, programs that use multithreading to do parallel processing in Python commonly depend on global variables—they become shared memory between functions running in parallel threads, and so act as a communication device.[38]

For now, though, especially if you are relatively new to programming, avoid the temptation to use globals whenever you can—try to communicate with passed-in arguments and return values instead. Six months from now, both you and your coworkers will be happy you did.

Minimize Cross-File Changes

Here’s another scope-related issue: although we can change variables in another file directly, we usually shouldn’t. Module files were introduced in Chapter 3 and are covered in more depth in the next part of this book. To illustrate their relationship to scopes, consider these two module files:

# first.py
X = 99                    # This code doesn't know about second.py

# second.py
import first
print(first.X)            # Okay: references a name in another file
first.X = 88              # But changing it can be too subtle and implicit

The first defines a variable X, which the second prints and then changes by assignment. Notice that we must import the first module into the second file to get to its variable at all—as we’ve learned, each module is a self-contained namespace (package of variables), and we must import one module to see inside it from another. That’s the main point about modules: by segregating variables on a per-file basis, they avoid name collisions across files.

Really, though, in terms of this chapter’s topic, the global scope of a module file becomes the attribute namespace of the module object once it is imported—importers automatically have access to all of the file’s global variables, because a file’s global scope morphs into an object’s attribute namespace when it is imported.

After importing the first module, the second module prints its variable and then assigns it a new value. Referencing the module’s variable to print it is fine—this is how modules are linked together into a larger system normally. The problem with the assignment, however, is that it is far too implicit: whoever’s charged with maintaining or reusing the first module probably has no clue that some arbitrarily far-removed module on the import chain can change X out from under him at runtime. In fact, the second module may be in a completely different directory, and so difficult to notice at all.

Although such cross-file variable changes are always possible in Python, they are usually much more subtle than you will want. Again, this sets up too strong a coupling between the two files—because they are both dependent on the value of the variable X, it’s difficult to understand or reuse one file without the other. Such implicit cross-file dependencies can lead to inflexible code at best, and outright bugs at worst.

Here again, the best prescription is generally to not do this—the best way to communicate across file boundaries is to call functions, passing in arguments and getting back return values. In this specific case, we would probably be better off coding an accessor function to manage the change:

# first.py
X = 99

def setX(new):
    global X
    X = new

# second.py
import first
first.setX(88)

This requires more code and may seem like a trivial change, but it makes a huge difference in terms of readability and maintainability—when a person reading the first module by itself sees a function, that person will know that it is a point of interface and will expect the change to the X. In other words, it removes the element of surprise that is rarely a good thing in software projects. Although we cannot prevent cross-file changes from happening, common sense dictates that they should be minimized unless widely accepted across the program.

Other Ways to Access Globals

Interestingly, because global-scope variables morph into the attributes of a loaded module object, we can emulate the global statement by importing the enclosing module and assigning to its attributes, as in the following example module file. Code in this file imports the enclosing module, first by name, and then by indexing the sys.modules loaded modules table (more on this table in Chapter 21):

# thismod.py

var = 99                              # Global variable == module attribute

def local():
    var = 0                           # Change local var

def glob1():
    global var                        # Declare global (normal)
    var += 1                          # Change global var

def glob2():
    var = 0                           # Change local var
    import thismod                    # Import myself
    thismod.var += 1                  # Change global var

def glob3():
    var = 0                           # Change local var
    import sys                        # Import system table
    glob = sys.modules['thismod']     # Get module object (or use __name__)
    glob.var += 1                     # Change global var

def test():
    print(var)
    local(); glob1(); glob2(); glob3()
    print(var)

When run, this adds 3 to the global variable (only the first function does not impact it):

>>> import thismod
>>> thismod.test()
99
102
>>> thismod.var
102

This works, and it illustrates the equivalence of globals to module attributes, but it’s much more work than using the global statement to make your intentions explicit.

As we’ve seen, global allows us to change names in a module outside a function. It has a cousin named nonlocal that can be used to change names in enclosing functions, too, but to understand how that can be useful, we first need to explore enclosing functions in general.

Scopes and Nested Functions

So far, I’ve omitted one part of Python’s scope rules on purpose, because it’s relatively rare to encounter it in practice. However, it’s time to take a deeper look at the letter E in the LEGB lookup rule. The E layer is fairly new (it was added in Python 2.2); it takes the form of the local scopes of any and all enclosing function defs. Enclosing scopes are sometimes also called statically nested scopes. Really, the nesting is a lexical one—nested scopes correspond to physically and syntactically nested code structures in your program’s source code.

Nested Scope Details

With the addition of nested function scopes, variable lookup rules become slightly more complex. Within a function:

A reference (X) looks for the name X first in the current local scope (function); then in the local scopes of any lexically enclosing functions in your source code, from inner to outer; then in the current global scope (the module file); and finally in the built-in scope (the module builtins). global declarations make the search begin in the global (module file) scope instead.

An assignment (X = value) creates or changes the name X in the current local scope, by default. If X is declared global within the function, the assignment creates or changes the name X in the enclosing module’s scope instead. If, on the other hand, X is declared nonlocal within the function, the assignment changes the name X in the closest enclosing function’s local scope.

Notice that the global declaration still maps variables to the enclosing module. When nested functions are present, variables in enclosing functions may be referenced, but they require nonlocal declarations to be changed.

Nested Scope Examples

To clarify the prior section’s points, let’s illustrate with some real code. Here is what an enclosing function scope looks like:

X = 99                   # Global scope name: not used

def f1():
    X = 88               # Enclosing def local
    def f2():
        print(X)         # Reference made in nested def
    f2()

f1()                     # Prints 88: enclosing def local

First off, this is legal Python code: the def is simply an executable statement, which can appear anywhere any other statement can—including nested in another def. Here, the nested def runs while a call to the function f1 is running; it generates a function and assigns it to the name f2, a local variable within f1’s local scope. In a sense, f2 is a temporary function that lives only during the execution of (and is visible only to code in) the enclosing f1.

But notice what happens inside f2: when it prints the variable X, it refers to the X that lives in the enclosing f1 function’s local scope. Because functions can access names in all physically enclosing def statements, the X in f2 is automatically mapped to the X in f1, by the LEGB lookup rule.

This enclosing scope lookup works even if the enclosing function has already returned. For example, the following code defines a function that makes and returns another function:

def f1():
    X = 88
    def f2():
        print(X)         # Remembers X in enclosing def scope
    return f2            # Return f2 but don't call it

action = f1()            # Make, return function
action()                 # Call it now: prints 88

In this code, the call to action is really running the function we named f2 when f1 ran. f2 remembers the enclosing scope’s X in f1, even though f1 is no longer active.

Factory functions

Depending on whom you ask, this sort of behavior is also sometimes called a closure or factory function. These terms refer to a function object that remembers values in enclosing scopes regardless of whether those scopes are still present in memory. Although classes (described in Part VI of this book) are usually best at remembering state because they make it explicit with attribute assignments, such functions provide an alternative.

For instance, factory functions are sometimes used by programs that need to generate event handlers on the fly in response to conditions at runtime (e.g., user inputs that cannot be anticipated). Look at the following function, for example:

>>> def maker(N):
...     def action(X):                    # Make and return action
...         return X ** N                 # action retains N from enclosing scope
...     return action
...

This defines an outer function that simply generates and returns a nested function, without calling it. If we call the outer function:

>>> f = maker(2)                          # Pass 2 to N
>>> f
<function action at 0x014720B0>

what we get back is a reference to the generated nested function—the one created by running the nested def. If we now call what we got back from the outer function:

>>> f(3)                                  # Pass 3 to X, N remembers 2: 3 ** 2
9
>>> f(4)                                  # 4 ** 2
16

it invokes the nested function—the one called action within maker. The most unusual part of this is that the nested function remembers integer 2, the value of the variable N in maker, even though maker has returned and exited by the time we call action. In effect, N from the enclosing local scope is retained as state information attached to action, and we get back its argument squared.

If we now call the outer function again, we get back a new nested function with different state information attached. That is, we get the argument cubed instead of squared, but the original still squares as before:

>>> g = maker(3)                          # g remembers 3, f remembers 2
>>> g(3)                                  # 3 ** 3
27
>>> f(3)                                  # 3 ** 2
9

This works because each call to a factory function like this gets its own set of state information. In our case, the function we assign to name g remembers 3, and f remembers 2, because each has its own state information retained by the variable N in maker.

This is an advanced technique that you’re unlikely to see very often in most code, except among programmers with backgrounds in functional programming languages. On the other hand, enclosing scopes are often employed by lambda function-creation expressions (discussed later in this chapter)—because they are expressions, they are almost always nested within a def. Moreover, function nesting is commonly used for decorators (explored in Chapter 38)—in some cases, it’s the most reasonable coding pattern.

As a general rule, classes are better at “memory” like this because they make the state retention explicit in attributes. Short of using classes, though, globals, enclosing scope references like these, and default arguments are the main ways that Python functions can retain state information. To see how they compete, Chapter 18 provides complete coverage of defaults, but the next section gives enough of an introduction to get us started.

Retaining enclosing scopes’ state with defaults

In earlier versions of Python, the sort of code in the prior section failed because nested defs did not do anything about scopes—a reference to a variable within f2 would search only the local (f2), then global (the code outside f1), and then built-in scopes. Because it skipped the scopes of enclosing functions, an error would result. To work around this, programmers typically used default argument values to pass in and remember the objects in an enclosing scope:

def f1():
    x = 88
    def f2(x=x):                # Remember enclosing scope X with defaults
        print(x)
    f2()

f1()                            # Prints 88

This code works in all Python releases, and you’ll still see this pattern in some existing Python code. In short, the syntax arg = val in a def header means that the argument arg will default to the value val if no real value is passed to arg in a call.

In the modified f2 here, the x=x means that the argument x will default to the value of x in the enclosing scope—because the second x is evaluated before Python steps into the nested def, it still refers to the x in f1. In effect, the default remembers what x was in f1 (i.e., the object 88).

That’s fairly complex, and it depends entirely on the timing of default value evaluations. In fact, the nested scope lookup rule was added to Python to make defaults unnecessary for this role—today, Python automatically remembers any values required in the enclosing scope for use in nested defs.

Of course, the best prescription for most code is simply to avoid nesting defs within defs, as it will make your programs much simpler. The following is an equivalent of the prior example that banishes the notion of nesting. Notice the forward reference in this code—it’s OK to call a function defined after the function that calls it, as long as the second def runs before the first function is actually called. Code inside a def is never evaluated until the function is actually called:

>>> def f1():
...     x = 88                  # Pass x along instead of nesting
...     f2(x)                   # Forward reference okay
...
>>> def f2(x):
...     print(x)
...
>>> f1()
88

If you avoid nesting this way, you can almost forget about the nested scopes concept in Python, unless you need to code in the factory function style discussed earlier—at least, for def statements. lambdas, which almost naturally appear nested in defs, often rely on nested scopes, as the next section explains.

Nested scopes and lambdas

While they’re rarely used in practice for defs themselves, you are more likely to care about nested function scopes when you start coding lambda expressions. We won’t cover lambda in depth until Chapter 19, but in short, it’s an expression that generates a new function to be called later, much like a def statement. Because it’s an expression, though, it can be used in places that def cannot, such as within list and dictionary literals.

Like a def, a lambda expression introduces a new local scope for the function it creates. Thanks to the enclosing scopes lookup layer, lambdas can see all the variables that live in the functions in which they are coded. Thus, the following code works, but only because the nested scope rules are applied:

def func():
    x = 4
    action = (lambda n: x ** n)          # x remembered from enclosing def
    return action

x = func()
print(x(2))                              # Prints 16, 4 ** 2

Prior to the introduction of nested function scopes, programmers used defaults to pass values from an enclosing scope into lambdas, just as for defs. For instance, the following works on all Python releases:

def func():
    x = 4
    action = (lambda n, x=x: x ** n)     # Pass x in manually
    return action

Because lambdas are expressions, they naturally (and even normally) nest inside enclosing defs. Hence, they are perhaps the biggest beneficiaries of the addition of enclosing function scopes in the lookup rules; in most cases, it is no longer necessary to pass values into lambdas with defaults.

Scopes versus defaults with loop variables

There is one notable exception to the rule I just gave: if a lambda or def defined within a function is nested inside a loop, and the nested function references an enclosing scope variable that is changed by that loop, all functions generated within the loop will have the same value—the value the referenced variable had in the last loop iteration.

For instance, the following attempts to build up a list of functions that each remember the current variable i from the enclosing scope:

>>> def makeActions():
...     acts = []
...     for i in range(5):                       # Tries to remember each i
...         acts.append(lambda x: i ** x)        # All remember same last i!
...     return acts
...
>>> acts = makeActions()
>>> acts[0]
<function <lambda> at 0x012B16B0>

This doesn’t quite work, though—because the enclosing scope variable is looked up when the nested functions are later called, they all effectively remember the same value (the value the loop variable had on the last loop iteration). That is, we get back 4 to the power of 2 for each function in the list, because i is the same in all of them:

>>> acts[0](2)                                   # All are 4 ** 2, value of last i
16
>>> acts[2](2)                                   # This should be 2 ** 2
16
>>> acts[4](2)                                   # This should be 4 ** 2
16

This is the one case where we still have to explicitly retain enclosing scope values with default arguments, rather than enclosing scope references. That is, to make this sort of code work, we must pass in the current value of the enclosing scope’s variable with a default. Because defaults are evaluated when the nested function is created (not when it’s later called), each remembers its own value for i:

>>> def makeActions():
...     acts = []
...     for i in range(5):                       # Use defaults instead
...         acts.append(lambda x, i=i: i ** x)   # Remember current i
...     return acts
...
>>> acts = makeActions()
>>> acts[0](2)                                   # 0 ** 2
0
>>> acts[2](2)                                   # 2 ** 2
4
>>> acts[4](2)                                   # 4 ** 2
16

This is a fairly obscure case, but it can come up in practice, especially in code that generates callback handler functions for a number of widgets in a GUI (e.g., button-press handlers). We’ll talk more about defaults in Chapter 18 and lambdas in Chapter 19, so you may want to return and review this section later.[39]

Arbitrary scope nesting

Before ending this discussion, I should note that scopes may nest arbitrarily, but only enclosing function def statements (not classes, described in Part VI) are searched:

>>> def f1():
...     x = 99
...     def f2():
...         def f3():
...             print(x)        # Found in f1's local scope!
...         f3()
...     f2()
...
>>> f1()
99

Python will search the local scopes of all enclosing defs, from inner to outer, after the referencing function’s local scope and before the module’s global scope or built-ins. However, this sort of code is even less likely to pop up in practice. In Python, we say flat is better than nested—except in very limited contexts, your life (and the lives of your coworkers) will generally be better if you minimize nested function definitions.

The nonlocal Statement

In the prior section we explored the way that nested functions can reference variables in an enclosing function’s scope, even if that function has already returned. It turns out that, as of Python 3.0, we can also change such enclosing scope variables, as long as we declare them in nonlocal statements. With this statement, nested defs can have both read and write access to names in enclosing functions.

The nonlocal statement is a close cousin to global, covered earlier. Like global, nonlocal declares that a name will be changed in an enclosing scope. Unlike global, though, nonlocal applies to a name in an enclosing function’s scope, not the global module scope outside all defs. Also unlike global, nonlocal names must already exist in the enclosing function’s scope when declared—they can exist only in enclosing functions and cannot be created by a first assignment in a nested def.

In other words, nonlocal both allows assignment to names in enclosing function scopes and limits scope lookups for such names to enclosing defs. The net effect is a more direct and reliable implementation of changeable state information, for programs that do not desire or need classes with attributes.

nonlocal Basics

Python 3.0 introduces a new nonlocal statement, which has meaning only inside a function:

def func():
    nonlocal name1, name2, ...

This statement allows a nested function to change one or more names defined in a syntactically enclosing function’s scope. In Python 2.X (including 2.6), when one function def is nested in another, the nested function can reference any of the names defined by assignment in the enclosing def’s scope, but it cannot change them. In 3.0, declaring the enclosing scopes’ names in a nonlocal statement enables nested functions to assign and thus change such names as well.

This provides a way for enclosing functions to provide writeable state information, remembered when the nested function is later called. Allowing the state to change makes it more useful to the nested function (imagine a counter in the enclosing scope, for instance). In 2.X, programmers usually achieve similar goals by using classes or other schemes. Because nested functions have become a more common coding pattern for state retention, though, nonlocal makes it more generally applicable.

Besides allowing names in enclosing defs to be changed, the nonlocal statement also forces the issue for references—just like the global statement, nonlocal causes searches for the names listed in the statement to begin in the enclosing defs’ scopes, not in the local scope of the declaring function. That is, nonlocal also means “skip my local scope entirely.”

In fact, the names listed in a nonlocal must have been previously defined in an enclosing def when the nonlocal is reached, or an error is raised. The net effect is much like global: global means the names reside in the enclosing module, and nonlocal means they reside in an enclosing def. nonlocal is even more strict, though—scope search is restricted to only enclosing defs. That is, nonlocal names can appear only in enclosing defs, not in the module’s global scope or built-in scopes outside the defs.

The addition of nonlocal does not alter name reference scope rules in general; they still work as before, per the “LEGB” rule described earlier. The nonlocal statement mostly serves to allow names in enclosing scopes to be changed rather than just referenced. However, global and nonlocal statements do both restrict the lookup rules somewhat, when coded in a function:

global makes scope lookup begin in the enclosing module’s scope and allows names there to be assigned. Scope lookup continues on to the built-in scope if the name does not exist in the module, but assignments to global names always create or change them in the module’s scope.

nonlocal restricts scope lookup to just enclosing defs, requires that the names already exist there, and allows them to be assigned. Scope lookup does not continue on to the global or built-in scopes.

In Python 2.6, references to enclosing def scope names are allowed, but not assignment. However, you can still use classes with explicit attributes to achieve the same changeable state information effect as nonlocals (and you may be better off doing so in some contexts); globals and function attributes can sometimes accomplish similar goals as well. More on this in a moment; first, let’s turn to some working code to make this more concrete.

nonlocal in Action

On to some examples, all run in 3.0. References to enclosing def scopes work as they do in 2.6. In the following, tester builds and returns the function nested, to be called later, and the state reference in nested maps the local scope of tester using the normal scope lookup rules:

C:\\misc>c:\python30\python

>>> def tester(start):
...     state = start             # Referencing nonlocals works normally
...     def nested(label):
...         print(label, state)   # Remembers state in enclosing scope
...     return nested
...
>>> F = tester(0)
>>> F('spam')
spam 0
>>> F('ham')
ham 0

Changing a name in an enclosing def’s scope is not allowed by default, though; this is the normal case in 2.6 as well:

>>> def tester(start):
...     state = start
...     def nested(label):
...         print(label, state)
...         state += 1            # Cannot change by default (or in 2.6)
...     return nested
...
>>> F = tester(0)
>>> F('spam')
UnboundLocalError: local variable 'state' referenced before assignment

Using nonlocal for changes

Now, under 3.0, if we declare state in the tester scope as nonlocal within nested, we get to change it inside the nested function, too. This works even though tester has returned and exited by the time we call the returned nested function through the name F:

>>> def tester(start):
...     state = start             # Each call gets its own state
...     def nested(label):
...         nonlocal state        # Remembers state in enclosing scope
...         print(label, state)
...         state += 1            # Allowed to change it if nonlocal
...     return nested
...
>>> F = tester(0)
>>> F('spam')                     # Increments state on each call
spam 0
>>> F('ham')
ham 1
>>> F('eggs')
eggs 2

As usual with enclosing scope references, we can call the tester factory function multiple times to get multiple copies of its state in memory. The state object in the enclosing scope is essentially attached to the nested function object returned; each call makes a new, distinct state object, such that updating one function’s state won’t impact the other. The following continues the prior listing’s interaction:

>>> G = tester(42)                # Make a new tester that starts at 42
>>> G('spam')
spam 42

>>> G('eggs')                     # My state information updated to 43
eggs 43

>>> F('bacon')                    # But F's is where it left off: at 3
bacon 3                           # Each call has different state information

Boundary cases

There are a few things to watch out for. First, unlike the global statement, nonlocal names really must have previously been assigned in an enclosing def’s scope when a nonlocal is evaluated, or else you’ll get an error—you cannot create them dynamically by assigning them anew in the enclosing scope:

>>> def tester(start):
...     def nested(label):
...         nonlocal state        # Nonlocals must already exist in enclosing def!
...         state = 0
...         print(label, state)
...     return nested
...
SyntaxError: no binding for nonlocal 'state' found

>>> def tester(start):
...     def nested(label):
...         global state          # Globals don't have to exist yet when declared
...         state = 0             # This creates the name in the module now
...         print(label, state)
...     return nested
...
>>> F = tester(0)
>>> F('abc')
abc 0
>>> state
0

Second, nonlocal restricts the scope lookup to just enclosing defs; nonlocals are not looked up in the enclosing module’s global scope or the built-in scope outside all defs, even if they are already there:

>>> spam = 99
>>> def tester():
...     def nested():
...         nonlocal spam         # Must be in a def, not the module!
...         print('Current=', spam)
...         spam += 1
...     return nested
...
SyntaxError: no binding for nonlocal 'spam' found

These restrictions make sense once you realize that Python would not otherwise generally know which enclosing scope to create a brand new name in. In the prior listing, should spam be assigned in tester, or the module outside? Because this is ambiguous, Python must resolve nonlocals at function creation time, not function call time.

Why nonlocal?

Given the extra complexity of nested functions, you might wonder what the fuss is about. Although it’s difficult to see in our small examples, state information becomes crucial in many programs. There are a variety of ways to “remember” information across function and method calls in Python. While there are tradeoffs for all, nonlocal does improve this story for enclosing scope references—the nonlocal statement allows multiple copies of changeable state to be retained in memory and addresses simple state-retention needs where classes may not be warranted.

As we saw in the prior section, the following code allows state to be retained and modified in an enclosing scope. Each call to tester creates a little self-contained package of changeable information, whose names do not clash with any other part of the program:

def tester(start):
    state = start                      # Each call gets its own state
    def nested(label):
        nonlocal state                 # Remembers state in enclosing scope
        print(label, state)
        state += 1                     # Allowed to change it if nonlocal
    return nested

F = tester(0)
F('spam')

Unfortunately, this code only works in Python 3.0. If you are using Python 2.6, other options are available, depending on your goals. The next three sections present some alternatives.

Shared state with globals

One usual prescription for achieving the nonlocal effect in 2.6 and earlier is to simply move the state out to the global scope (the enclosing module):

>>> def tester(start):
...     global state                   # Move it out to the module to change it
...     state = start                  # global allows changes in module scope
...     def nested(label):
...         global state
...         print(label, state)
...         state += 1
...     return nested
...
>>> F = tester(0)
>>> F('spam')                          # Each call increments shared global state
spam 0
>>> F('eggs')
eggs 1

This works in this case, but it requires global declarations in both functions and is prone to name collisions in the global scope (what if “state” is already being used?). A worse, and more subtle, problem is that it only allows for a single shared copy of the state information in the module scope—if we call tester again, we’ll wind up resetting the module’s state variable, such that prior calls will see their state overwritten:

>>> G = tester(42)                     # Resets state's single copy in global scope
>>> G('toast')
toast 42

>>> G('bacon')
bacon 43

>>> F('ham')                           # Oops -- my counter has been overwritten!
ham 44

As shown earlier, when using nonlocal instead of global, each call to tester remembers its own unique copy of the state object.

State with classes (preview)

The other prescription for changeable state information in 2.6 and earlier is to use classes with attributes to make state information access more explicit than the implicit magic of scope lookup rules. As an added benefit, each instance of a class gets a fresh copy of the state information, as a natural byproduct of Python’s object model.

We haven’t explored classes in detail yet, but as a brief preview, here is a reformulation of the tester/nested functions used earlier as a class—state is recorded in objects explicitly as they are created. To make sense of this code, you need to know that a def within a class like this works exactly like a def outside of a class, except that the function’s self argument automatically receives the implied subject of the call (an instance object created by calling the class itself):

>>> class tester:                          # Class-based alternative (see Part VI)
...     def __init__(self, start):         # On object construction,
...         self.state = start             # save state explicitly in new object
...     def nested(self, label):
...         print(label, self.state)       # Reference state explicitly
...         self.state += 1                # Changes are always allowed
...
>>> F = tester(0)                          # Create instance, invoke __init__
>>> F.nested('spam')                       # F is passed to self
spam 0
>>> F.nested('ham')
ham 1

>>> G = tester(42)                         # Each instance gets new copy of state
>>> G.nested('toast')                      # Changing one does not impact others
toast 42
>>> G.nested('bacon')
bacon 43

>>> F.nested('eggs')                       # F's state is where it left off
eggs 2
>>> F.state                                # State may be accessed outside class
3

With just slightly more magic, which we’ll delve into later in this book, we could also make our class look like a callable function using operator overloading. __call__ intercepts direct calls on an instance, so we don’t need to call a named method:

>>> class tester:
...     def __init__(self, start):
...         self.state = start
...     def __call__(self, label):         # Intercept direct instance calls
...         print(label, self.state)       # So .nested() not required
...         self.state += 1
...
>>> H = tester(99)
>>> H('juice')                             # Invokes __call__
juice 99
>>> H('pancakes')
pancakes 100

Don’t sweat the details in this code too much at this point in the book; we’ll explore classes in depth in Part VI and will look at specific operator overloading tools like __call__ in Chapter 29, so you may wish to file this code away for future reference. The point here is that classes can make state information more obvious, by leveraging explicit attribute assignment instead of scope lookups.

While using classes for state information is generally a good rule of thumb to follow, they might be overkill in cases like this, where state is a single counter. Such trivial state cases are more common than you might think; in such contexts, nested defs are sometimes more lightweight than coding classes, especially if you’re not familiar with OOP yet. Moreover, there are some scenarios in which nested defs may actually work better than classes (see the description of method decorators in Chapter 38 for an example that is far beyond this chapter’s scope).

State with function attributes

As a final state-retention option, we can also sometimes achieve the same effect as nonlocals with function attributes—user-defined names attached to functions directly. Here’s a final version of our example based on this technique—it replaces a nonlocal with an attribute attached to the nested function. Although this scheme may not be as intuitive to some, it also allows the state variable to be accessed outside the nested function (with nonlocals, we can only see state variables within the nested def):

>>> def tester(start):
...     def nested(label):
...         print(label, nested.state)     # nested is in enclosing scope
...         nested.state += 1              # Change attr, not nested itself
...     nested.state = start               # Initial state after func defined
...     return nested
...
>>> F = tester(0)
>>> F('spam')                              # F is a 'nested' with state attached
spam 0
>>> F('ham')
ham 1
>>> F.state                                # Can access state outside functions too
2
>>>
>>> G = tester(42)                         # G has own state, doesn't overwrite F's
>>> G('eggs')
eggs 42
>>> F('ham')
ham 2

This code relies on the fact that the function name nested is a local variable in the tester scope enclosing nested; as such, it can be referenced freely inside nested. This code also relies on the fact that changing an object in-place is not an assignment to a name; when it increments nested.state, it is changing part of the object nested references, not the name nested itself. Because we’re not really assigning a name in the enclosing scope, no nonlocal is needed.

As you can see, globals, nonlocals, classes, and function attributes all offer state-retention options. Globals only support shared data, classes require a basic knowledge of OOP, and both classes and function attributes allow state to be accessed outside the nested function itself. As usual, the best tool for your program depends upon your program’s goals.[40]

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

The output here is 'Spam', because the function references a global variable in the enclosing module (because it is not assigned in the function, it is considered global).

The output here is 'Spam' again because assigning the variable inside the function makes it a local and effectively hides the global of the same name. The print statement finds the variable unchanged in the global (module) scope.

It prints 'NI' on one line and 'Spam' on another, because the reference to the variable within the function finds the assigned local and the reference in the print statement finds the global.

This time it just prints 'NI' because the global declaration forces the variable assigned inside the function to refer to the variable in the enclosing global scope.

The output in this case is again 'NI' on one line and 'Spam' on another, because the print statement in the nested function finds the name in the enclosing function’s local scope, and the print at the end finds the variable in the global scope.

This example prints 'Spam', because the nonlocal statement (available in Python 3.0 but not 2.6) means that the assignment to X inside the nested function changes X in the enclosing function’s local scope. Without this statement, this assignment would classify X as local to the nested function, making it a different variable; the code would then print 'NI' instead.

Although the values of local variables go away when a function returns, you can make a Python function retain state information by using shared global variables, enclosing function scope references within nested functions, or using default argument values. Function attributes can sometimes allow state to be attached to the function itself, instead of looked up in scopes. Another alternative, using OOP with classes, sometimes supports state retention better than any of the scope-based techniques because it makes it explicit with attribute assignments; we’ll explore this option in Part VI.

[36] The scope lookup rule was called the “LGB rule” in the first edition of this book. The enclosing def “E” layer was added later in Python to obviate the task of passing in enclosing scope names explicitly with default arguments—a topic usually of marginal interest to Python beginners that we’ll defer until later in this chapter. Since this scope is addressed by the nonlocal statement in Python 3.0, I suppose the lookup rule might now be better named “LNGB,” but backward compatibility matters in books, too!

[37] There is technically one more scope in Python: loop variables in comprehension and generator expressions are local to the expression itself in 3.X (in 2.X, they are local in generators but not in list comprehensions). This is a special and obscure case that rarely impacts real code, and differs from for-loop statements which never localize their variables.

[38] Multithreading runs function calls in parallel with the rest of the program and is supported by Python’s standard library modules _thread, threading, and queue (thread, threading, and Queue in Python 2.6). Because all threaded functions run in the same process, global scopes often serve as shared memory between them. Threading is commonly used for long-running tasks in GUIs, to implement nonblocking operations in general and to leverage CPU capacity. It is also beyond this book’s scope; see the Python library manual, as well as the follow-up texts listed in the Preface (such as O’Reilly’s Programming Python), for more details.

[39] In the section Function Gotchas at the end of this part of the book, we’ll also see that there is an issue with using mutable objects like lists and dictionaries for default arguments (e.g., def f(a=[]))—because defaults are implemented as single objects attached to functions, mutable defaults retain state from call to call, rather then being initialized anew on each call. Depending on whom you ask, this is either considered a feature that supports state retention, or a strange wart on the language. More on this at the end of Chapter 20.

[40] Function attributes are supported in both Python 2.6 and 3.X. We'll explore them further in Chapter 19, and revisit all the state options introduced here in Chapter 38 in a more realistic context. Also note that it's possible to change a mutable object in the enclosing scope in 2.X and 3.X without declaring its name nonlocal (e.g, state=[start] in tester, state[0]+=1 in nested), though it's perhaps more obscure than either function attributes or 3.X's nonlocal.

Special Argument-Matching Modes

As we’ve just seen, arguments are always passed by assignment in Python; names in the def header are assigned to passed-in objects. On top of this model, though, Python provides additional tools that alter the way the argument objects in a call are matched with argument names in the header prior to assignment. These tools are all optional, but they allow us to write functions that support more flexible calling patterns, and you may encounter some libraries that require them.

By default, arguments are matched by position, from left to right, and you must pass exactly as many arguments as there are argument names in the function header. However, you can also specify matching by name, default values, and collectors for extra arguments.

The Basics

Before we go into the syntactic details, I want to stress that these special modes are optional and only have to do with matching objects to names; the underlying passing mechanism after the matching takes place is still assignment. In fact, some of these tools are intended more for people writing libraries than for application developers. But because you may stumble across these modes even if you don’t code them yourself, here’s a synopsis of the available tools:

Positionals: matched from left to right

The normal case, which we’ve mostly been using so far, is to match passed argument values to argument names in a function header by position, from left to right.

Keywords: matched by argument name

Alternatively, callers can specify which argument in the function is to receive a value by using the argument’s name in the call, with the name=value syntax.

Defaults: specify values for arguments that aren’t passed

Functions themselves can specify default values for arguments to receive if the call passes too few values, again using the name=value syntax.

Varargs collecting: collect arbitrarily many positional or keyword arguments

Functions can use special arguments preceded with one or two * characters to collect an arbitrary number of extra arguments (this feature is often referred to as varargs, after the varargs feature in the C language, which also supports variable-length argument lists).

Varargs unpacking: pass arbitrarily many positional or keyword arguments

Callers can also use the * syntax to unpack argument collections into discrete, separate arguments. This is the inverse of a * in a function header—in the header it means collect arbitrarily many arguments, while in the call it means pass arbitrarily many arguments.

Keyword-only arguments: arguments that must be passed by name

In Python 3.0 (but not 2.6), functions can also specify arguments that must be passed by name with keyword arguments, not by position. Such arguments are typically used to define configuration options in addition to actual arguments.

Matching Syntax

Table 18-1 summarizes the syntax that invokes the special argument-matching modes.

Table 18-1. Function argument-matching forms

Syntax

|

Location

|

Interpretation

func(value)

|

Caller

|

Normal argument: matched by position

func(name=value)

|

Caller

|

Keyword argument: matched by name

func(*sequence)

|

Caller

|

Pass all objects in sequence as individual positional arguments

func(**dict)

|

Caller

|

Pass all key/value pairs in dict as individual keyword arguments

def func(name)

|

Function

|

Normal argument: matches any passed value by position or name

def func(name=value)

|

Function

|

Default argument value, if not passed in the call

def func(*name)

|

Function

|

Matches and collects remaining positional arguments in a tuple

def func(**name)

|

Function

|

Matches and collects remaining keyword arguments in a dictionary

def func(*args, name)

def func(*, name=value)

|

Function

|

Arguments that must be passed by keyword only in calls (3.0)

These special matching modes break down into function calls and definitions as follows:

In a function call (the first four rows of the table), simple values are matched by position, but using the name=value form tells Python to match by name to arguments instead; these are called keyword arguments. Using a *sequence or **dict in a call allows us to package up arbitrarily many positional or keyword objects in sequences and dictionaries, respectively, and unpack them as separate, individual arguments when they are passed to the function.

In a function header (the rest of the table), a simple name is matched by position or name depending on how the caller passes it, but the name=value form specifies a default value. The *name form collects any extra unmatched positional arguments in a tuple, and the **name form collects extra keyword arguments in a dictionary. In Python 3.0 and later, any normal or defaulted argument names following a *name or a bare * are keyword-only arguments and must be passed by keyword in calls.

Of these, keyword arguments and defaults are probably the most commonly used in Python code. We’ve informally used both of these earlier in this book:

We’ve already used keywords to specify options to the 3.0 print function, but they are more general—keywords allow us to label any argument with its name, to make calls more informational.

We met defaults earlier, too, as a way to pass in values from the enclosing function’s scope, but they are also more general—they allow us to make any argument optional, providing its default value in a function definition.

As we’ll see, the combination of defaults in a function header and keywords in a call further allows us to pick and choose which defaults to override.

In short, special argument-matching modes let you be fairly liberal about how many arguments must be passed to a function. If a function specifies defaults, they are used if you pass too few arguments. If a function uses the * variable argument list forms, you can pass too many arguments; the * names collect the extra arguments in data structures for processing in the function.

The Gritty Details

If you choose to use and combine the special argument-matching modes, Python will ask you to follow these ordering rules:

In a function call, arguments must appear in this order: any positional arguments (value), followed by a combination of any keyword arguments (name=value) and the *sequence form, followed by the **dict form.

In a function header, arguments must appear in this order: any normal arguments (name), followed by any default arguments (name=value), followed by the *name (or * in 3.0) form if present, followed by any name or name=value keyword-only arguments (in 3.0), followed by the **name form.

In both the call and header, the **arg form must appear last if present. If you mix arguments in any other order, you will get a syntax error because the combinations can be ambiguous. The steps that Python internally carries out to match arguments before assignment can roughly be described as follows:

Assign nonkeyword arguments by position.

Assign keyword arguments by matching names.

Assign extra nonkeyword arguments to *name tuple.

Assign extra keyword arguments to **name dictionary.

Assign default values to unassigned arguments in header.

After this, Python checks to make sure each argument is passed just one value; if not, an error is raised. When all matching is complete, Python assigns argument names to the objects passed to them.

The actual matching algorithm Python uses is a bit more complex (it must also account for keyword-only arguments in 3.0, for instance), so we’ll defer to Python’s standard language manual for a more exact description. It’s not required reading, but tracing Python’s matching algorithm may help you to understand some convoluted cases, especially when modes are mixed.

Note

In Python 3.0, argument names in a function header can also have annotation values, specified as name:value (or name:value=default when defaults are present). This is simply additional syntax for arguments and does not augment or change the argument-ordering rules described here. The function itself can also have an annotation value, given as def f()->value. See the discussion of function annotation in Chapter 19 for more details.

Keyword and Default Examples

This is all simpler in code than the preceding descriptions may imply. If you don’t use any special matching syntax, Python matches names by position from left to right, like most other languages. For instance, if you define a function that requires three arguments, you must call it with three arguments:

>>> def f(a, b, c): print(a, b, c)
...

Here, we pass them by position—a is matched to 1, b is matched to 2, and so on (this works the same in Python 3.0 and 2.6, but extra tuple parentheses are displayed in 2.6 because we’re using 3.0 print calls):

>>> f(1, 2, 3)
1 2 3

Keywords

In Python, though, you can be more specific about what goes where when you call a function. Keyword arguments allow us to match by name, instead of by position:

>>> f(c=3, b=2, a=1)
1 2 3

The c=3 in this call, for example, means send 3 to the argument named c. More formally, Python matches the name c in the call to the argument named c in the function definition’s header, and then passes the value 3 to that argument. The net effect of this call is the same as that of the prior call, but notice that the left-to-right order of the arguments no longer matters when keywords are used because arguments are matched by name, not by position. It’s even possible to combine positional and keyword arguments in a single call. In this case, all positionals are matched first from left to right in the header, before keywords are matched by name:

>>> f(1, c=3, b=2)
1 2 3

When most people see this the first time, they wonder why one would use such a tool. Keywords typically have two roles in Python. First, they make your calls a bit more self-documenting (assuming that you use better argument names than a, b, and c). For example, a call of this form:

func(name='Bob', age=40, job='dev')

is much more meaningful than a call with three naked values separated by commas—the keywords serve as labels for the data in the call. The second major use of keywords occurs in conjunction with defaults, which we turn to next.

Defaults

We talked about defaults in brief earlier, when discussing nested function scopes. In short, defaults allow us to make selected function arguments optional; if not passed a value, the argument is assigned its default before the function runs. For example, here is a function that requires one argument and defaults two:

>>> def f(a, b=2, c=3): print(a, b, c)
...

When we call this function, we must provide a value for a, either by position or by keyword; however, providing values for b and c is optional. If we don’t pass values to b and c, they default to 2 and 3, respectively:

>>> f(1)
1 2 3
>>> f(a=1)
1 2 3

If we pass two values, only c gets its default, and with three values, no defaults are used:

>>> f(1, 4)
1 4 3
>>> f(1, 4, 5)
1 4 5

Finally, here is how the keyword and default features interact. Because they subvert the normal left-to-right positional mapping, keywords allow us to essentially skip over arguments with defaults:

>>> f(1, c=6)
1 2 6

Here, a gets 1 by position, c gets 6 by keyword, and b, in between, defaults to 2.

Be careful not to confuse the special name=value syntax in a function header and a function call; in the call it means a match-by-name keyword argument, while in the header it specifies a default for an optional argument. In both cases, this is not an assignment statement (despite its appearance); it is special syntax for these two contexts, which modifies the default argument-matching mechanics.

Combining keywords and defaults

Here is a slightly larger example that demonstrates keywords and defaults in action. In the following, the caller must always pass at least two arguments (to match spam and eggs), but the other two are optional. If they are omitted, Python assigns toast and ham to the defaults specified in the header:

def func(spam, eggs, toast=0, ham=0):   # First 2 required
    print((spam, eggs, toast, ham))

func(1, 2)                              # Output: (1, 2, 0, 0)
func(1, ham=1, eggs=0)                  # Output: (1, 0, 0, 1)
func(spam=1, eggs=0)                    # Output: (1, 0, 0, 0)
func(toast=1, eggs=2, spam=3)           # Output: (3, 2, 1, 0)
func(1, 2, 3, 4)                        # Output: (1, 2, 3, 4)

Notice again that when keyword arguments are used in the call, the order in which the arguments are listed doesn’t matter; Python matches by name, not by position. The caller must supply values for spam and eggs, but they can be matched by position or by name. Again, keep in mind that the form name=value means different things in the call and the def: a keyword in the call and a default in the header.

Arbitrary Arguments Examples

The last two matching extensions, * and **, are designed to support functions that take any number of arguments. Both can appear in either the function definition or a function call, and they have related purposes in the two locations.

Collecting arguments

The first use, in the function definition, collects unmatched positional arguments into a tuple:

>>> def f(*args): print(args)
...

When this function is called, Python collects all the positional arguments into a new tuple and assigns the variable args to that tuple. Because it is a normal tuple object, it can be indexed, stepped through with a for loop, and so on:

>>> f()
()
>>> f(1)
(1,)
>>> f(1, 2, 3, 4)
(1, 2, 3, 4)

The ** feature is similar, but it only works for keyword arguments—it collects them into a new dictionary, which can then be processed with normal dictionary tools. In a sense, the ** form allows you to convert from keywords to dictionaries, which you can then step through with keys calls, dictionary iterators, and the like:

>>> def f(**args): print(args)
...
>>> f()
{}
>>> f(a=1, b=2)
{'a': 1, 'b': 2}

Finally, function headers can combine normal arguments, the *, and the ** to implement wildly flexible call signatures. For instance, in the following, 1 is passed to a by position, 2 and 3 are collected into the pargs positional tuple, and x and y wind up in the kargs keyword dictionary:

>>> def f(a, *pargs, **kargs): print(a, pargs, kargs)
...
>>> f(1, 2, 3, x=1, y=2)
1 (2, 3) {'y': 2, 'x': 1}

In fact, these features can be combined in even more complex ways that may seem ambiguous at first glance—an idea we will revisit later in this chapter. First, though, let’s see what happens when * and ** are coded in function calls instead of definitions.

Unpacking arguments

In recent Python releases, we can use the * syntax when we call a function, too. In this context, its meaning is the inverse of its meaning in the function definition—it unpacks a collection of arguments, rather than building a collection of arguments. For example, we can pass four arguments to a function in a tuple and let Python unpack them into individual arguments:

>>> def func(a, b, c, d): print(a, b, c, d)
...
>>> args = (1, 2)
>>> args += (3, 4)
>>> func(*args)
1 2 3 4

Similarly, the ** syntax in a function call unpacks a dictionary of key/value pairs into separate keyword arguments:

>>> args = {'a': 1, 'b': 2, 'c': 3}
>>> args['d'] = 4
>>> func(**args)
1 2 3 4

Again, we can combine normal, positional, and keyword arguments in the call in very flexible ways:

>>> func(*(1, 2), **{'d': 4, 'c': 4})
1 2 4 4

>>> func(1, *(2, 3), **{'d': 4})
1 2 3 4

>>> func(1, c=3, *(2,), **{'d': 4})
1 2 3 4

>>> func(1, *(2, 3), d=4)
1 2 3 4

>>> func(1, *(2,), c=3, **{'d':4})
1 2 3 4

This sort of code is convenient when you cannot predict the number of arguments that will be passed to a function when you write your script; you can build up a collection of arguments at runtime instead and call the function generically this way. Again, don’t confuse the */** syntax in the function header and the function call—in the header it collects any number of arguments, while in the call it unpacks any number of arguments.

Note

As we saw in Chapter 14, the *pargs form in a call is an iteration context, so technically it accepts any iterable object, not just tuples or other sequences as shown in the examples here. For instance, a file object works after the *, and unpacks its lines into individual arguments (e.g., func(*open('fname')).

This generality is supported in both Python 3.0 and 2.6, but it holds true only for calls—a *pargs in a call allows any iterable, but the same form in a def header always bundles extra arguments into a tuple. This header behavior is similar in spirit and syntax to the * in Python 3.0 extended sequence unpacking assignment forms we met in Chapter 11 (e.g., x, *y = z), though that feature always creates lists, not tuples.

Applying functions generically

The prior section’s examples may seem obtuse, but they are used more often than you might expect. Some programs need to call arbitrary functions in a generic fashion, without knowing their names or arguments ahead of time. In fact, the real power of the special “varargs” call syntax is that you don’t need to know how many arguments a function call requires before you write a script. For example, you can use if logic to select from a set of functions and argument lists, and call any of them generically:

if <test>:
    action, args = func1, (1,)             # Call func1 with 1 arg in this case
else:
    action, args = func2, (1, 2, 3)        # Call func2 with 3 args here
...
action(*args)                              # Dispatch generically

More generally, this varargs call syntax is useful any time you cannot predict the arguments list. If your user selects an arbitrary function via a user interface, for instance, you may be unable to hardcode a function call when writing your script. To work around this, simply build up the arguments list with sequence operations, and call it with starred names to unpack the arguments:

>>> args = (2,3)
>>> args += (4,)
>>> args
(2, 3, 4)
>>> func(*args)

Because the arguments list is passed in as a tuple here, the program can build it at runtime. This technique also comes in handy for functions that test or time other functions. For instance, in the following code we support any function with any arguments by passing along whatever arguments were sent in:

def tracer(func, *pargs, **kargs):         # Accept arbitrary arguments
    print('calling:', func.__name__)
    return func(*pargs, **kargs)           # Pass along arbitrary arguments

def func(a, b, c, d):
    return a + b + c + d

print(tracer(func, 1, 2, c=3, d=4))

When this code is run, arguments are collected by the tracer and then propagated with varargs call syntax:

calling: func
10

We’ll see larger examples of such roles later in this book; see especially the sequence timing example in Chapter 20 and the various decorator tools we will code in Chapter 38.

The defunct apply built-in (Python 2.6)

Prior to Python 3.0, the effect of the *args and **args varargs call syntax could be achieved with a built-in function named apply. This original technique has been removed in 3.0 because it is now redundant (3.0 cleans up many such dusty tools that have been subsumed over the years). It’s still available in Python 2.6, though, and you may come across it in older 2.X code.

In short, the following are equivalent prior to Python 3.0:

func(*pargs, **kargs)             # Newer call syntax: func(*sequence, **dict)

apply(func, pargs, kargs)         # Defunct built-in:  apply(func, sequence, dict)

For example, consider the following function, which accepts any number of positional or keyword arguments:

>>> def echo(*args, **kwargs): print(args, kwargs)
...
>>> echo(1, 2, a=3, b=4)
(1, 2) {'a': 3, 'b': 4}

In Python 2.6, we can call it generically with apply, or with the call syntax that is now required in 3.0:

>>> pargs = (1, 2)
>>> kargs = {'a':3, 'b':4}

>>> apply(echo, pargs, kargs)
(1, 2) {'a': 3, 'b': 4}

>>> echo(*pargs, **kargs)
(1, 2) {'a': 3, 'b': 4}

The unpacking call syntax form is newer than the apply function, is preferred in general, and is required in 3.0. Apart from its symmetry with the *pargs and **kargs collector forms in def headers, and the fact that it requires fewer keystrokes overall, the newer call syntax also allows us to pass along additional arguments without having to manually extend argument sequences or dictionaries:

>>> echo(0, c=5, *pargs, **kargs)      # Normal, keyword, *sequence, **dictionary
(0, 1, 2) {'a': 3, 'c': 5, 'b': 4}

That is, the call syntax form is more general. Since it’s required in 3.0, you should now disavow all knowledge of apply (unless, of course, it appears in 2.X code you must use or maintain...).

Python 3.0 Keyword-Only Arguments

Python 3.0 generalizes the ordering rules in function headers to allow us to specify keyword-only arguments—arguments that must be passed by keyword only and will never be filled in by a positional argument. This is useful if we want a function to both process any number of arguments and accept possibly optional configuration options.

Syntactically, keyword-only arguments are coded as named arguments that appear after *args in the arguments list. All such arguments must be passed using keyword syntax in the call. For example, in the following, a may be passed by name or position, b collects any extra positional arguments, and c must be passed by keyword only:

>>> def kwonly(a, *b, c):
...     print(a, b, c)
...
>>> kwonly(1, 2, c=3)
1 (2,) 3
>>> kwonly(a=1, c=3)
1 () 3
>>> kwonly(1, 2, 3)
TypeError: kwonly() needs keyword-only argument c

We can also use a * character by itself in the arguments list to indicate that a function does not accept a variable-length argument list but still expects all arguments following the * to be passed as keywords. In the next function, a may be passed by position or name again, but b and c must be keywords, and no extra positionals are allowed:

>>> def kwonly(a, *, b, c):
...     print(a, b, c)
...
>>> kwonly(1, c=3, b=2)
1 2 3
>>> kwonly(c=3, b=2, a=1)
1 2 3
>>> kwonly(1, 2, 3)
TypeError: kwonly() takes exactly 1 positional argument (3 given)
>>> kwonly(1)
TypeError: kwonly() needs keyword-only argument b

You can still use defaults for keyword-only arguments, even though they appear after the * in the function header. In the following code, a may be passed by name or position, and b and c are optional but must be passed by keyword if used:

>>> def kwonly(a, *, b='spam', c='ham'):
...     print(a, b, c)
...
>>> kwonly(1)
1 spam ham
>>> kwonly(1, c=3)
1 spam 3
>>> kwonly(a=1)
1 spam ham
>>> kwonly(c=3, b=2, a=1)
1 2 3
>>> kwonly(1, 2)
TypeError: kwonly() takes exactly 1 positional argument (2 given)

In fact, keyword-only arguments with defaults are optional, but those without defaults effectively become required keywords for the function:

>>> def kwonly(a, *, b, c='spam'):
...     print(a, b, c)
...
>>> kwonly(1, b='eggs')
1 eggs spam
>>> kwonly(1, c='eggs')
TypeError: kwonly() needs keyword-only argument b
>>> kwonly(1, 2)
TypeError: kwonly() takes exactly 1 positional argument (2 given)

>>> def kwonly(a, *, b=1, c, d=2):
...     print(a, b, c, d)
...
>>> kwonly(3, c=4)
3 1 4 2
>>> kwonly(3, c=4, b=5)
3 5 4 2
>>> kwonly(3)
TypeError: kwonly() needs keyword-only argument c
>>> kwonly(1, 2, 3)
TypeError: kwonly() takes exactly 1 positional argument (3 given)

Ordering rules

Finally, note that keyword-only arguments must be specified after a single star, not two—named arguments cannot appear after the **args arbitrary keywords form, and a ** can’t appear by itself in the arguments list. Both attempts generate a syntax error:

>>> def kwonly(a, **pargs, b, c):
SyntaxError: invalid syntax
>>> def kwonly(a, **, b, c):
SyntaxError: invalid syntax

This means that in a function header, keyword-only arguments must be coded before the **args arbitrary keywords form and after the *args arbitrary positional form, when both are present. Whenever an argument name appears before *args, it is a possibly default positional argument, not keyword-only:

>>> def f(a, *b, **d, c=6): print(a, b, c, d)          # Keyword-only before **!
SyntaxError: invalid syntax

>>> def f(a, *b, c=6, **d): print(a, b, c, d)          # Collect args in header
...
>>> f(1, 2, 3, x=4, y=5)                               # Default used
1 (2, 3) 6 {'y': 5, 'x': 4}

>>> f(1, 2, 3, x=4, y=5, c=7)                          # Override default
1 (2, 3) 7 {'y': 5, 'x': 4}

>>> f(1, 2, 3, c=7, x=4, y=5)                          # Anywhere in keywords
1 (2, 3) 7 {'y': 5, 'x': 4}

>>> def f(a, c=6, *b, **d): print(a, b, c, d)          # c is not keyword-only!
...
>>> f(1, 2, 3, x=4)
1 (3,) 2 {'x': 4}

In fact, similar ordering rules hold true in function calls: when keyword-only arguments are passed, they must appear before a **args form. The keyword-only argument can be coded either before or after the *args, though, and may be included in **args:

>>> def f(a, *b, c=6, **d): print(a, b, c, d)          # KW-only between * and **
...
>>> f(1, *(2, 3), **dict(x=4, y=5))                    # Unpack args at call
1 (2, 3) 6 {'y': 5, 'x': 4}

>>> f(1, *(2, 3), **dict(x=4, y=5), c=7)               # Keywords before **args!
SyntaxError: invalid syntax

>>> f(1, *(2, 3), c=7, **dict(x=4, y=5))               # Override default
1 (2, 3) 7 {'y': 5, 'x': 4}

>>> f(1, c=7, *(2, 3), **dict(x=4, y=5))               # After or before *
1 (2, 3) 7 {'y': 5, 'x': 4}

>>> f(1, *(2, 3), **dict(x=4, y=5, c=7))               # Keyword-only in **
1 (2, 3) 7 {'y': 5, 'x': 4}

Trace through these cases on your own, in conjunction with the general argument-ordering rules described formally earlier. They may appear to be worst cases in the artificial examples here, but they can come up in real practice, especially for people who write libraries and tools for other Python programmers to use.

Why keyword-only arguments?

So why care about keyword-only arguments? In short, they make it easier to allow a function to accept both any number of positional arguments to be processed, and configuration options passed as keywords. While their use is optional, without keyword-only arguments extra work may be required to provide defaults for such options and to verify that no superfluous keywords were passed.

Imagine a function that processes a set of passed-in objects and allows a tracing flag to be passed:

process(X, Y, Z)                    # use flag's default
process(X, Y, notify=True)          # override flag default

Without keyword-only arguments we have to use both *args and **args and manually inspect the keywords, but with keyword-only arguments less code is required. The following guarantees that no positional argument will be incorrectly matched against notify and requires that it be a keyword if passed:

def process(*args, notify=False): ...

Since we’re going to see a more realistic example of this later in this chapter, in Emulating the Python 3.0 print Function, I’ll postpone the rest of this story until then. For an additional example of keyword-only arguments in action, see the iteration options timing case study in Chapter 20. And for additional function definition enhancements in Python 3.0, stay tuned for the discussion of function annotation syntax in Chapter 19.

The min Wakeup Call!

Time for something more realistic. To make this chapter’s concepts more concrete, let’s work through an exercise that demonstrates a practical application of argument-matching tools.

Suppose you want to code a function that is able to compute the minimum value from an arbitrary set of arguments and an arbitrary set of object data types. That is, the function should accept zero or more arguments, as many as you wish to pass. Moreover, the function should work for all kinds of Python object types: numbers, strings, lists, lists of dictionaries, files, and even None.

The first requirement provides a natural example of how the * feature can be put to good use—we can collect arguments into a tuple and step over each of them in turn with a simple for loop. The second part of the problem definition is easy: because every object type supports comparisons, we don’t have to specialize the function per type (an application of polymorphism); we can simply compare objects blindly and let Python worry about what sort of comparison to perform.

Full Credit

The following file shows three ways to code this operation, at least one of which was suggested by a student in one of my courses:

The first function fetches the first argument (args is a tuple) and traverses the rest by slicing off the first (there’s no point in comparing an object to itself, especially if it might be a large structure).

The second version lets Python pick off the first and rest of the arguments automatically, and so avoids an index and slice.

The third converts from a tuple to a list with the built-in list call and employs the list sort method.

The sort method is coded in C, so it can be quicker than the other approaches at times, but the linear scans of the first two techniques will make them faster most of the time.[41] The file mins.py contains the code for all three solutions:

def min1(*args):
    res = args[0]
    for arg in args[1:]:
        if arg < res:
            res = arg
    return res

def min2(first, *rest):
    for arg in rest:
        if arg < first:
            first = arg
    return first

def min3(*args):
    tmp = list(args)            # Or, in Python 2.4+: return sorted(args)[0]
    tmp.sort()
    return tmp[0]

print(min1(3,4,1,2))
print(min2("bb", "aa"))
print(min3([2,2], [1,1], [3,3]))

All three solutions produce the same result when the file is run. Try typing a few calls interactively to experiment with these on your own:

% python mins.py
1
aa
[1, 1]

Notice that none of these three variants tests for the case where no arguments are passed in. They could, but there’s no point in doing so here—in all three solutions, Python will automatically raise an exception if no arguments are passed in. The first variant raises an exception when we try to fetch item 0, the second when Python detects an argument list mismatch, and the third when we try to return item 0 at the end.

This is exactly what we want to happen—because these functions support any data type, there is no valid sentinel value that we could pass back to designate an error. There are exceptions to this rule (e.g., if you have to run expensive actions before you reach the error), but in general it’s better to assume that arguments will work in your functions’ code and let Python raise errors for you when they do not.

Bonus Points

You can get bonus points here for changing these functions to compute the maximum, rather than minimum, values. This one’s easy: the first two versions only require changing < to >, and the third simply requires that we return tmp[−1] instead of tmp[0]. For an extra point, be sure to set the function name to “max” as well (though this part is strictly optional).

It’s also possible to generalize a single function to compute either a minimum or a maximum value, by evaluating comparison expression strings with a tool like the eval built-in function (see the library manual) or passing in an arbitrary comparison function. The file minmax.py shows how to implement the latter scheme:

def minmax(test, *args):
    res = args[0]
    for arg in args[1:]:
        if test(arg, res):
            res = arg
    return res

def lessthan(x, y): return x < y                # See also: lambda
def grtrthan(x, y): return x > y

print(minmax(lessthan, 4, 2, 1, 5, 6, 3))       # Self-test code
print(minmax(grtrthan, 4, 2, 1, 5, 6, 3))

% python minmax.py
1
6

Functions are another kind of object that can be passed into a function like this one. To make this a max (or other) function, for example, we could simply pass in the right sort of test function. This may seem like extra work, but the main point of generalizing functions this way (instead of cutting and pasting to change just a single character) is that we’ll only have one version to change in the future, not two.

The Punch Line...

Of course, all this was just a coding exercise. There’s really no reason to code min or max functions, because both are built-ins in Python! We met them briefly in Chapter 5 in conjunction with numeric tools, and again in Chapter 14 when exploring iteration contexts. The built-in versions work almost exactly like ours, but they’re coded in C for optimal speed and accept either a single iterable or multiple arguments. Still, though it’s superfluous in this context, the general coding pattern we used here might be useful in other scenarios.

Generalized Set Functions

Let’s look at a more useful example of special argument-matching modes at work. At the end of Chapter 16, we wrote a function that returned the intersection of two sequences (it picked out items that appeared in both). Here is a version that intersects an arbitrary number of sequences (one or more) by using the varargs matching form *args to collect all the passed-in arguments. Because the arguments come in as a tuple, we can process them in a simple for loop. Just for fun, we’ll code a union function that also accepts an arbitrary number of arguments to collect items that appear in any of the operands:

def intersect(*args):
    res = []
    for x in args[0]:                  # Scan first sequence
        for other in args[1:]:         # For all other args
            if x not in other: break   # Item in each one?
        else:                          # No: break out of loop
            res.append(x)              # Yes: add items to end
    return res

def union(*args):
    res = []
    for seq in args:                   # For all args
        for x in seq:                  # For all nodes
            if not x in res:
                res.append(x)          # Add new items to result
    return res

Because these are tools worth reusing (and they’re too big to retype interactively), we’ll store the functions in a module file called inter2.py (if you’ve forgotten how modules and imports work, see the introduction in Chapter 3, or stay tuned for in-depth coverage in Part V). In both functions, the arguments passed in at the call come in as the args tuple. As in the original intersect, both work on any kind of sequence. Here, they are processing strings, mixed types, and more than two sequences:

% python
>>> from inter2 import intersect, union
>>> s1, s2, s3 = "SPAM", "SCAM", "SLAM"

>>> intersect(s1, s2), union(s1, s2)           # Two operands
(['S', 'A', 'M'], ['S', 'P', 'A', 'M', 'C'])

>>> intersect([1,2,3], (1,4))                  # Mixed types
[1]

>>> intersect(s1, s2, s3)                      # Three operands
['S', 'A', 'M']

>>> union(s1, s2, s3)
['S', 'P', 'A', 'M', 'C', 'L']

Note

I should note that because Python now has a set object type (described in Chapter 5), none of the set-processing examples in this book are strictly required anymore; they are included only as demonstrations of coding techniques. Because it’s constantly improving, Python has an uncanny way of conspiring to make my book examples obsolete over time!

Emulating the Python 3.0 print Function

To round out the chapter, let’s look at one last example of argument matching at work. The code you’ll see here is intended for use in Python 2.6 or earlier (it works in 3.0, too, but is pointless there): it uses both the *args arbitrary positional tuple and the **args arbitrary keyword-arguments dictionary to simulate most of what the Python 3.0 print function does.

As we learned in Chapter 11, this isn’t actually required, because 2.6 programmers can always enable the 3.0 print function with an import of this form:

from __future__ import print_function

To demonstrate argument matching in general, though, the following file, print30.py, does the same job in a small amount of reusable code:

"""
Emulate most of the 3.0 print function for use in 2.X
call signature: print30(*args, sep=' ', end='\n', file=None)
"""
import sys

def print30(*args, **kargs):
    sep  = kargs.get('sep', ' ')             # Keyword arg defaults
    end  = kargs.get('end', '\n')
    file = kargs.get('file', sys.stdout)
    output = ''
    first  = True
    for arg in args:
        output += ('' if first else sep) + str(arg)
        first = False
    file.write(output + end)

To test it, import this into another file or the interactive prompt, and use it like the 3.0 print function. Here is a test script, testprint30.py (notice that the function must be called “print30”, because “print” is a reserved word in 2.6):

from print30 import print30
print30(1, 2, 3)
print30(1, 2, 3, sep='')                     # Suppress separator
print30(1, 2, 3, sep='...')
print30(1, [2], (3,), sep='...')             # Various object types

print30(4, 5, 6, sep='', end='')             # Suppress newline
print30(7, 8, 9)
print30()                                    # Add newline (or blank line)

import sys
print30(1, 2, 3, sep='??', end='.\n', file=sys.stderr)    # Redirect to file

When run under 2.6, we get the same results as 3.0’s print function:

C:\misc> c:\python26\python testprint30.py
1 2 3
123
1...2...3
1...[2]...(3,)
4567 8 9

1??2??3.

Although pointless in 3.0, the results are the same when run there. As usual, the generality of Python’s design allows us to prototype or develop concepts in the Python language itself. In this case, argument-matching tools are as flexible in Python code as they are in Python’s internal implementation.

Using Keyword-Only Arguments

It’s interesting to notice that this example could be coded with Python 3.0 keyword-only arguments, described earlier in this chapter, to automatically validate configuration arguments:

# Use keyword-only args

def print30(*args, sep=' ', end='\n', file=sys.stdout):
    output = ''
    first  = True
    for arg in args:
        output += ('' if first else sep) + str(arg)
        first = False
    file.write(output + end)

This version works the same as the original, and it’s a prime example of how keyword-only arguments come in handy. The original version assumes that all positional arguments are to be printed, and all keywords are for options only. That’s almost sufficient, but any extra keyword arguments are silently ignored. A call like the following, for instance, will generate an exception with the keyword-only form:

>>> print30(99, name='bob')
TypeError: print30() got an unexpected keyword argument 'name'

but will silently ignore the name argument in the original version. To detect superfluous keywords manually, we could use dict.pop() to delete fetched entries, and check if the dictionary is not empty. Here is an equivalent to the keyword-only version:

# Use keyword args deletion with defaults

def print30(*args, **kargs):
    sep  = kargs.pop('sep', ' ')
    end  = kargs.pop('end', '\n')
    file = kargs.pop('file', sys.stdout)
    if kargs: raise TypeError('extra keywords: %s' % kargs)
    output = ''
    first  = True
    for arg in args:
        output += ('' if first else sep) + str(arg)
        first = False
    file.write(output + end)

This works as before, but it now catches extraneous keyword arguments, too:

>>> print30(99, name='bob')
TypeError: extra keywords: {'name': 'bob'}

This version of the function runs under Python 2.6, but it requires four more lines of code than the keyword-only version. Unfortunately, the extra code is required in this case—the keyword-only version only works on 3.0, which negates most of the reason that I wrote this example in the first place (a 3.0 emulator that only works on 3.0 isn’t incredibly useful!). In programs written to run on 3.0, though, keyword-only arguments can simplify a specific category of functions that accept both arguments and options. For another example of 3.0 keyword-only arguments, be sure to see the upcoming iteration timing case study in Chapter 20.

Why You Will Care: Keyword Arguments

As you can probably tell, advanced argument-matching modes can be complex. They are also entirely optional; you can get by with just simple positional matching, and it’s probably a good idea to do so when you’re starting out. However, because some Python tools make use of them, some general knowledge of these modes is important.

For example, keyword arguments play an important role in tkinter, the de facto standard GUI API for Python (this module’s name is Tkinter in Python 2.6). We touch on tkinter only briefly at various points in this book, but in terms of its call patterns, keyword arguments set configuration options when GUI components are built. For instance, a call of the form:

from tkinter import *
widget = Button(text="Press me", command=someFunction)

creates a new button and specifies its text and callback function, using the text and command keyword arguments. Since the number of configuration options for a widget can be large, keyword arguments let you pick and choose which to apply. Without them, you might have to either list all the possible options by position or hope for a judicious positional argument defaults protocol that would handle every possible option arrangement.

Many built-in functions in Python expect us to use keywords for usage-mode options as well, which may or may not have defaults. As we learned in Chapter 8, for instance, the sorted built-in:

sorted(iterable, key=None, reverse=False)

expects us to pass an iterable object to be sorted, but also allows us to pass in optional keyword arguments to specify a dictionary sort key and a reversal flag, which default to None and False, respectively. Since we normally don’t use these options, they may be omitted to use defaults.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

The output here is '1 2 5', because 1 and 2 are passed to a and b by position, and c is omitted in the call and defaults to 5.

The output this time is '1 2 3': 1 is passed to a by position, and b and c are passed 2 and 3 by name (the left-to-right order doesn’t matter when keyword arguments are used like this).

This code prints '1 (2, 3)', because 1 is passed to a and the *pargs collects the remaining positional arguments into a new tuple object. We can step through the extra positional arguments tuple with any iteration tool (e.g., for arg in pargs: ...).

This time the code prints '1 {'c': 3, 'b': 2}', because 1 is passed to a by name and the **kargs collects the remaining keyword arguments into a dictionary. We could step through the extra keyword arguments dictionary by key with any iteration tool (e.g., for key in kargs: ...).

The output here is '1 5 6 4': 1 matches a by position, 5 and 6 match b and c by *name positionals (6 overrides c’s default), and d defaults to 4 because it was not passed a value.

Functions can send back results with return statements, by changing passed-in mutable arguments, and by setting global variables. Globals are generally frowned upon (except for very special cases, like multithreaded programs) because they can make code more difficult to understand and use. return statements are usually best, but changing mutables is fine, if expected. Functions may also communicate with system devices such as files and sockets, but these are beyond our scope here.

[41] Actually, this is fairly complicated. The Python sort routine is coded in C and uses a highly optimized algorithm that attempts to take advantage of partial ordering in the items to be sorted. It’s named “timsort” after Tim Peters, its creator, and in its documentation it claims to have “supernatural performance” at times (pretty good, for a sort!). Still, sorting is an inherently exponential operation (it must chop up the sequence and put it back together many times), and the other versions simply perform one linear left-to-right scan. The net effect is that sorting is quicker if the arguments are partially ordered, but is likely to be slower otherwise. Even so, Python performance can change over time, and the fact that sorting is implemented in the C language can help greatly; for an exact analysis, you should time the alternatives with the time or timeit modules we’ll meet in Chapter 20.

Recursive Functions

While discussing scope rules near the start of Chapter 17, we briefly noted that Python supports recursive functions—functions that call themselves either directly or indirectly in order to loop. Recursion is a somewhat advanced topic, and it’s relatively rare to see in Python. Still, it’s a useful technique to know about, as it allows programs to traverse structures that have arbitrary and unpredictable shapes. Recursion is even an alternative for simple loops and iterations, though not necessarily the simplest or most efficient one.

Summation with Recursion

Let’s look at some examples. To sum a list (or other sequence) of numbers, we can either use the built-in sum function or write a more custom version of our own. Here’s what a custom summing function might look like when coded with recursion:

>>> def mysum(L):
...     if not L:
...         return 0
...     else:
...         return L[0] + mysum(L[1:])           # Call myself

>>> mysum([1, 2, 3, 4, 5])
15

At each level, this function calls itself recursively to compute the sum of the rest of the list, which is later added to the item at the front. The recursive loop ends and zero is returned when the list becomes empty. When using recursion like this, each open level of call to the function has its own copy of the function’s local scope on the runtime call stack—here, that means L is different in each level.

If this is difficult to understand (and it often is for new programmers), try adding a print of L to the function and run it again, to trace the current list at each call level:

>>> def mysum(L):
...     print(L)                                 # Trace recursive levels
...     if not L:                                # L shorter at each level
...         return 0
...     else:
...         return L[0] + mysum(L[1:])
...
>>> mysum([1, 2, 3, 4, 5])
[1, 2, 3, 4, 5]
[2, 3, 4, 5]
[3, 4, 5]
[4, 5]
[5]
[]
15

As you can see, the list to be summed grows smaller at each recursive level, until it becomes empty—the termination of the recursive loop. The sum is computed as the recursive calls unwind.

Coding Alternatives

Interestingly, we can also use Python’s if/else ternary expression (described in Chapter 12) to save some code real-estate here. We can also generalize for any summable type (which is easier if we assume at least one item in the input, as we did in Chapter 18’s minimum value example) and use Python 3.0’s extended sequence assignment to make the first/rest unpacking simpler (as covered in Chapter 11):

def mysum(L):
    return 0 if not L else L[0] + mysum(L[1:])           # Use ternary expression

def mysum(L):
    return L[0] if len(L) == 1 else L[0] + mysum(L[1:])  # Any type, assume one

def mysum(L):
    first, *rest = L
    return first if not rest else first + mysum(rest)    # Use 3.0 ext seq assign

The latter two of these fail for empty lists but allow for sequences of any object type that supports +, not just numbers:

>>> mysum([1])                              # mysum([]) fails in last 2
1
>>> mysum([1, 2, 3, 4, 5])
15
>>> mysum(('s', 'p', 'a', 'm'))             # But various types now work
'spam'
>>> mysum(['spam', 'ham', 'eggs'])
'spamhameggs'

If you study these three variants, you’ll find that the latter two also work on a single string argument (e.g., mysum ('spam')), because strings are sequences of one-character strings; the third variant works on arbitary iterables, including open input files, but the others do not because they index; and the function header def mysum(first, * rest), although similar to the third variant, wouldn’t work at all, because it expects individual arguments, not a single iterable.

Keep in mind that recursion can be direct, as in the examples so far, or indirect, as in the following (a function that calls another function, which calls back to its caller). The net effect is the same, though there are two function calls at each level instead of one:

>>> def mysum(L):
...     if not L: return 0
...     return nonempty(L)                  # Call a function that calls me
...
>>> def nonempty(L):
...     return L[0] + mysum(L[1:])          # Indirectly recursive
...
>>> mysum([1.1, 2.2, 3.3, 4.4])
11.0

Loop Statements Versus Recursion

Though recursion works for summing in the prior sections’ examples, it’s probably overkill in this context. In fact, recursion is not used nearly as often in Python as in more esoteric languages like Prolog or Lisp, because Python emphasizes simpler procedural statements like loops, which are usually more natural. The while, for example, often makes things a bit more concrete, and it doesn’t require that a function be defined to allow recursive calls:

>>> L = [1, 2, 3, 4, 5]
>>> sum = 0
>>> while L:
...     sum += L[0]
...     L = L[1:]
...
>>> sum
15

Better yet, for loops iterate for us automatically, making recursion largely extraneous in most cases (and, in all likelihood, less efficient in terms of memory space and execution time):

>>> L = [1, 2, 3, 4, 5]
>>> sum = 0
>>> for x in L: sum += x
...
>>> sum
15

With looping statements, we don’t require a fresh copy of a local scope on the call stack for each iteration, and we avoid the speed costs associated with function calls in general. (Stay tuned for Chapter 20’s timer case study for ways to compare the execution times of alternatives like these.)

Handling Arbitrary Structures

On the other hand, recursion (or equivalent explicit stack-based algorithms, which we’ll finesse here) can be required to traverse arbitrarily shaped structures. As a simple example of recursion’s role in this context, consider the task of computing the sum of all the numbers in a nested sublists structure like this:

[1, [2, [3, 4], 5], 6, [7, 8]]                   # Arbitrarily nested sublists

Simple looping statements won’t work here because this not a linear iteration. Nested looping statements do not suffice either, because the sublists may be nested to arbitrary depth and in an arbitrary shape. Instead, the following code accommodates such general nesting by using recursion to visit sublists along the way:

def sumtree(L):
    tot = 0
    for x in L:                                  # For each item at this level
        if not isinstance(x, list):
            tot += x                             # Add numbers directly
        else:
            tot += sumtree(x)                    # Recur for sublists
    return tot

L = [1, [2, [3, 4], 5], 6, [7, 8]]               # Arbitrary nesting
print(sumtree(L))                                # Prints 36


# Pathological cases

print(sumtree([1, [2, [3, [4, [5]]]]]))          # Prints 15 (right-heavy)

print(sumtree([[[[[1], 2], 3], 4], 5]))          # Prints 15 (left-heavy)

Trace through the test cases at the bottom of this script to see how recursion traverses their nested lists. Although this example is artificial, it is representative of a larger class of programs; inheritance trees and module import chains, for example, can exhibit similarly general structures. In fact, we will use recursion again in such roles in more realistic examples later in this book:

In Chapter 24’s reloadall.py, to traverse import chains

In Chapter 28’s classtree.py, to traverse class inheritance trees

In Chapter 30’s lister.py, to traverse class inheritance trees again

Although you should generally prefer looping statements to recursion for linear iterations on the grounds of simplicity and efficiency, we’ll find that recursion is essential in scenarios like those in these later examples.

Moreover, you sometimes need to be aware of the potential of unintended recursion in your programs. As you’ll also see later in the book, some operator overloading methods in classes such as __setattr__ and __getattribute__ have the potential to recursively loop if used incorrectly. Recursion is a powerful tool, but it tends to be best when expected!

Function Objects: Attributes and Annotations

Python functions are more flexible than you might think. As we’ve seen in this part of the book, functions in Python are much more than code-generation specifications for a compiler—Python functions are full-blown objects, stored in pieces of memory all their own. As such, they can be freely passed around a program and called indirectly. They also support operations that have little to do with calls at all—attribute storage and annotation.

Indirect Function Calls

Because Python functions are objects, you can write programs that process them generically. Function objects may be assigned to other names, passed to other functions, embedded in data structures, returned from one function to another, and more, as if they were simple numbers or strings. Function objects also happen to support a special operation: they can be called by listing arguments in parentheses after a function expression. Still, functions belong to the same general category as other objects.

We’ve seen some of these generic use cases for functions in earlier examples, but a quick review helps to underscore the object model. For example, there’s really nothing special about the name used in a def statement: it’s just a variable assigned in the current scope, as if it had appeared on the left of an = sign. After a def runs, the function name is simply a reference to an object—you can reassign that object to other names freely and call it through any reference:

>>> def echo(message):                   # Name echo assigned to function object
...     print(message)
...
>>> echo('Direct call')                  # Call object through original name
Direct call

>>> x = echo                             # Now x references the function too
>>> x('Indirect call!')                  # Call object through name by adding ()
Indirect call!

Because arguments are passed by assigning objects, it’s just as easy to pass functions to other functions as arguments. The callee may then call the passed-in function just by adding arguments in parentheses:

>>> def indirect(func, arg):
...     func(arg)                        # Call the passed-in object by adding ()
...
>>> indirect(echo, 'Argument call!')     # Pass the function to another function
Argument call!

You can even stuff function objects into data structures, as though they were integers or strings. The following, for example, embeds the function twice in a list of tuples, as a sort of actions table. Because Python compound types like these can contain any sort of object, there’s no special case here, either:

>>> schedule = [ (echo, 'Spam!'), (echo, 'Ham!') ]
>>> for (func, arg) in schedule:
...     func(arg)                        # Call functions embedded in containers
...
Spam!
Ham!

This code simply steps through the schedule list, calling the echo function with one argument each time through (notice the tuple-unpacking assignment in the for loop header, introduced in Chapter 13). As we saw in Chapter 17’s examples, functions can also be created and returned for use elsewhere:

>>> def make(label):                     # Make a function but don't call it
...     def echo(message):
...         print(label + ':' + message)
...     return echo
...
>>> F = make('Spam')                     # Label in enclosing scope is retained
>>> F('Ham!')                            # Call the function that make returned
Spam:Ham!
>>> F('Eggs!')
Spam:Eggs!

Python’s universal object model and lack of type declarations make for an incredibly flexible programming language.

Function Introspection

Because they are objects, we can also process functions with normal object tools. In fact, functions are more flexible than you might expect. For instance, once we make a function, we can call it as usual:

>>> def func(a):
...     b = 'spam'
...     return b * a
...
>>> func(8)
'spamspamspamspamspamspamspamspam'

But the call expression is just one operation defined to work on function objects. We can also inspect their attributes generically (the following is run in Python 3.0, but 2.6 results are similar):

>>> func.__name__
'func'
>>> dir(func)
['__annotations__', '__call__', '__class__', '__closure__', '__code__',
...more omitted...
'__repr__', '__setattr__', '__sizeof__', '__str__', '__subclasshook__']

Introspection tools allow us to explore implementation details too—functions have attached code objects, for example, which provide details on aspects such as the functions’ local variables and arguments:

>>> func.__code__
<code object func at 0x0257C9B0, file "<stdin>", line 1>

>>> dir(func.__code__)
['__class__', '__delattr__', '__doc__', '__eq__', '__format__', '__ge__',
...more omitted...
'co_argcount', 'co_cellvars', 'co_code', 'co_consts', 'co_filename',
'co_firstlineno', 'co_flags', 'co_freevars', 'co_kwonlyargcount', 'co_lnotab',
'co_name', 'co_names', 'co_nlocals', 'co_stacksize', 'co_varnames']

>>> func.__code__.co_varnames
('a', 'b')
>>> func.__code__.co_argcount
1

Tool writers can make use of such information to manage functions (in fact, we will too in Chapter 38, to implement validation of function arguments in decorators).

Function Attributes

Function objects are not limited to the system-defined attributes listed in the prior section, though. As we learned in Chapter 17, it’s possible to attach arbitrary user-defined attributes to them as well:

>>> func
<function func at 0x0257C738>
>>> func.count = 0
>>> func.count += 1
>>> func.count
1
>>> func.handles = 'Button-Press'
>>> func.handles
'Button-Press'
>>> dir(func)
['__annotations__', '__call__', '__class__', '__closure__', '__code__',
...more omitted...
__str__', '__subclasshook__', 'count', 'handles']

As we saw in that chapter, such attributes can be used to attach state information to function objects directly, instead of using other techniques such as globals, nonlocals, and classes. Unlike nonlocals, such attributes are accessible anywhere the function itself is. In a sense, this is also a way to emulate “static locals” in other languages—variables whose names are local to a function, but whose values are retained after a function exits. Attributes are related to objects instead of scopes, but the net effect is similar.

Function Annotations in 3.0

In Python 3.0 (but not 2.6), it’s also possible to attach annotation information—arbitrary user-defined data about a function’s arguments and result—to a function object. Python provides special syntax for specifying annotations, but it doesn’t do anything with them itself; annotations are completely optional, and when present are simply attached to the function object’s __annotations__ attribute for use by other tools.

We met Python 3.0’s keyword-only arguments in the prior chapter; annotations generalize function header syntax further. Consider the following nonannotated function, which is coded with three arguments and returns a result:

>>> def func(a, b, c):
...     return a + b + c
...
>>> func(1, 2, 3)
6

Syntactically, function annotations are coded in def header lines, as arbitrary expressions associated with arguments and return values. For arguments, they appear after a colon immediately following the argument’s name; for return values, they are written after a -> following the arguments list. This code, for example, annotates all three of the prior function’s arguments, as well as its return value:

>>> def func(a: 'spam', b: (1, 10), c: float) -> int:
...     return a + b + c
...
>>> func(1, 2, 3)
6

Calls to an annotated function work as usual, but when annotations are present Python collects them in a dictionary and attaches it to the function object itself. Argument names become keys, the return value annotation is stored under key “return” if coded, and the values of annotation keys are assigned to the results of the annotation expressions:

>>> func.__annotations__
{'a': 'spam', 'c': <class 'float'>, 'b': (1, 10), 'return': <class 'int'>}

Because they are just Python objects attached to a Python object, annotations are straightforward to process. The following annotates just two of three arguments and steps through the attached annotations generically:

>>> def func(a: 'spam', b, c: 99):
...     return a + b + c
...
>>> func(1, 2, 3)
6
>>> func.__annotations__
{'a': 'spam', 'c': 99}

>>> for arg in func.__annotations__:
...    print(arg, '=>', func.__annotations__[arg])
...
a => spam
c => 99

There are two fine points to note here. First, you can still use defaults for arguments if you code annotations—the annotation (and its : character) appear before the default (and its = character). In the following, for example, a: 'spam' = 4 means that argument a defaults to 4 and is annotated with the string 'spam':

>>> def func(a: 'spam' = 4, b: (1, 10) = 5, c: float = 6) -> int:
...     return a + b + c
...
>>> func(1, 2, 3)
6
>>> func()                       # 4 + 5 + 6   (all defaults)
15
>>> func(1, c=10)                # 1 + 5 + 10  (keywords work normally)
16
>>> func.__annotations__
{'a': 'spam', 'c': <class 'float'>, 'b': (1, 10), 'return': <class 'int'>}

Second, note that the blank spaces in the prior example are all optional—you can use spaces between components in function headers or not, but omitting them might degrade your code’s readability to some observers:

>>> def func(a:'spam'=4, b:(1,10)=5, c:float=6)->int:
...     return a + b + c
...
>>> func(1, 2)                   # 1 + 2 + 6
9
>>> func.__annotations__
{'a': 'spam', 'c': <class 'float'>, 'b': (1, 10), 'return': <class 'int'>}

Annotations are a new feature in 3.0, and some of their potential uses remain to be uncovered. It’s easy to imagine annotations being used to specify constraints for argument types or values, though, and larger APIs might use this feature as a way to register function interface information. In fact, we’ll see a potential application in Chapter 38, where we’ll look at annotations as an alternative to function decorator arguments (a more general concept in which information is coded outside the function header and so is not limited to a single role). Like Python itself, annotation is a tool whose roles are shaped by your imagination.

Finally, note that annotations work only in def statements, not lambda expressions, because lambda’s syntax already limits the utility of the functions it defines. Coincidentally, this brings us to our next topic.

Anonymous Functions: lambda

Besides the def statement, Python also provides an expression form that generates function objects. Because of its similarity to a tool in the Lisp language, it’s called lambda.[42] Like def, this expression creates a function to be called later, but it returns the function instead of assigning it to a name. This is why lambdas are sometimes known as anonymous (i.e., unnamed) functions. In practice, they are often used as a way to inline a function definition, or to defer execution of a piece of code.

lambda Basics

The lambda’s general form is the keyword lambda, followed by one or more arguments (exactly like the arguments list you enclose in parentheses in a def header), followed by an expression after a colon:

lambda argument1, argument2,... argumentN :expression using arguments

Function objects returned by running lambda expressions work exactly the same as those created and assigned by defs, but there are a few differences that make lambdas useful in specialized roles:

lambda is an expression, not a statement. Because of this, a lambda can appear in places a def is not allowed by Python’s syntax—inside a list literal or a function call’s arguments, for example. As an expression, lambda returns a value (a new function) that can optionally be assigned a name. In contrast, the def statement always assigns the new function to the name in the header, instead of returning it as a result.

lambda’s body is a single expression, not a block of statements. The lambda’s body is similar to what you’d put in a def body’s return statement; you simply type the result as a naked expression, instead of explicitly returning it. Because it is limited to an expression, a lambda is less general than a def—you can only squeeze so much logic into a lambda body without using statements such as if. This is by design, to limit program nesting: lambda is designed for coding simple functions, and def handles larger tasks.

Apart from those distinctions, defs and lambdas do the same sort of work. For instance, we’ve seen how to make a function with a def statement:

>>> def func(x, y, z): return x + y + z
...
>>> func(2, 3, 4)
9

But you can achieve the same effect with a lambda expression by explicitly assigning its result to a name through which you can later call the function:

>>> f = lambda x, y, z: x + y + z
>>> f(2, 3, 4)
9

Here, f is assigned the function object the lambda expression creates; this is how def works, too, but its assignment is automatic.

Defaults work on lambda arguments, just like in a def:

>>> x = (lambda a="fee", b="fie", c="foe": a + b + c)
>>> x("wee")
'weefiefoe'

The code in a lambda body also follows the same scope lookup rules as code inside a def. lambda expressions introduce a local scope much like a nested def, which automatically sees names in enclosing functions, the module, and the built-in scope (via the LEGB rule):

>>> def knights():
...     title = 'Sir'
...     action = (lambda x: title + ' ' + x)        # Title in enclosing def
...     return action                               # Return a function
...
>>> act = knights()
>>> act('robin')
'Sir robin'

In this example, prior to Release 2.2, the value for the name title would typically have been passed in as a default argument value instead; flip back to the scopes coverage in Chapter 17 if you’ve forgotten why.

Why Use lambda?

Generally speaking, lambdas come in handy as a sort of function shorthand that allows you to embed a function’s definition within the code that uses it. They are entirely optional (you can always use defs instead), but they tend to be simpler coding constructs in scenarios where you just need to embed small bits of executable code.

For instance, we’ll see later that callback handlers are frequently coded as inline lambda expressions embedded directly in a registration call’s arguments list, instead of being defined with a def elsewhere in a file and referenced by name (see the sidebar Why You Will Care: Callbacks for an example).

lambdas are also commonly used to code jump tables, which are lists or dictionaries of actions to be performed on demand. For example:

L = [lambda x: x ** 2,               # Inline function definition
     lambda x: x ** 3,
     lambda x: x ** 4]               # A list of 3 callable functions

for f in L:
    print(f(2))                      # Prints 4, 8, 16

print(L[0](3))                       # Prints 9

The lambda expression is most useful as a shorthand for def, when you need to stuff small pieces of executable code into places where statements are illegal syntactically. This code snippet, for example, builds up a list of three functions by embedding lambda expressions inside a list literal; a def won’t work inside a list literal like this because it is a statement, not an expression. The equivalent def coding would require temporary function names and function definitions outside the context of intended use:

def f1(x): return x ** 2
def f2(x): return x ** 3             # Define named functions
def f3(x): return x ** 4

L = [f1, f2, f3]                     # Reference by name

for f in L:
    print(f(2))                      # Prints 4, 8, 16

print(L[0](3))                       # Prints 9

In fact, you can do the same sort of thing with dictionaries and other data structures in Python to build up more general sorts of action tables. Here’s another example to illustrate, at the interactive prompt:

>>> key = 'got'
>>> {'already': (lambda: 2 + 2),
...  'got':     (lambda: 2 * 4),
...  'one':     (lambda: 2 ** 6)}[key]()
8

Here, when Python makes the temporary dictionary, each of the nested lambdas generates and leaves behind a function to be called later. Indexing by key fetches one of those functions, and parentheses force the fetched function to be called. When coded this way, a dictionary becomes a more general multiway branching tool than what I could show you in Chapter 12’s coverage of if statements.

To make this work without lambda, you’d need to instead code three def statements somewhere else in your file, outside the dictionary in which the functions are to be used, and reference the functions by name:

>>> def f1(): return 2 + 2
...
>>> def f2(): return 2 * 4
...
>>> def f3(): return 2 ** 6
...
>>> key = 'one'
>>> {'already': f1, 'got': f2, 'one': f3}[key]()
64

This works, too, but your defs may be arbitrarily far away in your file, even if they are just little bits of code. The code proximity that lambdas provide is especially useful for functions that will only be used in a single context—if the three functions here are not useful anywhere else, it makes sense to embed their definitions within the dictionary as lambdas. Moreover, the def form requires you to make up names for these little functions that may clash with other names in this file (perhaps unlikely, but always possible).

lambdas also come in handy in function-call argument lists as a way to inline temporary function definitions not used anywhere else in your program; we’ll see some examples of such other uses later in this chapter, when we study map.

How (Not) to Obfuscate Your Python Code

The fact that the body of a lambda has to be a single expression (not a series of statements) would seem to place severe limits on how much logic you can pack into a lambda. If you know what you’re doing, though, you can code most statements in Python as expression-based equivalents.

For example, if you want to print from the body of a lambda function, simply say print(X) in Python 3.X (where this becomes a call expression instead of a statement), but say sys.stdout.write(str(x)+'\n') in either Python 2.X or 3.X to make sure it's an expression portably (recall from Chapter 11 that this is what print really does). Similarly, to nest logic in a lambda, you can use the if/else ternary expression introduced in Chapter 12, or the equivalent but trickier and/or combination also described there. As you learned earlier, the following statement:

if a:
    b
else:
    c

can be emulated by either of these roughly equivalent expressions:

b if a else c
((a and b) or c)

Because expressions like these can be placed inside a lambda, they may be used to implement selection logic within a lambda function:

>>> lower = (lambda x, y: x if x < y else y)
>>> lower('bb', 'aa')
'aa'
>>> lower('aa', 'bb')
'aa'

Furthermore, if you need to perform loops within a lambda, you can also embed things like map calls and list comprehension expressions (tools we met in earlier chapters and will revisit in this and the next chapter):

>>> import sys
>>> showall = lambda x: list(map(sys.stdout.write, x))        # Use list in 3.0

>>> t = showall(['spam\n', 'toast\n', 'eggs\n'])
spam
toast
eggs

>>> showall = lambda x: [sys.stdout.write(line) for line in x]

>>> t = showall(('bright\n', 'side\n', 'of\n', 'life\n'))
bright
side
of
life

Now that I’ve shown you these tricks, I am required by law to ask you to please only use them as a last resort. Without due care, they can lead to unreadable (a.k.a. obfuscated) Python code. In general, simple is better than complex, explicit is better than implicit, and full statements are better than arcane expressions. That’s why lambda is limited to expressions. If you have larger logic to code, use def; lambda is for small pieces of inline code. On the other hand, you may find these techniques useful in moderation.

Nested lambdas and Scopes

lambdas are the main beneficiaries of nested function scope lookup (the E in the LEGB scope rule we studied in Chapter 17). In the following, for example, the lambda appears inside a def—the typical case—and so can access the value that the name x had in the enclosing function’s scope at the time that the enclosing function was called:

>>> def action(x):
...     return (lambda y: x + y)         # Make and return function, remember x
...
>>> act = action(99)
>>> act
<function <lambda> at 0x00A16A88>
>>> act(2)                               # Call what action returned
101

What wasn’t illustrated in the prior discussion of nested function scopes is that a lambda also has access to the names in any enclosing lambda. This case is somewhat obscure, but imagine if we recoded the prior def with a lambda:

>>> action = (lambda x: (lambda y: x + y))
>>> act = action(99)
>>> act(3)
102
>>> ((lambda x: (lambda y: x + y))(99))(4)
103

Here, the nested lambda structure makes a function that makes a function when called. In both cases, the nested lambda’s code has access to the variable x in the enclosing lambda. This works, but it’s fairly convoluted code; in the interest of readability, nested lambdas are generally best avoided.

Why You Will Care: Callbacks

Another very common application of lambda is to define inline callback functions for Python’s tkinter GUI API (this module is named Tkinter in Python 2.6). For example, the following creates a button that prints a message on the console when pressed, assuming tkinter is available on your computer (it is by default on Windows and other OSs):

import sys
from tkinter import Button, mainloop     # Tkinter in 2.6
x = Button(
        text ='Press me',
        command=(lambda:sys.stdout.write('Spam\n')))
x.pack()
mainloop()

Here, the callback handler is registered by passing a function generated with a lambda to the command keyword argument. The advantage of lambda over def here is that the code that handles a button press is right here, embedded in the button-creation call.

In effect, the lambda defers execution of the handler until the event occurs: the write call happens on button presses, not when the button is created.

Because the nested function scope rules apply to lambdas as well, they are also easier to use as callback handlers, as of Python 2.2—they automatically see names in the functions in which they are coded and no longer require passed-in defaults in most cases. This is especially handy for accessing the special self instance argument that is a local variable in enclosing class method functions (more on classes in Part VI):

class MyGui:
    def makewidgets(self):
        Button(command=(lambda: self.onPress("spam")))
    def onPress(self, message):
        ...use message...

In prior releases, even self had to be passed in to a lambda with defaults.

Mapping Functions over Sequences: map

One of the more common things programs do with lists and other sequences is apply an operation to each item and collect the results. For instance, updating all the counters in a list can be done easily with a for loop:

>>> counters = [1, 2, 3, 4]
>>>
>>> updated = []
>>> for x in counters:
...     updated.append(x + 10)                 # Add 10 to each item
...
>>> updated
[11, 12, 13, 14]

But because this is such a common operation, Python actually provides a built-in that does most of the work for you. The map function applies a passed-in function to each item in an iterable object and returns a list containing all the function call results. For example:

>>> def inc(x): return x + 10                  # Function to be run
...
>>> list(map(inc, counters))                   # Collect results
[11, 12, 13, 14]

We met map briefly in Chapters 13 and 14, as a way to apply a built-in function to items in an iterable. Here, we make better use of it by passing in a user-defined function to be applied to each item in the list—map calls inc on each list item and collects all the return values into a new list. Remember that map is an iterable in Python 3.0, so a list call is used to force it to produce all its results for display here; this isn’t necessary in 2.6.

Because map expects a function to be passed in, it also happens to be one of the places where lambda commonly appears:

>>> list(map((lambda x: x + 3), counters))     # Function expression
[4, 5, 6, 7]

Here, the function adds 3 to each item in the counters list; as this little function isn’t needed elsewhere, it was written inline as a lambda. Because such uses of map are equivalent to for loops, with a little extra code you can always code a general mapping utility yourself:

>>> def mymap(func, seq):
...     res = []
...     for x in seq: res.append(func(x))
...     return res

Assuming the function inc is still as it was when it was shown previously, we can map it across a sequence with the built-in or our equivalent:

>>> list(map(inc, [1, 2, 3]))             # Built-in is an iterator
[11, 12, 13]
>>> mymap(inc, [1, 2, 3])                 # Ours builds a list (see generators)
[11, 12, 13]

However, as map is a built-in, it’s always available, always works the same way, and has some performance benefits (as we’ll prove in the next chapter, it’s usually faster than a manually coded for loop). Moreover, map can be used in more advanced ways than shown here. For instance, given multiple sequence arguments, it sends items taken from sequences in parallel as distinct arguments to the function:

>>> pow(3, 4)                             # 3**4
81
>>> list(map(pow, [1, 2, 3], [2, 3, 4]))  # 1**2, 2**3, 3**4
[1, 8, 81]

With multiple sequences, map expects an N-argument function for N sequences. Here, the pow function takes two arguments on each call—one from each sequence passed to map. It’s not much extra work to simulate this multiple-sequence generality in code, too, but we’ll postpone doing so until later in the next chapter, after we’ve met some additional iteration tools.

The map call is similar to the list comprehension expressions we studied in Chapter 14 and will meet again in the next chapter, but map applies a function call to each item instead of an arbitrary expression. Because of this limitation, it is a somewhat less general tool. However, in some cases map may be faster to run than a list comprehension (e.g., when mapping a built-in function), and it may also require less coding.

Functional Programming Tools: filter and reduce

The map function is the simplest representative of a class of Python built-ins used for functional programming—tools that apply functions to sequences and other iterables. Its relatives filter out items based on a test function (filter) and apply functions to pairs of items and running results (reduce). Because they return iterables, range and filter both require list calls to display all their results in 3.0. For example, the following filter call picks out items in a sequence that are greater than zero:

>>> list(range(−5, 5))                                   # An iterator in 3.0
[−5, −4, −3, −2, −1, 0, 1, 2, 3, 4]

>>> list(filter((lambda x: x > 0), range(−5, 5)))        # An iterator in 3.0
[1, 2, 3, 4]

Items in the sequence or iterable for which the function returns a true result are added to the result list. Like map, this function is roughly equivalent to a for loop, but it is built-in and fast:

>>> res = []
>>> for x in range(−5, 5):
...     if x > 0:
...         res.append(x)
...
>>> res
[1, 2, 3, 4]

reduce, which is a simple built-in function in 2.6 but lives in the functools module in 3.0, is more complex. It accepts an iterator to process, but it’s not an iterator itself—it returns a single result. Here are two reduce calls that compute the sum and product of the items in a list:

>>> from functools import reduce      # Import in 3.0, not in 2.6

>>> reduce((lambda x, y: x + y), [1, 2, 3, 4])
10
>>> reduce((lambda x, y: x * y), [1, 2, 3, 4])
24

At each step, reduce passes the current sum or product, along with the next item from the list, to the passed-in lambda function. By default, the first item in the sequence initializes the starting value. To illustrate, here’s the for loop equivalent to the first of these calls, with the addition hardcoded inside the loop:

>>> L = [1,2,3,4]
>>> res = L[0]
>>> for x in L[1:]:
...     res = res + x
...
>>> res
10

Coding your own version of reduce is actually fairly straightforward. The following function emulates most of the built-in’s behavior and helps demystify its operation in general:

>>> def myreduce(function, sequence):
...     tally = sequence[0]
...     for next in sequence[1:]:
...         tally = function(tally, next)
...     return tally
...
>>> myreduce((lambda x, y: x + y), [1, 2, 3, 4, 5])
15
>>> myreduce((lambda x, y: x * y), [1, 2, 3, 4, 5])
120

The built-in reduce also allows an optional third argument placed before the items in the sequence to serve as a default result when the sequence is empty, but we’ll leave this extension as a suggested exercise.

If this coding technique has sparked your interest, you might also be interested in the standard library operator module, which provides functions that correspond to built-in expressions and so comes in handy for some uses of functional tools (see Python’s library manual for more details on this module):

>>> import operator, functools
>>> functools.reduce(operator.add, [2, 4, 6])        # Function-based +
12
>>> functools.reduce((lambda x, y: x + y), [2, 4, 6])
12

Together with map, filter and reduce support powerful functional programming techniques. Some observers might also extend the functional programming toolset in Python to include lambda, discussed earlier, as well as list comprehensions—a topic we will return to in the next chapter.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

Both lambda and def create function objects to be called later. Because lambda is an expression, though, it returns a function object instead of assigning it to a name, and it can be used to nest a function definition in places where a def will not work syntactically. A lambda only allows for a single implicit return value expression, though; because it does not support a block of statements, it is not ideal for larger functions.

lambdas allow us to “inline” small units of executable code, defer its execution, and provide it with state in the form of default arguments and enclosing scope variables. Using a lambda is never required; you can always code a def instead and reference the function by name. lambdas come in handy, though, to embed small pieces of deferred code that are unlikely to be used elsewhere in a program. They commonly appear in callback-based program such as GUIs, and they have a natural affinity with function tools like map and filter that expect a processing function.

These three built-in functions all apply another function to items in a sequence (iterable) object and collect results. map passes each item to the function and collects all results, filter collects items for which the function returns a True value, and reduce computes a single value by applying the function to an accumulator and successive items. Unlike the other two, reduce is available in the functools module in 3.0, not the built-in scope.

Function annotations, available in 3.0 and later, are syntactic embellishments of a function’s arguments and result, which are collected into a dictionary assigned to the function’s __annotations__ attribute. Python places no semantic meaning on these annotations, but simply packages them for potential use by other tools.

Recursive functions call themselves either directly or indirectly in order to loop. They may be used to traverse arbitrarily shaped structures, but they can also be used for iteration in general (though the latter role is often more simply and efficiently coded with looping statements).

Functions should generally be small, as self-contained as possible, have a single unified purpose, and communicate with other components through input arguments and return values. They may use mutable arguments to communicate results too if changes are expected, and some types of programs imply other communication mechanisms.

[42] The lambda tends to intimidate people more than it should. This reaction seems to stem from the name “lambda” itself—a name that comes from the Lisp language, which got it from lambda calculus, which is a form of symbolic logic. In Python, though, it’s really just a keyword that introduces the expression syntactically. Obscure mathematical heritage aside, lambda is simpler to use than you may think.

Chapter 20. Iterations and Comprehensions, Part 2

This chapter continues the advanced function topics theme, with a reprisal of the comprehension and iteration concepts introduced in Chapter 14. Because list comprehensions are as much related to the prior chapter’s functional tools (e.g., map and filter) as they are to for loops, we’ll revisit them in this context here. We’ll also take a second look at iterators in order to study generator functions and their generator expression relatives—user-defined ways to produce results on demand.

Iteration in Python also encompasses user-defined classes, but we’ll defer that final part of this story until Part VI, when we study operator overloading. As this is the last pass we’ll make over built-in iteration tools, though, we will summarize the various tools we’ve met thus far, and time the relative performance of some of them. Finally, because this is the last chapter in the part of the book, we’ll close with the usual sets of “gotchas” and exercises to help you start coding the ideas you’ve read about.

List Comprehensions Revisited: Functional Tools

In the prior chapter, we studied functional programming tools like map and filter, which map operations over sequences and collect results. Because this is such a common task in Python coding, Python eventually sprouted a new expression—the list comprehension—that is even more flexible than the tools we just studied. In short, list comprehensions apply an arbitrary expression to items in an iterable, rather than applying a function. As such, they can be more general tools.

We met list comprehensions in Chapter 14, in conjunction with looping statements. Because they’re also related to functional programming tools like the map and filter calls, though, we’ll resurrect the topic here for one last look. Technically, this feature is not tied to functions—as we’ll see, list comprehensions can be a more general tool than map and filter—but it is sometimes best understood by analogy to function-based alternatives.

List Comprehensions Versus map

Let’s work through an example that demonstrates the basics. As we saw in Chapter 7, Python’s built-in ord function returns the ASCII integer code of a single character (the chr built-in is the converse—it returns the character for an ASCII integer code):

>>> ord('s')
115

Now, suppose we wish to collect the ASCII codes of all characters in an entire string. Perhaps the most straightforward approach is to use a simple for loop and append the results to a list:

>>> res = []
>>> for x in 'spam':
...     res.append(ord(x))
...
>>> res
[115, 112, 97, 109]

Now that we know about map, though, we can achieve similar results with a single function call without having to manage list construction in the code:

>>> res = list(map(ord, 'spam'))          # Apply function to sequence
>>> res
[115, 112, 97, 109]

However, we can get the same results from a list comprehension expression—while map maps a function over a sequence, list comprehensions map an expression over a sequence:

>>> res = [ord(x) for x in 'spam']        # Apply expression to sequence
>>> res
[115, 112, 97, 109]

List comprehensions collect the results of applying an arbitrary expression to a sequence of values and return them in a new list. Syntactically, list comprehensions are enclosed in square brackets (to remind you that they construct lists). In their simple form, within the brackets you code an expression that names a variable followed by what looks like a for loop header that names the same variable. Python then collects the expression’s results for each iteration of the implied loop.

The effect of the preceding example is similar to that of the manual for loop and the map call. List comprehensions become more convenient, though, when we wish to apply an arbitrary expression to a sequence:

>>> [x ** 2 for x in range(10)]
[0, 1, 4, 9, 16, 25, 36, 49, 64, 81]

Here, we’ve collected the squares of the numbers 0 through 9 (we’re just letting the interactive prompt print the resulting list; assign it to a variable if you need to retain it). To do similar work with a map call, we would probably need to invent a little function to implement the square operation. Because we won’t need this function elsewhere, we’d typically (but not necessarily) code it inline, with a lambda, instead of using a def statement elsewhere:

>>> list(map((lambda x: x ** 2), range(10)))
[0, 1, 4, 9, 16, 25, 36, 49, 64, 81]

This does the same job, and it’s only a few keystrokes longer than the equivalent list comprehension. It’s also only marginally more complex (at least, once you understand the lambda). For more advanced kinds of expressions, though, list comprehensions will often require considerably less typing. The next section shows why.

Adding Tests and Nested Loops: filter

List comprehensions are even more general than shown so far. For instance, as we learned in Chapter 14, you can code an if clause after the for to add selection logic. List comprehensions with if clauses can be thought of as analogous to the filter built-in discussed in the prior chapter—they skip sequence items for which the if clause is not true.

To demonstrate, here are both schemes picking up even numbers from 0 to 4; like the map list comprehension alternative of the prior section, the filter version here must invent a little lambda function for the test expression. For comparison, the equivalent for loop is shown here as well:

>>> [x for x in range(5) if x % 2 == 0]
[0, 2, 4]

>>> list(filter((lambda x: x % 2 == 0), range(5)))
[0, 2, 4]

>>> res = []
>>> for x in range(5):
...     if x % 2 == 0:
...         res.append(x)
...
>>> res
[0, 2, 4]

All of these use the modulus (remainder of division) operator, %, to detect even numbers: if there is no remainder after dividing a number by 2, it must be even. The filter call here is not much longer than the list comprehension either. However, we can combine an if clause and an arbitrary expression in our list comprehension, to give it the effect of a filter and a map, in a single expression:

>>> [x ** 2 for x in range(10) if x % 2 == 0]
[0, 4, 16, 36, 64]

This time, we collect the squares of the even numbers from 0 through 9: the for loop skips numbers for which the attached if clause on the right is false, and the expression on the left computes the squares. The equivalent map call would require a lot more work on our part—we would have to combine filter selections with map iteration, making for a noticeably more complex expression:

>>> list( map((lambda x: x**2), filter((lambda x: x % 2 == 0), range(10))) )
[0, 4, 16, 36, 64]

In fact, list comprehensions are more general still. You can code any number of nested for loops in a list comprehension, and each may have an optional associated if test. The general structure of list comprehensions looks like this:

[ expression for target1 in iterable1 [if condition1]
             for target2 in iterable2 [if condition2] ...
             for targetN in iterableN [if conditionN] ]

When for clauses are nested within a list comprehension, they work like equivalent nested for loop statements. For example, the following:

>>> res = [x + y for x in [0, 1, 2] for y in [100, 200, 300]]
>>> res
[100, 200, 300, 101, 201, 301, 102, 202, 302]

has the same effect as this substantially more verbose equivalent:

>>> res = []
>>> for x in [0, 1, 2]:
...     for y in [100, 200, 300]:
...         res.append(x + y)
...
>>> res
[100, 200, 300, 101, 201, 301, 102, 202, 302]

Although list comprehensions construct lists, remember that they can iterate over any sequence or other iterable type. Here’s a similar bit of code that traverses strings instead of lists of numbers, and so collects concatenation results:

>>> [x + y for x in 'spam' for y in 'SPAM']
['sS', 'sP', 'sA', 'sM', 'pS', 'pP', 'pA', 'pM',
'aS', 'aP', 'aA', 'aM', 'mS', 'mP', 'mA', 'mM']

Finally, here is a much more complex list comprehension that illustrates the effect of attached if selections on nested for clauses:

>>> [(x, y) for x in range(5) if x % 2 == 0 for y in range(5) if y % 2 == 1]
[(0, 1), (0, 3), (2, 1), (2, 3), (4, 1), (4, 3)]

This expression permutes even numbers from 0 through 4 with odd numbers from 0 through 4. The if clauses filter out items in each sequence iteration. Here is the equivalent statement-based code:

>>> res = []
>>> for x in range(5):
...     if x % 2 == 0:
...         for y in range(5):
...             if y % 2 == 1:
...                 res.append((x, y))
...
>>> res
[(0, 1), (0, 3), (2, 1), (2, 3), (4, 1), (4, 3)]

Recall that if you’re confused about what a complex list comprehension does, you can always nest the list comprehension’s for and if clauses inside each other (indenting successively further to the right) to derive the equivalent statements. The result is longer, but perhaps clearer.

The map and filter equivalent would be wildly complex and deeply nested, so I won’t even try showing it here. I’ll leave its coding as an exercise for Zen masters, ex-Lisp programmers, and the criminally insane....

List Comprehensions and Matrixes

Not all list comprehensions are so artificial, of course. Let’s look at one more application to stretch a few synapses. One basic way to code matrixes (a.k.a. multidimensional arrays) in Python is with nested list structures. The following, for example, defines two 3 × 3 matrixes as lists of nested lists:

>>> M = [[1, 2, 3],
...      [4, 5, 6],
...      [7, 8, 9]]

>>> N = [[2, 2, 2],
...      [3, 3, 3],
...      [4, 4, 4]]

Given this structure, we can always index rows, and columns within rows, using normal index operations:

>>> M[1]
[4, 5, 6]

>>> M[1][2]
6

List comprehensions are powerful tools for processing such structures, though, because they automatically scan rows and columns for us. For instance, although this structure stores the matrix by rows, to collect the second column we can simply iterate across the rows and pull out the desired column, or iterate through positions in the rows and index as we go:

>>> [row[1] for row in M]
[2, 5, 8]

>>> [M[row][1] for row in (0, 1, 2)]
[2, 5, 8]

Given positions, we can also easily perform tasks such as pulling out a diagonal. The following expression uses range to generate the list of offsets and then indexes with the row and column the same, picking out M[0][0], then M[1][1], and so on (we assume the matrix has the same number of rows and columns):

>>> [M[i][i] for i in range(len(M))]
[1, 5, 9]

Finally, with a bit of creativity, we can also use list comprehensions to combine multiple matrixes. The following first builds a flat list that contains the result of multiplying the matrixes pairwise, and then builds a nested list structure having the same values by nesting list comprehensions:

>>> [M[row][col] * N[row][col] for row in range(3) for col in range(3)]
[2, 4, 6, 12, 15, 18, 28, 32, 36]

>>> [[M[row][col] * N[row][col] for col in range(3)] for row in range(3)]
[[2, 4, 6], [12, 15, 18], [28, 32, 36]]

This last expression works because the row iteration is an outer loop: for each row, it runs the nested column iteration to build up one row of the result matrix. It’s equivalent to this statement-based code:

>>> res = []
>>> for row in range(3):
...     tmp = []
...     for col in range(3):
...         tmp.append(M[row][col] * N[row][col])
...     res.append(tmp)
...
>>> res
[[2, 4, 6], [12, 15, 18], [28, 32, 36]]

Compared to these statements, the list comprehension version requires only one line of code, will probably run substantially faster for large matrixes, and just might make your head explode! Which brings us to the next section.

Comprehending List Comprehensions

With such generality, list comprehensions can quickly become, well, incomprehensible, especially when nested. Consequently, my advice is typically to use simple for loops when getting started with Python, and map or comprehensions in isolated cases where they are easy to apply. The “keep it simple” rule applies here, as always: code conciseness is a much less important goal than code readability.

However, in this case, there is currently a substantial performance advantage to the extra complexity: based on tests run under Python today, map calls are roughly twice as fast as equivalent for loops, and list comprehensions are usually slightly faster than map calls.[43] This speed difference is generally due to the fact that map and list comprehensions run at C language speed inside the interpreter, which is much faster than stepping through Python for loop code within the PVM.

Because for loops make logic more explicit, I recommend them in general on the grounds of simplicity. However, map and list comprehensions are worth knowing and using for simpler kinds of iterations, and if your application’s speed is an important consideration. In addition, because map and list comprehensions are both expressions, they can show up syntactically in places that for loop statements cannot, such as in the bodies of lambda functions, within list and dictionary literals, and more. Still, you should try to keep your map calls and list comprehensions simple; for more complex tasks, use full statements instead.

Why You Will Care: List Comprehensions and map

Here’s a more realistic example of list comprehensions and map in action (we solved this problem with list comprehensions in Chapter 14, but we’ll revive it here to add map-based alternatives). Recall that the file readlines method returns lines with \n end-of-line characters at the ends:

>>> open('myfile').readlines()
['aaa\n', 'bbb\n', 'ccc\n']

If you don’t want the end-of-line characters, you can slice them off all the lines in a single step with a list comprehension or a map call (map results are iterables in Python 3.0, so we must run them through list to see all their results at once):

>>> [line.rstrip() for line in open('myfile').readlines()]
['aaa', 'bbb', 'ccc']

>>> [line.rstrip() for line in open('myfile')]
['aaa', 'bbb', 'ccc']

>>> list(map((lambda line: line.rstrip()), open('myfile')))
['aaa', 'bbb', 'ccc']

The last two of these make use of file iterators (which essentially means that you don’t need a method call to grab all the lines in iteration contexts such as these). The map call is slightly longer than the list comprehension, but neither has to manage result list construction explicitly.

A list comprehension can also be used as a sort of column projection operation. Python’s standard SQL database API returns query results as a list of tuples much like the following—the list is the table, tuples are rows, and items in tuples are column values:

listoftuple = [('bob', 35, 'mgr'), ('mel', 40, 'dev')]

A for loop could pick up all the values from a selected column manually, but map and list comprehensions can do it in a single step, and faster:

>>> [age for (name, age, job) in listoftuple]
[35, 40]

>>> list(map((lambda row: row[1]), listoftuple))
[35, 40]

The first of these makes use of tuple assignment to unpack row tuples in the list, and the second uses indexing. In Python 2.6 (but not in 3.0—see the note on 2.6 argument unpacking in Chapter 18), map can use tuple unpacking on its argument, too:

# 2.6 only
>>> list(map((lambda (name, age, job): age), listoftuple))
[35, 40]

See other books and resources for more on Python’s database API.

Beside the distinction between running functions versus expressions, the biggest difference between map and list comprehensions in Python 3.0 is that map is an iterator, generating results on demand; to achieve the same memory economy, list comprehensions must be coded as generator expressions (one of the topics of this chapter).

Iterators Revisited: Generators

Python today supports procrastination much more than it did in the past—it provides tools that produce results only when needed, instead of all at once. In particular, two language constructs delay result creation whenever possible:

Generator functions are coded as normal def statements but use yield statements to return results one at a time, suspending and resuming their state between each.

Generator expressions are similar to the list comprehensions of the prior section, but they return an object that produces results on demand instead of building a result list.

Because neither constructs a result list all at once, they save memory space and allow computation time to be split across result requests. As we’ll see, both of these ultimately perform their delayed-results magic by implementing the iteration protocol we studied in Chapter 14.

Generator Functions: yield Versus return

In this part of the book, we’ve learned about coding normal functions that receive input parameters and send back a single result immediately. It is also possible, however, to write functions that may send back a value and later be resumed, picking up where they left off. Such functions are known as generator functions because they generate a sequence of values over time.

Generator functions are like normal functions in most respects, and in fact are coded with normal def statements. However, when created, they are automatically made to implement the iteration protocol so that they can appear in iteration contexts. We studied iterators in Chapter 14; here, we’ll revisit them to see how they relate to generators.

State suspension

Unlike normal functions that return a value and exit, generator functions automatically suspend and resume their execution and state around the point of value generation. Because of that, they are often a useful alternative to both computing an entire series of values up front and manually saving and restoring state in classes. Because the state that generator functions retain when they are suspended includes their entire local scope, their local variables retain information and make it available when the functions are resumed.

The chief code difference between generator and normal functions is that a generator yields a value, rather than returning one—the yield statement suspends the function and sends a value back to the caller, but retains enough state to enable the function to resume from where it left off. When resumed, the function continues execution immediately after the last yield run. From the function’s perspective, this allows its code to produce a series of values over time, rather than computing them all at once and sending them back in something like a list.

Iteration protocol integration

To truly understand generator functions, you need to know that they are closely bound up with the notion of the iteration protocol in Python. As we’ve seen, iterable objects define a __next__ method, which either returns the next item in the iteration, or raises the special StopIteration exception to end the iteration. An object’s iterator is fetched with the iter built-in function.

Python for loops, and all other iteration contexts, use this iteration protocol to step through a sequence or value generator, if the protocol is supported; if not, iteration falls back on repeatedly indexing sequences instead.

To support this protocol, functions containing a yield statement are compiled specially as generators. When called, they return a generator object that supports the iteration interface with an automatically created method named __next__ to resume execution. Generator functions may also have a return statement that, along with falling off the end of the def block, simply terminates the generation of values—technically, by raising a StopIteration exception after any normal function exit actions. From the caller’s perspective, the generator’s __next__ method resumes the function and runs until either the next yield result is returned or a StopIteration is raised.

The net effect is that generator functions, coded as def statements containing yield statements, are automatically made to support the iteration protocol and thus may be used in any iteration context to produce results over time and on demand.

Note

As noted in Chapter 14, in Python 2.6 and earlier, iterable objects define a method named next instead of __next__. This includes the generator objects we are using here. In 3.0 this method is renamed to __next__. The next built-in function is provided as a convenience and portability tool: next(I) is the same as I.__next__() in 3.0 and I.next() in 2.6. Prior to 2.6, programs simply call I.next() instead to iterate manually.

Generator functions in action

To illustrate generator basics, let’s turn to some code. The following code defines a generator function that can be used to generate the squares of a series of numbers over time:

>>> def gensquares(N):
...     for i in range(N):
...         yield i ** 2        # Resume here later
...

This function yields a value, and so returns to its caller, each time through the loop; when it is resumed, its prior state is restored and control picks up again immediately after the yield statement. For example, when it’s used in the body of a for loop, control returns to the function after its yield statement each time through the loop:

>>> for i in gensquares(5):     # Resume the function
...     print(i, end=' : ')     # Print last yielded value
...
0 : 1 : 4 : 9 : 16 :
>>>

To end the generation of values, functions either use a return statement with no value or simply allow control to fall off the end of the function body.

If you want to see what is going on inside the for, call the generator function directly:

>>> x = gensquares(4)
>>> x
<generator object at 0x0086C378>

You get back a generator object that supports the iteration protocol we met in Chapter 14—the generator object has a __next__ method that starts the function, or resumes it from where it last yielded a value, and raises a StopIteration exception when the end of the series of values is reached. For convenience, the next(X) built-in calls an object’s X.__next__() method for us:

>>> next(x)                     # Same as x.__next__() in 3.0
0
>>> next(x)                     # Use x.next() or next() in 2.6
1
>>> next(x)
4
>>> next(x)
9
>>> next(x)

Traceback (most recent call last):
...more text omitted...
StopIteration

As we learned in Chapter 14, for loops (and other iteration contexts) work with generators in the same way—by calling the __next__ method repeatedly, until an exception is caught. If the object to be iterated over does not support this protocol, for loops instead use the indexing protocol to iterate.

Note that in this example, we could also simply build the list of yielded values all at once:

>>> def buildsquares(n):
...     res = []
...     for i in range(n): res.append(i ** 2)
...     return res
...
>>> for x in buildsquares(5): print(x, end=' : ')
...
0 : 1 : 4 : 9 : 16 :

For that matter, we could use any of the for loop, map, or list comprehension techniques:

>>> for x in [n ** 2 for n in range(5)]:
...     print(x, end=' : ')
...
0 : 1 : 4 : 9 : 16 :

>>> for x in map((lambda n: n ** 2), range(5)):
...     print(x, end=' : ')
...
0 : 1 : 4 : 9 : 16 :

However, generators can be better in terms of both memory use and performance. They allow functions to avoid doing all the work up front, which is especially useful when the result lists are large or when it takes a lot of computation to produce each value. Generators distribute the time required to produce the series of values among loop iterations.

Moreover, for more advanced uses, generators can provide a simpler alternative to manually saving the state between iterations in class objects—with generators, variables accessible in the function’s scopes are saved and restored automatically.[44] We’ll discuss class-based iterators in more detail in Part VI.

Extended generator function protocol: send versus next

In Python 2.5, a send method was added to the generator function protocol. The send method advances to the next item in the series of results, just like __next__, but also provides a way for the caller to communicate with the generator, to affect its operation.

Technically, yield is now an expression form that returns the item passed to send, not a statement (though it can be called either way—as yield X, or A = (yield X)). The expression must be enclosed in parentheses unless it’s the only item on the right side of the assignment statement. For example, X = yield Y is OK, as is X = (yield Y) + 42.

When this extra protocol is used, values are sent into a generator G by calling G.send(value). The generator’s code is then resumed, and the yield expression in the generator returns the value passed to send. If the regular G.__next__() method (or its next(G) equivalent) is called to advance, the yield simply returns None. For example:

>>> def gen():
...    for i in range(10):
...        X = yield i
...        print(X)
...
>>> G = gen()
>>> next(G)              # Must call next() first, to start generator
0
>>> G.send(77)           # Advance, and send value to yield expression
77
1
>>> G.send(88)
88
2
>>> next(G)              # next() and X.__next__() send None
None
3

The send method can be used, for example, to code a generator that its caller can terminate by sending a termination code, or redirect by passing a new position. In addition, generators in 2.5 also support a throw(type) method to raise an exception inside the generator at the latest yield, and a close method that raises a special GeneratorExit exception inside the generator to terminate the iteration. These are advanced features that we won’t delve into in more detail here; see reference texts and Python’s standard manuals for more information.

Note that while Python 3.0 provides a next(X) convenience built-in that calls the X.__next__() method of an object, other generator methods, like send, must be called as methods of generator objects directly (e.g., G.send(X)). This makes sense if you realize that these extra methods are implemented on built-in generator objects only, whereas the __next__ method applies to all iterable objects (both built-in types and user-defined classes).

Generator Expressions: Iterators Meet Comprehensions

In all recent versions of Python, the notions of iterators and list comprehensions are combined in a new feature of the language, generator expressions. Syntactically, generator expressions are just like normal list comprehensions, but they are enclosed in parentheses instead of square brackets:

>>> [x ** 2 for x in range(4)]          # List comprehension: build a list
[0, 1, 4, 9]

>>> (x ** 2 for x in range(4))          # Generator expression: make an iterable
<generator object at 0x011DC648>

In fact, at least on a function basis, coding a list comprehension is essentially the same as wrapping a generator expression in a list built-in call to force it to produce all its results in a list at once:

>>> list(x ** 2 for x in range(4))      # List comprehension equivalence
[0, 1, 4, 9]

Operationally, however, generator expressions are very different—instead of building the result list in memory, they return a generator object, which in turn supports the iteration protocol to yield one piece of the result list at a time in any iteration context:

>>> G = (x ** 2 for x in range(4))
>>> next(G)
0
>>> next(G)
1
>>> next(G)
4
>>> next(G)
9
>>> next(G)

Traceback (most recent call last):
...more text omitted...
StopIteration

We don’t typically see the next iterator machinery under the hood of a generator expression like this because for loops trigger it for us automatically:

>>> for num in (x ** 2 for x in range(4)):
...     print('%s, %s' % (num, num / 2.0))
...
0, 0.0
1, 0.5
4, 2.0
9, 4.5

As we’ve already learned, every iteration context does this, including the sum, map, and sorted built-in functions; list comprehensions; and other iteration contexts we learned about in Chapter 14, such as the any, all, and list built-in functions.

Notice that the parentheses are not required around a generator expression if they are the sole item enclosed in other parentheses, like those of a function call. Extra parentheses are required, however, in the second call to sorted:

>>> sum(x ** 2 for x in range(4))
14

>>> sorted(x ** 2 for x in range(4))
[0, 1, 4, 9]

>>> sorted((x ** 2 for x in range(4)), reverse=True)
[9, 4, 1, 0]

>>> import math
>>> list( map(math.sqrt, (x ** 2 for x in range(4))) )
[0.0, 1.0, 2.0, 3.0]

Generator expressions are primarily a memory-space optimization—they do not require the entire result list to be constructed all at once, as the square-bracketed list comprehension does. They may also run slightly slower in practice, so they are probably best used only for very large result sets. A more authoritative statement about performance, though, will have to await the timing script we’ll code later in this chapter.

Generator Functions Versus Generator Expressions

Interestingly, the same iteration can often be coded with either a generator function or a generator expression. The following generator expression, for example, repeats each character in a string four times:

>>> G = (c * 4 for c in 'SPAM')           # Generator expression
>>> list(G)                               # Force generator to produce all results
['SSSS', 'PPPP', 'AAAA', 'MMMM']

The equivalent generator function requires slightly more code, but as a multistatement function it will be able to code more logic and use more state information if needed:

>>> def timesfour(S):                     # Generator function
...     for c in S:
...         yield c * 4
...
>>> G = timesfour('spam')
>>> list(G)                               # Iterate automatically
['ssss', 'pppp', 'aaaa', 'mmmm']

Both expressions and functions support both automatic and manual iteration—the prior list call iterates automatically, and the following iterate manually:

>>> G = (c * 4 for c in 'SPAM')
>>> I = iter(G)                           # Iterate manually
>>> next(I)
'SSSS'
>>> next(I)
'PPPP'

>>> G = timesfour('spam')
>>> I = iter(G)
>>> next(I)
'ssss'
>>> next(I)
'pppp'

Notice that we make new generators here to iterate again—as explained in the next section, generators are one-shot iterators.

Generators Are Single-Iterator Objects

Both generator functions and generator expressions are their own iterators and thus support just one active iteration—unlike some built-in types, you can’t have multiple iterators of either positioned at different locations in the set of results. For example, using the prior section’s generator expression, a generator’s iterator is the generator itself (in fact, calling iter on a generator is a no-op):

>>> G = (c * 4 for c in 'SPAM')
>>> iter(G) is G                          # My iterator is myself: G has __next__
True

If you iterate over the results stream manually with multiple iterators, they will all point to the same position:

>>> G = (c * 4 for c in 'SPAM')           # Make a new generator
>>> I1 = iter(G)                          # Iterate manually
>>> next(I1)
'SSSS'
>>> next(I1)
'PPPP'
>>> I2 = iter(G)                          # Second iterator at same position!
>>> next(I2)
'AAAA'

Moreover, once any iteration runs to completion, all are exhausted—we have to make a new generator to start again:

>>> list(I1)                              # Collect the rest of I1's items
['MMMM']
>>> next(I2)                              # Other iterators exhausted too
StopIteration

>>> I3 = iter(G)                          # Ditto for new iterators
>>> next(I3)
StopIteration

>>> I3 = iter(c * 4 for c in 'SPAM')      # New generator to start over
>>> next(I3)
'SSSS'

The same holds true for generator functions—the following def statement-based equivalent supports just one active iterator and is exhausted after one pass:

>>> def timesfour(S):
...     for c in S:
...         yield c * 4
...
>>> G = timesfour('spam')                 # Generator functions work the same way
>>> iter(G) is G
True
>>> I1, I2 = iter(G), iter(G)
>>> next(I1)
'ssss'
>>> next(I1)
'pppp'
>>> next(I2)                              # I2 at same position as I1
'aaaa'

This is different from the behavior of some built-in types, which support multiple iterators and passes and reflect their in-place changes in active iterators:

>>> L = [1, 2, 3, 4]
>>> I1, I2 = iter(L), iter(L)
>>> next(I1)
1
>>> next(I1)
2
>>> next(I2)                              # Lists support multiple iterators
1
>>> del L[2:]                             # Changes reflected in iterators
>>> next(I1)
StopIteration

When we begin coding class-based iterators in Part VI, we’ll see that it’s up to us to decide how many iterations we wish to support for our objects, if any.

Emulating zip and map with Iteration Tools

To demonstrate the power of iteration tools in action, let’s turn to some more advanced use case examples. Once you know about list comprehensions, generators, and other iteration tools, it turns out that emulating many of Python’s functional built-ins is both straightforward and instructive.

For example, we’ve already seen how the built-in zip and map functions combine iterables and project functions across them, respectively. With multiple sequence arguments, map projects the function across items taken from each sequence in much the same way that zip pairs them up:

>>> S1 = 'abc'
>>> S2 = 'xyz123'
>>> list(zip(S1, S2))                     # zip pairs items from iterables
[('a', 'x'), ('b', 'y'), ('c', 'z')]

# zip pairs items, truncates at shortest

>>> list(zip([−2, −1, 0, 1, 2]))               # Single sequence: 1-ary tuples
[(−2,), (−1,), (0,), (1,), (2,)]

>>> list(zip([1, 2, 3], [2, 3, 4, 5]))         # N sequences: N-ary tuples
[(1, 2), (2, 3), (3, 4)]

# map passes paired itenms to a function, truncates

>>> list(map(abs, [−2, −1, 0, 1, 2]))          # Single sequence: 1-ary function
[2, 1, 0, 1, 2]

>>> list(map(pow, [1, 2, 3], [2, 3, 4, 5]))    # N sequences: N-ary function
[1, 8, 81]

Though they’re being used for different purposes, if you study these examples long enough, you might notice a relationship between zip results and mapped function arguments that our next example can exploit.

Coding your own map(func, ...)

Although the map and zip built-ins are fast and convenient, it’s always possible to emulate them in code of our own. In the preceding chapter, for example, we saw a function that emulated the map built-in for a single sequence argument. It doesn’t take much more work to allow for multiple sequences, as the built-in does:

# map(func, seqs...) workalike with zip

def mymap(func, *seqs):
    res = []
    for args in zip(*seqs):
        res.append(func(*args))
    return res

print(mymap(abs, [−2, −1, 0, 1, 2]))
print(mymap(pow, [1, 2, 3], [2, 3, 4, 5]))

This version relies heavily upon the special *args argument-passing syntax—it collects multiple sequence (really, iterable) arguments, unpacks them as zip arguments to combine, and then unpacks the paired zip results as arguments to the passed-in function. That is, we’re using the fact that the zipping is essentially a nested operation in mapping. The test code at the bottom applies this to both one and two sequences to produce this output (the same we would get with the built-in map):

[2, 1, 0, 1, 2]
[1, 8, 81]

Really, though, the prior version exhibits the classic list comprehension pattern, building a list of operation results within a for loop. We can code our map more concisely as an equivalent one-line list comprehension:

# Using a list comprehension

def mymap(func, *seqs):
    return [func(*args) for args in zip(*seqs)]

print(mymap(abs, [−2, −1, 0, 1, 2]))
print(mymap(pow, [1, 2, 3], [2, 3, 4, 5]))

When this is run the result is the same as before, but the code is more concise and might run faster (more on performance in the section Timing Iteration Alternatives). Both of the preceding mymap versions build result lists all at once, though, and this can waste memory for larger lists. Now that we know about generator functions and expressions, it’s simple to recode both these alternatives to produce results on demand instead:

# Using generators: yield and (...)

def mymap(func, *seqs):
    res = []
    for args in zip(*seqs):
        yield func(*args)

def mymap(func, *seqs):
    return (func(*args) for args in zip(*seqs))

These versions produce the same results but return generators designed to support the iteration protocol—the first yields one result at a time, and the second returns a generator expression’s result to do the same. They produce the same results if we wrap them in list calls to force them to produce their values all at once:

print(list(mymap(abs, [−2, −1, 0, 1, 2])))
print(list(mymap(pow, [1, 2, 3], [2, 3, 4, 5])))

No work is really done here until the list calls force the generators to run, by activating the iteration protocol. The generators returned by these functions themselves, as well as that returned by the Python 3.0 flavor of the zip built-in they use, produce results only on demand.

Coding your own zip(...) and map(None, ...)

Of course, much of the magic in the examples shown so far lies in their use of the zip built-in to pair arguments from multiple sequences. You’ll also note that our map workalikes are really emulating the behavior of the Python 3.0 map—they truncate at the length of the shortest sequence, and they do not support the notion of padding results when lengths differ, as map does in Python 2.X with a None argument:

C:\misc> c:\python26\python
>>> map(None, [1, 2, 3], [2, 3, 4, 5])
[(1, 2), (2, 3), (3, 4), (None, 5)]
>>> map(None, 'abc', 'xyz123')
[('a', 'x'), ('b', 'y'), ('c', 'z'), (None, '1'), (None, '2'), (None, '3')]

Using iteration tools, we can code workalikes that emulate both truncating zip and 2.6’s padding map—these turn out to be nearly the same in code:

# zip(seqs...) and 2.6 map(None, seqs...) workalikes

def myzip(*seqs):
    seqs = [list(S) for S in seqs]
    res  = []
    while all(seqs):
        res.append(tuple(S.pop(0) for S in seqs))
    return res

def mymapPad(*seqs, pad=None):
    seqs = [list(S) for S in seqs]
    res  = []
    while any(seqs):
        res.append(tuple((S.pop(0) if S else pad) for S in seqs))
    return res

S1, S2 = 'abc', 'xyz123'
print(myzip(S1, S2))
print(mymapPad(S1, S2))
print(mymapPad(S1, S2, pad=99))

Both of the functions coded here work on any type of iterable object, because they run their arguments through the list built-in to force result generation (e.g., files would work as arguments, in addition to sequences like strings). Notice the use of the all and any built-ins here—these return True if all and any items in an iterable are True (or equivalently, nonempty), respectively. These built-ins are used to stop looping when any or all of the listified arguments become empty after deletions.

Also note the use of the Python 3.0 keyword-only argument, pad; unlike the 2.6 map, our version will allow any pad object to be specified (if you’re using 2.6, use a **kargs form to support this option instead; see Chapter 18 for details). When these functions are run, the following results are printed—a zip, and two padding maps:

[('a', 'x'), ('b', 'y'), ('c', 'z')]
[('a', 'x'), ('b', 'y'), ('c', 'z'), (None, '1'), (None, '2'), (None, '3')]
[('a', 'x'), ('b', 'y'), ('c', 'z'), (99, '1'), (99, '2'), (99, '3')]

These functions aren’t amenable to list comprehension translation because their loops are too specific. As before, though, while our zip and map workalikes currently build and return result lists, it’s just as easy to turn them into generators with yield so that they each return one piece of their result set at a time. The results are the same as before, but we need to use list again to force the generators to yield their values for display:

# Using generators: yield

def myzip(*seqs):
    seqs = [list(S) for S in seqs]
    while all(seqs):
        yield tuple(S.pop(0) for S in seqs)

def mymapPad(*seqs, pad=None):
    seqs = [list(S) for S in seqs]
    while any(seqs):
        yield tuple((S.pop(0) if S else pad) for S in seqs)

S1, S2 = 'abc', 'xyz123'
print(list(myzip(S1, S2)))
print(list(mymapPad(S1, S2)))
print(list(mymapPad(S1, S2, pad=99)))

Finally, here’s an alternative implementation of our zip and map emulators—rather than deleting arguments from lists with the pop method, the following versions do their job by calculating the minimum and maximum argument lengths. Armed with these lengths, it’s easy to code nested list comprehensions to step through argument index ranges:

# Alternate implementation with lengths

def myzip(*seqs):
    minlen = min(len(S) for S in seqs)
    return [tuple(S[i] for S in seqs) for i in range(minlen)]

def mymapPad(*seqs, pad=None):
    maxlen = max(len(S) for S in seqs)
    index  = range(maxlen)
    return [tuple((S[i] if len(S) > i else pad) for S in seqs) for i in index]

S1, S2 = 'abc', 'xyz123'
print(myzip(S1, S2))
print(mymapPad(S1, S2))
print(mymapPad(S1, S2, pad=99))

Because these use len and indexing, they assume that arguments are sequences or similar, not arbitrary iterables. The outer comprehensions here step through argument index ranges, and the inner comprehensions (passed to tuple) step through the passed-in sequences to pull out arguments in parallel. When they’re run, the results are as before.

Most strikingly, generators and iterators seem to run rampant in this example. The arguments passed to min and max are generator expressions, which run to completion before the nested comprehensions begin iterating. Moreover, the nested list comprehensions employ two levels of delayed evaluation—the Python 3.0 range built-in is an iterable, as is the generator expression argument to tuple.

In fact, no results are produced here until the square brackets of the list comprehensions request values to place in the result list—they force the comprehensions and generators to run. To turn these functions themselves into generators instead of list builders, use parentheses instead of square brackets again. Here’s the case for our zip:

# Using generators: (...)

def myzip(*seqs):
    minlen = min(len(S) for S in seqs)
    return (tuple(S[i] for S in seqs) for i in range(minlen))

print(list(myzip(S1, S2)))

In this case, it takes a list call to activate the generators and iterators to produce their results. Experiment with these on your own for more details. Developing further coding alternatives is left as a suggested exercise (see also the sidebar for investigation of one such option).

Why You Will Care: One-Shot Iterations

In Chapter 14, we saw how some built-ins (like map) support only a single traversal and are empty after it occurs, and I promised to show you an example of how that can become subtle but important in practice. Now that we’ve studied a few more iteration topics, I can make good on this promise. Consider the following clever alternative coding for this chapter’s zip emulation examples, adapted from one in Python’s manuals:

def myzip(*args):
    iters = map(iter, args)
    while iters:
        res = [next(i) for i in iters]
        yield tuple(res)

Because this code uses iter and next, it works on any type of iterable. Note that there is no reason to catch the StopIteration raised by the next(it) inside the comprehension here when any one of the arguments’ iterators is exhausted—allowing it to pass ends this generator function and has the same effect that a return statement would. The while iters: suffices to loop if at least one argument is passed, and avoids an infinite loop otherwise (the list comprehension would always return an empty list).

This code works fine in Python 2.6 as is:

>>> list(myzip('abc', 'lmnop'))
[('a', 'l'), ('b', 'm'), ('c', 'n')]

But it falls into an infinite loop and fails in Python 3.0, because the 3.0 map returns a one-shot iterable object instead of a list as in 2.6. In 3.0, as soon as we’ve run the list comprehension inside the loop once, iters will be empty (and res will be []) forever. To make this work in 3.0, we need to use the list built-in function to create an object that can support multiple iterations:

def myzip(*args):
    iters = list(map(iter, args))
    ...rest as is...

Run this on your own to trace its operation. The lesson here: wrapping map calls in list calls in 3.0 is not just for display!

Value Generation in Built-in Types and Classes

Finally, although we’ve focused on coding value generators ourselves in this section, don’t forget that many built-in types behave in similar ways—as we saw in Chapter 14, for example, dictionaries have iterators that produce keys on each iteration:

>>> D = {'a':1, 'b':2, 'c':3}
>>> x = iter(D)
>>> next(x)
'a'
>>> next(x)
'c'

Like the values produced by handcoded generators, dictionary keys may be iterated over both manually and with automatic iteration tools including for loops, map calls, list comprehensions, and the many other contexts we met in Chapter 14:

>>> for key in D:
...     print(key, D[key])
...
a 1
c 3
b 2

As we’ve also seen, for file iterators, Python simply loads lines from the file on demand:

>>> for line in open('temp.txt'):
...     print(line, end='')
...
Tis but
a flesh wound.

While built-in type iterators are bound to a specific type of value generation, the concept is similar to generators we code with expressions and functions. Iteration contexts like for loops accept any iterable, whether user-defined or built-in.

Although beyond the scope of this chapter, it is also possible to implement arbitrary user-defined generator objects with classes that conform to the iteration protocol. Such classes define a special __iter__ method run by the iter built-in function that returns an object having a __next__ method run by the next built-in function (a __getitem__ indexing method is also available as a fallback option for iteration).

The instance objects created from such a class are considered iterable and may be used in for loops and all other iteration contexts. With classes, though, we have access to richer logic and data structuring options than other generator constructs can offer.

The iterator story won’t really be complete until we’ve seen how it maps to classes, too. For now, we’ll have to settle for postponing its conclusion until we study class-based iterators in Chapter 29.

Function Gotchas

Now that we’ve reached the end of the function story, let’s review some common pitfalls. Functions have some jagged edges that you might not expect. They’re all obscure, and a few have started to fall away from the language completely in recent releases, but most have been known to trip up new users.

Local Names Are Detected Statically

As you know, Python classifies names assigned in a function as locals by default; they live in the function’s scope and exist only while the function is running. What you may not realize is that Python detects locals statically, when it compiles the def’s code, rather than by noticing assignments as they happen at runtime. This leads to one of the most common oddities posted on the Python newsgroup by beginners.

Normally, a name that isn’t assigned in a function is looked up in the enclosing module:

>>> X = 99

>>> def selector():       # X used but not assigned
...     print(X)          # X found in global scope
...
>>> selector()
99

Here, the X in the function resolves to the X in the module. But watch what happens if you add an assignment to X after the reference:

>>> def selector():
...     print(X)          # Does not yet exist!
...     X = 88            # X classified as a local name (everywhere)
...                       # Can also happen for "import X", "def X"...
>>> selector()
UnboundLocalError: local variable 'X' referenced before assignment

You get the name usage error shown here, but the reason is subtle. Python reads and compiles this code when it’s typed interactively or imported from a module. While compiling, Python sees the assignment to X and decides that X will be a local name everywhere in the function. But when the function is actually run, because the assignment hasn’t yet happened when the print executes, Python says you’re using an undefined name. According to its name rules, it should say this; the local X is used before being assigned. In fact, any assignment in a function body makes a name local. Imports, =, nested defs, nested classes, and so on are all susceptible to this behavior.

The problem occurs because assigned names are treated as locals everywhere in a function, not just after the statements where they're assigned. The previous example is ambiguous: was the intention to print the global X and create a local X, or is this a real programming error? Because Python treats X as a local everywhere, it’s seen as an error; if you mean to print the global X, you need to declare it in a global statement:

>>> def selector():
...     global X                # Force X to be global (everywhere)
...     print(X)
...     X = 88
...
>>> selector()
99

Remember, though, that this means the assignment also changes the global X, not a local X. Within a function, you can’t use both local and global versions of the same simple name. If you really meant to print the global and then set a local of the same name, you’d need to import the enclosing module and use module attribute notation to get to the global version:

>>> X = 99
>>> def selector():
...     import __main__         # Import enclosing module
...     print(__main__.X)       # Qualify to get to global version of name
...     X = 88                  # Unqualified X classified as local
...     print(X)                # Prints local version of name
...
>>> selector()
99
88

Qualification (the .X part) fetches a value from a namespace object. The interactive namespace is a module called __main__, so __main__.X reaches the global version of X. If that isn’t clear, check out Chapter 17.

In recent versions Python has improved on this story somewhat by issuing for this case the more specific “unbound local” error message shown in the example listing (it used to simply raise a generic name error); this gotcha is still present in general, though.

Defaults and Mutable Objects

Default argument values are evaluated and saved when a def statement is run, not when the resulting function is called. Internally, Python saves one object per default argument attached to the function itself.

That’s usually what you want—because defaults are evaluated at def time, it lets you save values from the enclosing scope, if needed. But because a default retains an object between calls, you have to be careful about changing mutable defaults. For instance, the following function uses an empty list as a default value, and then changes it in-place each time the function is called:

>>> def saver(x=[]):               # Saves away a list object
...     x.append(1)                # Changes same object each time!
...     print(x)
...
>>> saver([2])                     # Default not used
[2, 1]
>>> saver()                        # Default used
[1]
>>> saver()                        # Grows on each call!
[1, 1]
>>> saver()
[1, 1, 1]

Some see this behavior as a feature—because mutable default arguments retain their state between function calls, they can serve some of the same roles as static local function variables in the C language. In a sense, they work sort of like global variables, but their names are local to the functions and so will not clash with names elsewhere in a program.

To most observers, though, this seems like a gotcha, especially the first time they run into it. There are better ways to retain state between calls in Python (e.g., using classes, which will be discussed in Part VI).

Moreover, mutable defaults are tricky to remember (and to understand at all). They depend upon the timing of default object construction. In the prior example, there is just one list object for the default value—the one created when the def is executed. You don’t get a new list every time the function is called, so the list grows with each new append; it is not reset to empty on each call.

If that’s not the behavior you want, simply make a copy of the default at the start of the function body, or move the default value expression into the function body. As long as the value resides in code that’s actually executed each time the function runs, you’ll get a new object each time through:

>>> def saver(x=None):
...     if x is None:             # No argument passed?
...         x = []                # Run code to make a new list
...     x.append(1)               # Changes new list object
...     print(x)
...
>>> saver([2])
[2, 1]
>>> saver()                       # Doesn't grow here
[1]
>>> saver()
[1]

By the way, the if statement in this example could almost be replaced by the assignment x = x or [], which takes advantage of the fact that Python’s or returns one of its operand objects: if no argument was passed, x would default to None, so the or would return the new empty list on the right.

However, this isn’t exactly the same. If an empty list were passed in, the or expression would cause the function to extend and return a newly created list, rather than extending and returning the passed-in list like the if version. (The expression becomes [] or [], which evaluates to the new empty list on the right; see the section Truth Tests if you don’t recall why). Real program requirements may call for either behavior.

Today, another way to achieve the effect of mutable defaults in a possibly less confusing way is to use the function attributes we discussed in Chapter 19:

>>> def saver():
...     saver.x.append(1)
...     print(saver.x)
...
>>> saver.x = []
>>> saver()
[1]
>>> saver()
[1, 1]
>>> saver()
[1, 1, 1]

The function name is global to the function itself, but it need not be declared because it isn’t changed directly within the function. This isn’t used in exactly the same way, but when coded like this, the attachment of an object to the function is much more explicit (and arguably less magical).

Functions Without returns

In Python functions, return (and yield) statements are optional. When a function doesn’t return a value explicitly, the function exits when control falls off the end of the function body. Technically, all functions return a value; if you don’t provide a return statement, your function returns the None object automatically:

>>> def proc(x):
...     print(x)                 # No return is a None return
...
>>> x = proc('testing 123...')
testing 123...
>>> print(x)
None

Functions such as this without a return are Python’s equivalent of what are called “procedures” in some languages. They’re usually invoked as statements, and the None results are ignored, as they do their business without computing a useful result.

This is worth knowing, because Python won’t tell you if you try to use the result of a function that doesn’t return one. For instance, assigning the result of a list append method won’t raise an error, but you’ll get back None, not the modified list:

>>> list = [1, 2, 3]
>>> list = list.append(4)        # append is a "procedure"
>>> print(list)                  # append changes list in-place
None

As mentioned in Common Coding Gotchas in Chapter 15, such functions do their business as a side effect and are usually designed to be run as statements, not expressions.

Enclosing Scope Loop Variables

We described this gotcha in Chapter 17’s discussion of enclosing function scopes, but as a reminder, be careful about relying on enclosing function scope lookup for variables that are changed by enclosing loops—all such references will remember the value of the last loop iteration. Use defaults to save loop variable values instead (see Chapter 17 for more details on this topic).

Chapter Summary

This chapter wrapped up our coverage of built-in comprehension and iteration tools. It explored list comprehensions in the context of functional tools and presented generator functions and expressions as additional iteration protocol tools. As a finale, we also measured the performance of iteration alternatives, and we closed with a review of common function-related mistakes to help you avoid pitfalls.

This concludes the functions part of this book. In the next part, we will study modules—the topmost organizational structure in Python, and the structure in which our functions always live. After that, we will explore classes, tools that are largely packages of functions with special first arguments. As we’ll see, user-defined classes can implement objects that tap into the iteration protocol, just like the generators and iterables we met here. Everything we have learned in this part of the book will apply when functions pop up later in the context of class methods.

Before moving on to modules, though, be sure to work through this chapter’s quiz and the exercises for this part of the book, to practice what we’ve learned about functions here.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

List comprehensions in square brackets produce the result list all at once in memory. When they are enclosed in parentheses instead, they are actually generator expressions—they have a similar meaning but do not produce the result list all at once. Instead, generator expressions return a generator object, which yields one item in the result at a time when used in an iteration context.

Generators are objects that support the iteration protocol—they have a __next__ method that repeatedly advances to the next item in a series of results and raises an exception at the end of the series. In Python, we can code generator functions with def, generator expressions with parenthesized list comprehensions, and generator objects with classes that define a special method named __iter__ (discussed later in the book).

A generator function has a yield statement somewhere in its code. Generator functions are otherwise identical to normal functions syntactically, but they are compiled specially by Python so as to return an iterable object when called.

When present, this statement makes Python compile the function specially as a generator; when called, the function returns a generator object that supports the iteration protocol. When the yield statement is run, it sends a result back to the caller and suspends the function’s state; the function can then be resumed after the last yield statement, in response to a next built-in or __next__ method call issued by the caller. Generator functions may also have a return statement, which terminates the generator.

The map call is similar to a list comprehension—both build a new list by collecting the results of applying an operation to each item in a sequence or other iterable, one item at a time. The main difference is that map applies a function call to each item, and list comprehensions apply arbitrary expressions. Because of this, list comprehensions are more general; they can apply a function call expression like map, but map requires a function to apply other kinds of expressions. List comprehensions also support extended syntax such as nested for loops and if clauses that subsume the filter built-in.

Test Your Knowledge: Part IV Exercises

In these exercises, you’re going to start coding more sophisticated programs. Be sure to check the solutions in Part IV, Functions in Appendix B, and be sure to start writing your code in module files. You won’t want to retype these exercises from scratch if you make a mistake.

The basics. At the Python interactive prompt, write a function that prints its single argument to the screen and call it interactively, passing a variety of object types: string, integer, list, dictionary. Then, try calling it without passing any argument. What happens? What happens when you pass two arguments?

Arguments. Write a function called adder in a Python module file. The function should accept two arguments and return the sum (or concatenation) of the two. Then, add code at the bottom of the file to call the adder function with a variety of object types (two strings, two lists, two floating points), and run this file as a script from the system command line. Do you have to print the call statement results to see results on your screen?

varargs. Generalize the adder function you wrote in the last exercise to compute the sum of an arbitrary number of arguments, and change the calls to pass more or fewer than two arguments. What type is the return value sum? (Hints: a slice such as S[:0] returns an empty sequence of the same type as S, and the type built-in function can test types; but see the manually coded min examples in Chapter 18 for a simpler approach.) What happens if you pass in arguments of different types? What about passing in dictionaries?

Keywords. Change the adder function from exercise 2 to accept and sum/concatenate three arguments: def adder(good, bad, ugly). Now, provide default values for each argument, and experiment with calling the function interactively. Try passing one, two, three, and four arguments. Then, try passing keyword arguments. Does the call adder(ugly=1, good=2) work? Why? Finally, generalize the new adder to accept and sum/concatenate an arbitrary number of keyword arguments. This is similar to what you did in exercise 3, but you’ll need to iterate over a dictionary, not a tuple. (Hint: the dict.keys method returns a list you can step through with a for or while, but be sure to wrap it in a list call to index it in 3.0!)

Write a function called copyDict(dict) that copies its dictionary argument. It should return a new dictionary containing all the items in its argument. Use the dictionary keys method to iterate (or, in Python 2.2, step over a dictionary’s keys without calling keys). Copying sequences is easy (X[:] makes a top-level copy); does this work for dictionaries, too?

Write a function called addDict(dict1, dict2) that computes the union of two dictionaries. It should return a new dictionary containing all the items in both its arguments (which are assumed to be dictionaries). If the same key appears in both arguments, feel free to pick a value from either. Test your function by writing it in a file and running the file as a script. What happens if you pass lists instead of dictionaries? How could you generalize your function to handle this case, too? (Hint: see the type built-in function used earlier.) Does the order of the arguments passed in matter?

More argument-matching examples. First, define the following six functions (either interactively or in a module file that can be imported):

def f1(a, b): print(a, b)            # Normal args
def f2(a, *b): print(a, b)           # Positional varargs

def f3(a, **b): print(a, b)          # Keyword varargs

def f4(a, *b, **c): print(a, b, c)   # Mixed modes

def f5(a, b=2, c=3): print(a, b, c)  # Defaults

def f6(a, b=2, *c): print(a, b, c)   # Defaults and positional varargs

Now, test the following calls interactively, and try to explain each result; in some cases, you’ll probably need to fall back on the matching algorithm shown in Chapter 18. Do you think mixing matching modes is a good idea in general? Can you think of cases where it would be useful?

>>> f1(1, 2)
>>> f1(b=2, a=1)

>>> f2(1, 2, 3)
>>> f3(1, x=2, y=3)
>>> f4(1, 2, 3, x=2, y=3)

>>> f5(1)
>>> f5(1, 4)

>>> f6(1)
>>> f6(1, 3, 4)

Primes revisited. Recall the following code snippet from Chapter 13, which simplistically determines whether a positive integer is prime:

x = y // 2                           # For some y > 1
while x > 1:
    if y % x == 0:                   # Remainder
      print(y, 'has factor', x)
      break                         # Skip else
    x -= 1
else:                               # Normal exit
    print(y, 'is prime')

Package this code as a reusable function in a module file (y should be a passed-in argument), and add some calls to the function at the bottom of your file. While you’re at it, experiment with replacing the first line’s // operator with / to see how true division changes the / operator in Python 3.0 and breaks this code (refer back to Chapter 5 if you need a refresher). What can you do about negatives, and the values 0 and 1? How about speeding this up? Your outputs should look something like this:

13 is prime
13.0 is prime
15 has factor 5
15.0 has factor 5.0

List comprehensions. Write code to build a new list containing the square roots of all the numbers in this list: [2, 4, 9, 16, 25]. Code this as a for loop first, then as a map call, and finally as a list comprehension. Use the sqrt function in the built-in math module to do the calculation (i.e., import math and say math.sqrt(x)). Of the three, which approach do you like best?

Timing tools. In Chapter 5, we saw three ways to compute square roots: math.sqrt(X), X ** .5, and pow(X, .5). If your programs run a lot these, their relative performance might become important. To see which is quickest, repurpose the timerseqs.py script we wrote in this chapter to time each of these three tools. Use the mytimer.py timer module with the best function (you can use either the 3.0-ony keyword-only variant, or the 2.6/3.0 version). You might also want to repackage the testing code in this script for better reusability—by passing a test functions tuple to a general tester function, for example (for this exercise a copy-and-modify approach is fine). Which of the three square root tools seems to run fastest on your machine and Python in general? Finally, how might you go about interactively timing the speed of dictionary comprehensions versus for loops?

[43] These performance generalizations can depend on call patterns, as well as changes and optimizations in Python itself. Recent Python releases have sped up the simple for loop statement, for example. Usually, though, list comprehensions are still substantially faster than for loops and even faster than map (though map can still win for built-in functions). To time these alternatives yourself, see the standard library’s time module’s time.clock and time.time calls, the newer timeit module added in Release 2.4, or this chapter’s upcoming section Timing Iteration Alternatives.

[44] Interestingly, generator functions are also something of a “poor man’s” multithreading device—they interleave a function’s work with that of its caller, by dividing its operation into steps run between yields. Generators are not threads, though: the program is explicitly directed to and from the function within a single thread of control. In one sense, threading is more general (producers can run truly independently and post results to a queue), but generators may be simpler to code. See the second footnote in Chapter 17 for a brief introduction to Python multithreading tools. Note that because control is routed explicitly at yield and next calls, generators are also not backtracking, but are more strongly related to coroutines—formal concepts that are both beyond this chapter’s scope.

[45] Also note how we must pass functions in to the timer manually here. In Chapters 38 and 39 we'll see decorator-based timer alternatives with which timed functions are called normally.

[46] For more fun, apply a simple user-defined function like def f(I): return(I) in all five iteration techniques timed. The results are similar to using a built-in function like abs: among the five iteration techniques, map is fastest today if all five call a function, built-in or not, but slowest when the others do not. That is, map appears to be slower simply because it requires function calls, and function calls are relatively slow in general. Since map can't avoid calling functions, it can lose by association.

Chapter 21. Modules: The Big Picture

This chapter begins our in-depth look at the Python module, the highest-level program organization unit, which packages program code and data for reuse. In concrete terms, modules usually correspond to Python program files (or extensions coded in external languages such as C, Java, or C#). Each file is a module, and modules import other modules to use the names they define. Modules are processed with two statements and one important function:

import

Lets a client (importer) fetch a module as a whole

from

Allows clients to fetch particular names from a module

imp.reload

Provides a way to reload a module’s code without stopping Python

Chapter 3 introduced module fundamentals, and we’ve been using them ever since. This part of the book begins by expanding on core module concepts, then moves on to explore more advanced module usage. This first chapter offers a general look at the role of modules in overall program structure. In the following chapters, we’ll dig into the coding details behind the theory.

Along the way, we’ll flesh out module details omitted so far: you’ll learn about reloads, the __name__ and __all__ attributes, package imports, relative import syntax, and so on. Because modules and classes are really just glorified namespaces, we’ll formalize namespace concepts here as well.

Why Use Modules?

In short, modules provide an easy way to organize components into a system by serving as self-contained packages of variables known as namespaces. All the names defined at the top level of a module file become attributes of the imported module object. As we saw in the last part of this book, imports give access to names in a module’s global scope. That is, the module file’s global scope morphs into the module object’s attribute namespace when it is imported. Ultimately, Python’s modules allow us to link individual files into a larger program system.

More specifically, from an abstract perspective, modules have at least three roles:

Code reuse

As discussed in Chapter 3, modules let you save code in files permanently. Unlike code you type at the Python interactive prompt, which goes away when you exit Python, code in module files is persistent—it can be reloaded and rerun as many times as needed. More to the point, modules are a place to define names, known as attributes, which may be referenced by multiple external clients.

System namespace partitioning

Modules are also the highest-level program organization unit in Python. Fundamentally, they are just packages of names. Modules seal up names into self-contained packages, which helps avoid name clashes—you can never see a name in another file, unless you explicitly import that file. In fact, everything “lives” in a module—code you execute and objects you create are always implicitly enclosed in modules. Because of that, modules are natural tools for grouping system components.

Implementing shared services or data

From an operational perspective, modules also come in handy for implementing components that are shared across a system and hence require only a single copy. For instance, if you need to provide a global object that’s used by more than one function or file, you can code it in a module that can then be imported by many clients.

For you to truly understand the role of modules in a Python system, though, we need to digress for a moment and explore the general structure of a Python program.

How Imports Work

The prior section talked about importing modules without really explaining what happens when you do so. Because imports are at the heart of program structure in Python, this section goes into more detail on the import operation to make this process less abstract.

Some C programmers like to compare the Python module import operation to a C #include, but they really shouldn’t—in Python, imports are not just textual insertions of one file into another. They are really runtime operations that perform three distinct steps the first time a program imports a given file:

Find the module’s file.

Compile it to byte code (if needed).

Run the module’s code to build the objects it defines.

To better understand module imports, we’ll explore these steps in turn. Bear in mind that all three of these steps are carried out only the first time a module is imported during a program’s execution; later imports of the same module bypass all of these steps and simply fetch the already loaded module object in memory. Technically, Python does this by storing loaded modules in a table named sys.modules and checking there at the start of an import operation. If the module is not present, a three-step process begins.

1. Find It

First, Python must locate the module file referenced by an import statement. Notice that the import statement in the prior section’s example names the file without a .py suffix and without its directory path: it just says import b, instead of something like import c:\dir1\b.py. In fact, you can only list a simple name; path and suffix details are omitted on purpose and Python uses a standard module search path to locate the module file corresponding to an import statement.[47] Because this is the main part of the import operation that programmers must know about, we’ll return to this topic in a moment.

2. Compile It (Maybe)

After finding a source code file that matches an import statement by traversing the module search path, Python next compiles it to byte code, if necessary. (We discussed byte code in Chapter 2.)

Python checks the file timestamps and, if the byte code file is older than the source file (i.e., if you’ve changed the source), automatically regenerates the byte code when the program is run. If, on the other hand, it finds a .pyc byte code file that is not older than the corresponding .py source file, it skips the source-to–byte code compile step. In addition, if Python finds only a byte code file on the search path and no source, it simply loads the byte code directly (this means you can ship a program as just byte code files and avoid sending source). In other words, the compile step is bypassed if possible to speed program startup. As noted in Chapter 2, imports also recreate byte code if its "magic" Python version number does not match.

Notice that compilation happens when a file is being imported. Because of this, you will not usually see a .pyc byte code file for the top-level file of your program, unless it is also imported elsewhere—only imported files leave behind .pyc files on your machine. The byte code of top-level files is used internally and discarded; byte code of imported files is saved in files to speed future imports.

Top-level files are often designed to be executed directly and not imported at all. Later, we’ll see that it is possible to design a file that serves both as the top-level code of a program and as a module of tools to be imported. Such a file may be both executed and imported, and thus does generate a .pyc. To learn how this works, watch for the discussion of the special __name__ attribute and __main__ in Chapter 24.

3. Run It

The final step of an import operation executes the byte code of the module. All statements in the file are executed in turn, from top to bottom, and any assignments made to names during this step generate attributes of the resulting module object. This execution step therefore generates all the tools that the module’s code defines. For instance, def statements in a file are run at import time to create functions and assign attributes within the module to those functions. The functions can then be called later in the program by the file’s importers.

Because this last import step actually runs the file’s code, if any top-level code in a module file does real work, you’ll see its results at import time. For example, top-level print statements in a module show output when the file is imported. Function def statements simply define objects for later use.

As you can see, import operations involve quite a bit of work—they search for files, possibly run a compiler, and run Python code. Because of this, any given module is imported only once per process by default. Future imports skip all three import steps and reuse the already loaded module in memory. If you need to import a file again after it has already been loaded (for example, to support end-user customization), you have to force the issue with an imp.reload call—a tool we’ll meet in the next chapter.[48]

The Module Search Path

As mentioned earlier, the part of the import procedure that is most important to programmers is usually the first—locating the file to be imported (the “find it” part). Because you may need to tell Python where to look to find files to import, you need to know how to tap into its search path in order to extend it.

In many cases, you can rely on the automatic nature of the module import search path and won’t need to configure this path at all. If you want to be able to import files across directory boundaries, though, you will need to know how the search path works in order to customize it. Roughly, Python’s module search path is composed of the concatenation of these major components, some of which are preset for you and some of which you can tailor to tell Python where to look:

The home directory of the program

PYTHONPATH directories (if set)

Standard library directories

The contents of any .pth files (if present)

Ultimately, the concatenation of these four components becomes sys.path, a list of directory name strings that I’ll expand upon later in this section. The first and third elements of the search path are defined automatically. Because Python searches the concatenation of these components from first to last, though, the second and fourth elements can be used to extend the path to include your own source code directories. Here is how Python uses each of these path components:

Home directory

Python first looks for the imported file in the home directory. The meaning of this entry depends on how you are running the code. When you’re running a program, this entry is the directory containing your program’s top-level script file. When you’re working interactively, this entry is the directory in which you are working (i.e., the current working directory).

Because this directory is always searched first, if a program is located entirely in a single directory, all of its imports will work automatically with no path configuration required. On the other hand, because this directory is searched first, its files will also override modules of the same name in directories elsewhere on the path; be careful not to accidentally hide library modules this way if you need them in your program.

PYTHONPATH directories

Next, Python searches all directories listed in your PYTHONPATH environment variable setting, from left to right (assuming you have set this at all). In brief, PYTHONPATH is simply set to a list of user-defined and platform-specific names of directories that contain Python code files. You can add all the directories from which you wish to be able to import, and Python will extend the module search path to include all the directories your PYTHONPATH lists.

Because Python searches the home directory first, this setting is only important when importing files across directory boundaries—that is, if you need to import a file that is stored in a different directory from the file that imports it. You’ll probably want to set your PYTHONPATH variable once you start writing substantial programs, but when you’re first starting out, as long as you save all your module files in the directory in which you’re working (i.e., the home directory, described earlier) your imports will work without you needing to worry about this setting at all.

Standard library directories

Next, Python automatically searches the directories where the standard library modules are installed on your machine. Because these are always searched, they normally do not need to be added to your PYTHONPATH or included in path files (discussed next).

.pth path file directories

Finally, a lesser-used feature of Python allows users to add directories to the module search path by simply listing them, one per line, in a text file whose name ends with a .pth suffix (for “path”). These path configuration files are a somewhat advanced installation-related feature; we won't cover them fully here, but they provide an alternative to PYTHONPATH settings.

In short, text files of directory names dropped in an appropriate directory can serve roughly the same role as the PYTHONPATH environment variable setting. For instance, if you’re running Windows and Python 3.0, a file named myconfig.pth may be placed at the top level of the Python install directory (C:\Python30) or in the site-packages subdirectory of the standard library there (C:\Python30\Lib\site-packages) to extend the module search path. On Unix-like systems, this file might be located in usr/local/lib/python3.0/site-packages or /usr/local/lib/site-python instead.

When present, Python will add the directories listed on each line of the file, from first to last, near the end of the module search path list. In fact, Python will collect the directory names in all the path files it finds and will filter out any duplicates and nonexistent directories. Because they are files rather than shell settings, path files can apply to all users of an installation, instead of just one user or shell. Moreover, for some users text files may be simpler to code than environment settings.

This feature is more sophisticated than I’ve described here. For more details consult the Python library manual, and especially its documentation for the standard library module site—this module allows the locations of Python libraries and path files to be configured, and its documentation describes the expected locations of path files in general. I recommend that beginners use PYTHONPATH or perhaps a single .pth file, and then only if you must import across directories. Path files are used more often by third-party libraries, which commonly install a path file in Python’s site-packages directory so that user settings are not required (Python’s distutils install system, described in an upcoming sidebar, automates many install steps).

Configuring the Search Path

The net effect of all of this is that both the PYTHONPATH and path file components of the search path allow you to tailor the places where imports look for files. The way you set environment variables and where you store path files varies per platform. For instance, on Windows, you might use your Control Panel’s System icon to set PYTHONPATH to a list of directories separated by semicolons, like this:

c:\pycode\utilities;d:\pycode\package1

Or you might instead create a text file called C:\Python30\pydirs.pth, which looks like this:

c:\pycode\utilities
d:\pycode\package1

These settings are analogous on other platforms, but the details can vary too widely for us to cover in this chapter. See Appendix A for pointers on extending your module search path with PYTHONPATH or .pth files on various platforms.

Search Path Variations

This description of the module search path is accurate, but generic; the exact configuration of the search path is prone to changing across platforms and Python releases. Depending on your platform, additional directories may automatically be added to the module search path as well.

For instance, Python may add an entry for the current working directory—the directory from which you launched your program—in the search path after the PYTHONPATH directories, and before the standard library entries. When you’re launching from a command line, the current working directory may not be the same as the home directory of your top-level file (i.e., the directory where your program file resides). Because the current working directory can vary each time your program runs, you normally shouldn’t depend on its value for import purposes. See Chapter 3 for more on launching programs from command lines.[49]

To see how your Python configures the module search path on your platform, you can always inspect sys.path—the topic of the next section.

The sys.path List

If you want to see how the module search path is truly configured on your machine, you can always inspect the path as Python knows it by printing the built-in sys.path list (that is, the path attribute of the standard library module sys). This list of directory name strings is the actual search path within Python; on imports, Python searches each directory in this list from left to right.

Really, sys.path is the module search path. Python configures it at program startup, automatically merging the home directory of the top-level file (or an empty string to designate the current working directory), any PYTHONPATH directories, the contents of any .pth file paths you’ve created, and the standard library directories. The result is a list of directory name strings that Python searches on each import of a new file.

Python exposes this list for two good reasons. First, it provides a way to verify the search path settings you’ve made—if you don’t see your settings somewhere in this list, you need to recheck your work. For example, here is what my module search path looks like on Windows under Python 3.0, with my PYTHONPATH set to C:\users and a C:\Python30\mypath.pth path file that lists C:\users\mark. The empty string at the front means current directory and my two settings are merged in (the rest are standard library directories and files):

>>> import sys
>>> sys.path
['', 'C:\\users', 'C:\\Windows\\system32\\python30.zip', 'c:\\Python30\\DLLs',
'c:\\Python30\\lib', 'c:\\Python30\\lib\\plat-win', 'c:\\Python30',
'C:\\Users\\Mark', 'c:\\Python30\\lib\\site-packages']

Second, if you know what you’re doing, this list provides a way for scripts to tailor their search paths manually. As you’ll see later in this part of the book, by modifying the sys.path list, you can modify the search path for all future imports. Such changes only last for the duration of the script, however; PYTHONPATH and .pth files offer more permanent ways to modify the path.[50]

Module File Selection

Keep in mind that filename suffixes (e.g., .py) are intentionally omitted from import statements. Python chooses the first file it can find on the search path that matches the imported name. For example, an import statement of the form import b might load:

A source code file named b.py

A byte code file named b.pyc

A directory named b, for package imports (described in Chapter 23)

A compiled extension module, usually coded in C or C++ and dynamically linked when imported (e.g., b.so on Linux, or b.dll or b.pyd on Cygwin and Windows)

A compiled built-in module coded in C and statically linked into Python

A ZIP file component that is automatically extracted when imported

An in-memory image, for frozen executables

A Java class, in the Jython version of Python

A .NET component, in the IronPython version of Python

C extensions, Jython, and package imports all extend imports beyond simple files. To importers, though, differences in the loaded file type are completely transparent, both when importing and when fetching module attributes. Saying import b gets whatever module b is, according to your module search path, and b.attr fetches an item in the module, be it a Python variable or a linked-in C function. Some standard modules we will use in this book are actually coded in C, not Python; because of this transparency, their clients don’t have to care.

If you have both a b.py and a b.so in different directories, Python will always load the one found in the first (leftmost) directory of your module search path during the left-to-right search of sys.path. But what happens if it finds both a b.py and a b.so in the same directory? In this case, Python follows a standard picking order, though this order is not guaranteed to stay the same over time. In general, you should not depend on which type of file Python will choose within a given directory—make your module names distinct, or configure your module search path to make your module selection preferences more obvious.

Advanced Module Selection Concepts

Normally, imports work as described in this section—they find and load files on your machine. However, it is possible to redefine much of what an import operation does in Python, using what are known as import hooks. These hooks can be used to make imports do various useful things, such as loading files from archives, performing decryption, and so on.

In fact, Python itself makes use of these hooks to enable files to be directly imported from ZIP archives: archived files are automatically extracted at import time when a .zip file is selected from the module import search path. One of the standard library directories in the earlier sys.path display, for example, is a .zip file today. For more details, see the Python standard library manual’s description of the built-in __import__ function, the customizable tool that import statements actually run.

Python also supports the notion of .pyo optimized byte code files, created and run with the -O Python command-line flag; because these run only slightly faster than normal .pyc files (typically 5 percent faster), however, they are infrequently used. The Psyco system (see Chapter 2) provides more substantial speedups.

Third-Party Software: distutils

This chapter’s description of module search path settings is targeted mainly at user-defined source code that you write on your own. Third-party extensions for Python typically use the distutils tools in the standard library to automatically install themselves, so no path configuration is required to use their code.

Systems that use distutils generally come with a setup.py script, which is run to install them; this script imports and uses distutils modules to place such systems in a directory that is automatically part of the module search path (usually in the Lib\site-packages subdirectory of the Python install tree, wherever that resides on the target machine).

For more details on distributing and installing with distutils, see the Python standard manual set; its use is beyond the scope of this book (for instance, it also provides ways to automatically compile C-coded extensions on the target machine). Also check out the emerging third-party open source eggs system, which adds dependency checking for installed Python software.

Chapter Summary

In this chapter, we covered the basics of modules, attributes, and imports and explored the operation of import statements. We learned that imports find the designated file on the module search path, compile it to byte code, and execute all of its statements to generate its contents. We also learned how to configure the search path to be able to import from directories other than the home directory and the standard library directories, primarily with PYTHONPATH settings.

As this chapter demonstrated, the import operation and modules are at the heart of program architecture in Python. Larger programs are divided into multiple files, which are linked together at runtime by imports. Imports in turn use the module search path to locate files, and modules define attributes for external use.

Of course, the whole point of imports and modules is to provide a structure to your program, which divides its logic into self-contained software components. Code in one module is isolated from code in another; in fact, no file can ever see the names defined in another, unless explicit import statements are run. Because of this, modules minimize name collisions between different parts of your program.

You’ll see what this all means in terms of actual statements and code in the next chapter. Before we move on, though, let’s run through the chapter quiz.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

A module’s source code file automatically becomes a module object when that module is imported. Technically, the module’s source code is run during the import, one statement at a time, and all the names assigned in the process become attributes of the module object.

You only need to set PYTHONPATH to import from directories other than the one in which you are working (i.e., the current directory when working interactively, or the directory containing your top-level file).

The four major components of the module import search path are the top-level script’s home directory (the directory containing it), all directories listed in the PYTHONPATH environment variable, the standard library directories, and all directories listed in .pth path files located in standard places. Of these, programmers can customize PYTHONPATH and .pth files.

Python might load a source code (.py) file, a byte code (.pyc) file, a C extension module (e.g., a .so file on Linux or a .dll or .pyd file on Windows), or a directory of the same name for package imports. Imports may also load more exotic things such as ZIP file components, Java classes under the Jython version of Python, .NET components under IronPython, and statically linked C extensions that have no files present at all. With import hooks, imports can load anything.

A namespace is a self-contained package of variables, which are known as the attributes of the namespace object. A module’s namespace contains all the names assigned by code at the top level of the module file (i.e., not nested in def or class statements). Technically, a module’s global scope morphs into the module object’s attributes namespace. A module’s namespace may also be altered by assignments from other files that import it, though this is frowned upon (see Chapter 17 for more on this issue).

[47] It’s actually syntactically illegal to include path and suffix details in a standard import. Package imports, which we’ll discuss in Chapter 23, allow import statements to include part of the directory path leading to a file as a set of period-separated names; however, package imports still rely on the normal module search path to locate the leftmost directory in a package path (i.e., they are relative to a directory in the search path). They also cannot make use of any platform-specific directory syntax in the import statements; such syntax only works on the search path. Also, note that module file search path issues are not as relevant when you run frozen executables (discussed in Chapter 2); they typically embed byte code in the binary image.

[48] As described earlier, Python keeps already imported modules in the built-in sys.modules dictionary so it can keep track of what’s been loaded. In fact, if you want to see which modules are loaded, you can import sys and print list(sys.modules.keys()). More on other uses for this internal table in Chapter 24.

[49] See also Chapter 23’s discussion of the new relative import syntax in Python 3.0; this modifies the search path for from statements in files inside packages when “.” characters are used (e.g., from . import string). By default, a package’s own directory is not automatically searched by imports in Python 3.0, unless relative imports are used by files in the package itself.

[50] Some programs really need to change sys.path, though. Scripts that run on web servers, for example, often run as the user “nobody” to limit machine access. Because such scripts cannot usually depend on “nobody” to have set PYTHONPATH in any particular way, they often set sys.path manually to include required source directories, prior to running any import statements. A sys.path.append(dirname) will often suffice.

Module Creation

To define a module, simply use your text editor to type some Python code into a text file, and save it with a “.py” extension; any such file is automatically considered a Python module. All the names assigned at the top level of the module become its attributes (names associated with the module object) and are exported for clients to use.

For instance, if you type the following def into a file called module1.py and import it, you create a module object with one attribute—the name printer, which happens to be a reference to a function object:

def printer(x):                   # Module attribute
    print(x)

Before we go on, I should say a few more words about module filenames. You can call modules just about anything you like, but module filenames should end in a .py suffix if you plan to import them. The .py is technically optional for top-level files that will be run but not imported, but adding it in all cases makes your files’ types more obvious and allows you to import any of your files in the future.

Because module names become variable names inside a Python program (without the .py), they should also follow the normal variable name rules outlined in Chapter 11. For instance, you can create a module file named if.py, but you cannot import it because if is a reserved word—when you try to run import if, you’ll get a syntax error. In fact, both the names of module files and the names of directories used in package imports (discussed in the next chapter) must conform to the rules for variable names presented in Chapter 11; they may, for instance, contain only letters, digits, and underscores. Package directories also cannot contain platform-specific syntax such as spaces in their names.

When a module is imported, Python maps the internal module name to an external filename by adding a directory path from the module search path to the front, and a .py or other extension at the end. For instance, a module named M ultimately maps to some external file <directory>\M.<extension> that contains the module’s code.

As mentioned in the preceding chapter, it is also possible to create a Python module by writing code in an external language such as C or C++ (or Java, in the Jython implementation of the language). Such modules are called extension modules, and they are generally used to wrap up external libraries for use in Python scripts. When imported by Python code, extension modules look and feel the same as modules coded as Python source code files—they are accessed with import statements, and they provide functions and objects as module attributes. Extension modules are beyond the scope of this book; see Python’s standard manuals or advanced texts such as Programming Python for more details.

Module Usage

Clients can use the simple module file we just wrote by running an import or from statement. Both statements find, compile, and run a module file’s code, if it hasn’t yet been loaded. The chief difference is that import fetches the module as a whole, so you must qualify to fetch its names; in contrast, from fetches (or copies) specific names out of the module.

Let’s see what this means in terms of code. All of the following examples wind up calling the printer function defined in the prior section’s module1.py module file, but in different ways.

The import Statement

In the first example, the name module1 serves two different purposes—it identifies an external file to be loaded, and it becomes a variable in the script, which references the module object after the file is loaded:

>>> import module1                         # Get module as a whole
>>> module1.printer('Hello world!')        # Qualify to get names
Hello world!

Because import gives a name that refers to the whole module object, we must go through the module name to fetch its attributes (e.g., module1.printer).

The from Statement

By contrast, because from also copies names from one file over to another scope, it allows us to use the copied names directly in the script without going through the module (e.g., printer):

>>> from module1 import printer            # Copy out one variable
>>> printer('Hello world!')                # No need to qualify name
Hello world!

This has the same effect as the prior example, but because the imported name is copied into the scope where the from statement appears, using that name in the script requires less typing: we can use it directly instead of naming the enclosing module.

As you’ll see in more detail later, the from statement is really just a minor extension to the import statement—it imports the module file as usual, but adds an extra step that copies one or more names out of the file.

The from * Statement

Finally, the next example uses a special form of from: when we use a *, we get copies of all the names assigned at the top level of the referenced module. Here again, we can then use the copied name printer in our script without going through the module name:

>>> from module1 import *                   # Copy out all variables
>>> printer('Hello world!')
Hello world!

Technically, both import and from statements invoke the same import operation; the from * form simply adds an extra step that copies all the names in the module into the importing scope. It essentially collapses one module’s namespace into another; again, the net effect is less typing for us.

And that’s it—modules really are simple to use. To give you a better understanding of what really happens when you define and use modules, though, let’s move on to look at some of their properties in more detail.

Note

In Python 3.0, the from ...* statement form described here can be used only at the top level of a module file, not within a function. Python 2.6 allows it to be used within a function, but issues a warning. It’s extremely rare to see this statement used inside a function in practice; when present, it makes it impossible for Python to detect variables statically, before the function runs.

Imports Happen Only Once

One of the most common questions people seem to ask when they start using modules is, “Why won’t my imports keep working?” They often report that the first import works fine, but later imports during an interactive session (or program run) seem to have no effect. In fact, they’re not supposed to. This section explains why.

Modules are loaded and run on the first import or from, and only the first. This is on purpose—because importing is an expensive operation, by default Python does it just once per file, per process. Later import operations simply fetch the already loaded module object.

As one consequence, because top-level code in a module file is usually executed only once, you can use it to initialize variables. Consider the file simple.py, for example:

print('hello')
spam = 1                   # Initialize variable

In this example, the print and = statements run the first time the module is imported, and the variable spam is initialized at import time:

% python
>>> import simple          # First import: loads and runs file's code
hello
>>> simple.spam            # Assignment makes an attribute
1

Second and later imports don’t rerun the module’s code; they just fetch the already created module object from Python’s internal modules table. Thus, the variable spam is not reinitialized:

>>> simple.spam = 2        # Change attribute in module
>>> import simple          # Just fetches already loaded module
>>> simple.spam            # Code wasn't rerun: attribute unchanged
2

Of course, sometimes you really want a module’s code to be rerun on a subsequent import. We’ll see how to do this with Python’s reload function later in this chapter.

import and from Are Assignments

Just like def, import and from are executable statements, not compile-time declarations. They may be nested in if tests, appear in function defs, and so on, and they are not resolved or run until Python reaches them while executing your program. In other words, imported modules and names are not available until their associated import or from statements run. Also, like def, import and from are implicit assignments:

import assigns an entire module object to a single name.

from assigns one or more names to objects of the same names in another module.

All the things we’ve already discussed about assignment apply to module access, too. For instance, names copied with a from become references to shared objects; as with function arguments, reassigning a fetched name has no effect on the module from which it was copied, but changing a fetched mutable object can change it in the module from which it was imported. To illustrate, consider the following file, small.py:

x = 1
y = [1, 2]

% python
>>> from small import x, y         # Copy two names out
>>> x = 42                         # Changes local x only
>>> y[0] = 42                      # Changes shared mutable in-place

Here, x is not a shared mutable object, but y is. The name y in the importer and the importee reference the same list object, so changing it from one place changes it in the other:

>>> import small                   # Get module name (from doesn't)
>>> small.x                        # Small's x is not my x
1
>>> small.y                        # But we share a changed mutable
[42, 2]

For a graphical picture of what from assignments do with references, flip back to Figure 18-1 (function argument passing), and mentally replace “caller” and “function” with “imported” and “importer.” The effect is the same, except that here we’re dealing with names in modules, not functions. Assignment works the same everywhere in Python.

Cross-File Name Changes

Recall from the preceding example that the assignment to x in the interactive session changed the name x in that scope only, not the x in the file—there is no link from a name copied with from back to the file it came from. To really change a global name in another file, you must use import:

% python
>>> from small import x, y         # Copy two names out
>>> x = 42                         # Changes my x only

>>> import small                   # Get module name
>>> small.x = 42                   # Changes x in other module

This phenomenon was introduced in Chapter 17. Because changing variables in other modules like this is a common source of confusion (and often a bad design choice), we’ll revisit this technique again later in this part of the book. Note that the change to y[0] in the prior session is different; it changes an object, not a name.

import and from Equivalence

Notice in the prior example that we have to execute an import statement after the from to access the small module name at all. from only copies names from one module to another; it does not assign the module name itself. At least conceptually, a from statement like this one:

from module import name1, name2     # Copy these two names out (only)

is equivalent to this statement sequence:

import module                       # Fetch the module object
name1 = module.name1                # Copy names out by assignment
name2 = module.name2
del module                          # Get rid of the module name

Like all assignments, the from statement creates new variables in the importer, which initially refer to objects of the same names in the imported file. Only the names are copied out, though, not the module itself. When we use the from * form of this statement (from module import *), the equivalence is the same, but all the top-level names in the module are copied over to the importing scope this way.

Notice that the first step of the from runs a normal import operation. Because of this, the from always imports the entire module into memory if it has not yet been imported, regardless of how many names it copies out of the file. There is no way to load just part of a module file (e.g., just one function), but because modules are byte code in Python instead of machine code, the performance implications are generally negligible.

Potential Pitfalls of the from Statement

Because the from statement makes the location of a variable more implicit and obscure (name is less meaningful to the reader than module.name), some Python users recommend using import instead of from most of the time. I’m not sure this advice is warranted, though; from is commonly and widely used, without too many dire consequences. In practice, in realistic programs, it’s often convenient not to have to type a module’s name every time you wish to use one of its tools. This is especially true for large modules that provide many attributes—the standard library’s tkinter GUI module, for example.

It is true that the from statement has the potential to corrupt namespaces, at least in principle—if you use it to import variables that happen to have the same names as existing variables in your scope, your variables will be silently overwritten. This problem doesn’t occur with the simple import statement because you must always go through a module’s name to get to its contents (module.attr will not clash with a variable named attr in your scope). As long as you understand and expect that this can happen when using from, though, this isn’t a major concern in practice, especially if you list the imported names explicitly (e.g., from module import x, y, z).

On the other hand, the from statement has more serious issues when used in conjunction with the reload call, as imported names might reference prior versions of objects. Moreover, the from module import * form really can corrupt namespaces and make names difficult to understand, especially when applied to more than one file—in this case, there is no way to tell which module a name came from, short of searching the external source files. In effect, the from * form collapses one namespace into another, and so defeats the namespace partitioning feature of modules. We will explore these issues in more detail in the section Module Gotchas at the end of this part of the book (see Chapter 24).

Probably the best real-world advice here is to generally prefer import to from for simple modules, to explicitly list the variables you want in most from statements, and to limit the from * form to just one import per file. That way, any undefined names can be assumed to live in the module referenced with the from *. Some care is required when using the from statement, but armed with a little knowledge, most programmers find it to be a convenient way to access modules.

When import is required

The only time you really must use import instead of from is when you must use the same name defined in two different modules. For example, if two files define the same name differently:

# M.py

def func():
    ...do something...

# N.py

def func():
    ...do something else...

and you must use both versions of the name in your program, the from statement will fail—you can only have one assignment to the name in your scope:

# O.py

from M import func
from N import func        # This overwites the one we got from M
func()                    # Calls N.func only

An import will work here, though, because including the name of the enclosing module makes the two names unique:

# O.py

import M, N               # Get the whole modules, not their names
M.func()                  # We can call both names now
N.func()                  # The module names make them unique

This case is unusual enough that you’re unlikely to encounter it very often in practice. If you do, though, import allows you to avoid the name collision.

Module Namespaces

Modules are probably best understood as simply packages of names—i.e., places to define names you want to make visible to the rest of a system. Technically, modules usually correspond to files, and Python creates a module object to contain all the names assigned in a module file. But in simple terms, modules are just namespaces (places where names are created), and the names that live in a module are called its attributes. We’ll explore how all this works in this section.

Files Generate Namespaces

So, how do files morph into namespaces? The short story is that every name that is assigned a value at the top level of a module file (i.e., not nested in a function or class body) becomes an attribute of that module.

For instance, given an assignment statement such as X = 1 at the top level of a module file M.py, the name X becomes an attribute of M, which we can refer to from outside the module as M.X. The name X also becomes a global variable to other code inside M.py, but we need to explain the notion of module loading and scopes a bit more formally to understand why:

Module statements run on the first import. The first time a module is imported anywhere in a system, Python creates an empty module object and executes the statements in the module file one after another, from the top of the file to the bottom.

Top-level assignments create module attributes. During an import, statements at the top level of the file not nested in a def or class that assign names (e.g., =, def) create attributes of the module object; assigned names are stored in the module’s namespace.

Module namespaces can be accessed via the attribute__dict__ or dir(M). Module namespaces created by imports are dictionaries; they may be accessed through the built-in __dict__ attribute associated with module objects and may be inspected with the dir function. The dir function is roughly equivalent to the sorted keys list of an object’s __dict__ attribute, but it includes inherited names for classes, may not be complete, and is prone to changing from release to release.

Modules are a single scope (local is global). As we saw in Chapter 17, names at the top level of a module follow the same reference/assignment rules as names in a function, but the local and global scopes are the same (more formally, they follow the LEGB scope rule we met in Chapter 17, but without the L and E lookup layers). But, in modules, the module scope becomes an attribute dictionary of a module object after the module has been loaded. Unlike with functions (where the local namespace exists only while the function runs), a module file’s scope becomes a module object’s attribute namespace and lives on after the import.

Here’s a demonstration of these ideas. Suppose we create the following module file in a text editor and call it module2.py:

print('starting to load...')
import sys
name = 42

def func(): pass

class klass: pass

print('done loading.')

The first time this module is imported (or run as a program), Python executes its statements from top to bottom. Some statements create names in the module’s namespace as a side effect, but others do actual work while the import is going on. For instance, the two print statements in this file execute at import time:

>>> import module2
starting to load...
done loading.

Once the module is loaded, its scope becomes an attribute namespace in the module object we get back from import. We can then access attributes in this namespace by qualifying them with the name of the enclosing module:

>>> module2.sys
<module 'sys' (built-in)>

>>> module2.name
42

>>> module2.func
<function func at 0x026D3BB8>

>>> module2.klass
<class 'module2.klass'>

Here, sys, name, func, and klass were all assigned while the module’s statements were being run, so they are attributes after the import. We’ll talk about classes in Part VI, but notice the sys attribute—import statements really assign module objects to names, and any type of assignment to a name at the top level of a file generates a module attribute.

Internally, module namespaces are stored as dictionary objects. These are just normal dictionary objects with the usual methods. We can access a module’s namespace dictionary through the module’s __dict__ attribute (remember to wrap this in a list call in Python 3.0—it’s a view object):

>>> list(module2.__dict__.keys())
['name', '__builtins__', '__file__', '__package__', 'sys', 'klass', 'func',
'__name__', '__doc__']

The names we assigned in the module file become dictionary keys internally, so most of the names here reflect top-level assignments in our file. However, Python also adds some names in the module’s namespace for us; for instance, __file__ gives the name of the file the module was loaded from, and __name__ gives its name as known to importers (without the .py extension and directory path).

Attribute Name Qualification

Now that you’re becoming more familiar with modules, we should look at the notion of name qualification (fetching attributes) in more depth. In Python, you can access the attributes of any object that has attributes using the qualification syntax object.attribute.

Qualification is really an expression that returns the value assigned to an attribute name associated with an object. For example, the expression module2.sys in the previous example fetches the value assigned to sys in module2. Similarly, if we have a built-in list object L, L.append returns the append method object associated with that list.

So, what does attribute qualification do to the scope rules we studied in Chapter 17? Nothing, really: it’s an independent concept. When you use qualification to access names, you give Python an explicit object from which to fetch the specified names. The LEGB rule applies only to bare, unqualified names. Here are the rules:

Simple variables

X means search for the name X in the current scopes (following the LEGB rule).

Qualification

X.Y means find X in the current scopes, then search for the attribute Y in the object X (not in scopes).

Qualification paths

X.Y.Z means look up the name Y in the object X, then look up Z in the object X.Y.

Generality

Qualification works on all objects with attributes: modules, classes, C extension types, etc.

In Part VI, we’ll see that qualification means a bit more for classes (it’s also the place where something called inheritance happens), but in general, the rules outlined here apply to all names in Python.

Imports Versus Scopes

As we’ve learned, it is never possible to access names defined in another module file without first importing that file. That is, you never automatically get to see names in another file, regardless of the structure of imports or function calls in your program. A variable’s meaning is always determined by the locations of assignments in your source code, and attributes are always requested of an object explicitly.

For example, consider the following two simple modules. The first, moda.py, defines a variable X global to code in its file only, along with a function that changes the global X in this file:

X = 88                        # My X: global to this file only
def f():
    global X                  # Change this file's X
    X = 99                    # Cannot see names in other modules

The second module, modb.py, defines its own global variable X and imports and calls the function in the first module:

X = 11                        # My X: global to this file only

import moda                   # Gain access to names in moda
moda.f()                      # Sets moda.X, not this file's X
print(X, moda.X)

When run, moda.f changes the X in moda, not the X in modb. The global scope for moda.f is always the file enclosing it, regardless of which module it is ultimately called from:

% python modb.py
11 99

In other words, import operations never give upward visibility to code in imported files—an imported file cannot see names in the importing file. More formally:

Functions can never see names in other functions, unless they are physically enclosing.

Module code can never see names in other modules, unless they are explicitly imported.

Such behavior is part of the lexical scoping notion—in Python, the scopes surrounding a piece of code are completely determined by the code’s physical position in your file. Scopes are never influenced by function calls or module imports.[51]

Namespace Nesting

In some sense, although imports do not nest namespaces upward, they do nest downward. Using attribute qualification paths, it’s possible to descend into arbitrarily nested modules and access their attributes. For example, consider the next three files. mod3.py defines a single global name and attribute by assignment:

X = 3

mod2.py in turn defines its own X, then imports mod3 and uses qualification to access the imported module’s attribute:

X = 2
import mod3

print(X, end=' ')             # My global X
print(mod3.X)                 # mod3's X

mod1.py also defines its own X, then imports mod2, and fetches attributes in both the first and second files:

X = 1
import mod2

print(X, end=' ')             # My global X
print(mod2.X, end=' ')        # mod2's X
print(mod2.mod3.X)            # Nested mod3's X

Really, when mod1 imports mod2 here, it sets up a two-level namespace nesting. By using the path of names mod2.mod3.X, it can descend into mod3, which is nested in the imported mod2. The net effect is that mod1 can see the Xs in all three files, and hence has access to all three global scopes:

% python mod1.py
2 3
1 2 3

The reverse, however, is not true: mod3 cannot see names in mod2, and mod2 cannot see names in mod1. This example may be easier to grasp if you don’t think in terms of namespaces and scopes, but instead focus on the objects involved. Within mod1, mod2 is just a name that refers to an object with attributes, some of which may refer to other objects with attributes (import is an assignment). For paths like mod2.mod3.X, Python simply evaluates from left to right, fetching attributes from objects along the way.

Note that mod1 can say import mod2, and then mod2.mod3.X, but it cannot say import mod2.mod3—this syntax invokes something called package (directory) imports, described in the next chapter. Package imports also create module namespace nesting, but their import statements are taken to reflect directory trees, not simple import chains.

Reloading Modules

As we’ve seen, a module’s code is run only once per process by default. To force a module’s code to be reloaded and rerun, you need to ask Python to do so explicitly by calling the reload built-in function. In this section, we’ll explore how to use reloads to make your systems more dynamic. In a nutshell:

Imports (via both import and from statements) load and run a module’s code only the first time the module is imported in a process.

Later imports use the already loaded module object without reloading or rerunning the file’s code.

The reload function forces an already loaded module’s code to be reloaded and rerun. Assignments in the file’s new code change the existing module object in-place.

Why all the fuss about reloading modules? The reload function allows parts of a program to be changed without stopping the whole program. With reload, therefore, the effects of changes in components can be observed immediately. Reloading doesn’t help in every situation, but where it does, it makes for a much shorter development cycle. For instance, imagine a database program that must connect to a server on startup; because program changes or customizations can be tested immediately after reloads, you need to connect only once while debugging. Long-running servers can update themselves this way, too.

Because Python is interpreted (more or less), it already gets rid of the compile/link steps you need to go through to get a C program to run: modules are loaded dynamically when imported by a running program. Reloading offers a further performance advantage by allowing you to also change parts of running programs without stopping. Note that reload currently only works on modules written in Python; compiled extension modules coded in a language such as C can be dynamically loaded at runtime, too, but they can’t be reloaded.

Note

Version skew note: In Python 2.6, reload is available as a built-in function. In Python 3.0, it has been moved to the imp standard library module—it’s known as imp.reload in 3.0. This simply means that an extra import or from statement is required to load this tool (in 3.0 only). Readers using 2.6 can ignore these imports in this book’s examples, or use them anyhow—2.6 also has a reload in its imp module to ease migration to 3.0. Reloading works the same regardless of its packaging.

reload Basics

Unlike import and from:

reload is a function in Python, not a statement.

reload is passed an existing module object, not a name.

reload lives in a module in Python 3.0 and must be imported itself.

Because reload expects an object, a module must have been previously imported successfully before you can reload it (if the import was unsuccessful, due to a syntax or other error, you may need to repeat it before you can reload the module). Furthermore, the syntax of import statements and reload calls differs: reloads require parentheses, but imports do not. Reloading looks like this:

import module                     # Initial import
...use module.attributes...
...                               # Now, go change the module file
...
from imp import reload            # Get reload itself (in 3.0)
reload(module)                    # Get updated exports
...use module.attributes...

The typical usage pattern is that you import a module, then change its source code in a text editor, and then reload it. When you call reload, Python rereads the module file’s source code and reruns its top-level statements. Perhaps the most important thing to know about reload is that it changes a module object in-place; it does not delete and re-create the module object. Because of that, every reference to a module object anywhere in your program is automatically affected by a reload. Here are the details:

reload runs a module file’s new code in the module’s current namespace. Rerunning a module file’s code overwrites its existing namespace, rather than deleting and re-creating it.

Top-level assignments in the file replace names with new values. For instance, rerunning a def statement replaces the prior version of the function in the module’s namespace by reassigning the function name.

Reloads impact all clients that use import to fetch modules. Because clients that use import qualify to fetch attributes, they’ll find new values in the module object after a reload.

Reloads impact future from clients only. Clients that used from to fetch attributes in the past won’t be affected by a reload; they’ll still have references to the old objects fetched before the reload.

reload Example

To demonstrate, here’s a more concrete example of reload in action. In the following, we’ll change and reload a module file without stopping the interactive Python session. Reloads are used in many other scenarios, too (see the sidebar Why You Will Care: Module Reloads), but we’ll keep things simple for illustration here. First, in the text editor of your choice, write a module file named changer.py with the following contents:

message = "First version"
def printer():
    print(message)

This module creates and exports two names—one bound to a string, and another to a function. Now, start the Python interpreter, import the module, and call the function it exports. The function will print the value of the global message variable:

% python
>>> import changer
>>> changer.printer()
First version

Keeping the interpreter active, now edit the module file in another window:

...modify changer.py without stopping Python...
% vi changer.py

Change the global message variable, as well as the printer function body:

message = "After editing"
def printer():
    print('reloaded:', message)

Then, return to the Python window and reload the module to fetch the new code. Notice in the following interaction that importing the module again has no effect; we get the original message, even though the file’s been changed. We have to call reload in order to get the new version:

...back to the Python interpreter/program...

>>> import changer
>>> changer.printer()                 # No effect: uses loaded module
First version
>>> from imp import reload
>>> reload(changer)                   # Forces new code to load/run
<module 'changer' from 'changer.py'>
>>> changer.printer()                 # Runs the new version now
reloaded: After editing

Notice that reload actually returns the module object for us—its result is usually ignored, but because expression results are printed at the interactive prompt, Python shows a default <module 'name'...> representation.

Why You Will Care: Module Reloads

Besides allowing you to reload (and hence rerun) modules at the interactive prompt, module reloads are also useful in larger systems, especially when the cost of restarting the entire application is prohibitive. For instance, systems that must connect to servers over a network on startup are prime candidates for dynamic reloads.

They’re also useful in GUI work (a widget’s callback action can be changed while the GUI remains active), and when Python is used as an embedded language in a C or C++ program (the enclosing program can request a reload of the Python code it runs, without having to stop). See Programming Python for more on reloading GUI callbacks and embedded Python code.

More generally, reloads allow programs to provide highly dynamic interfaces. For instance, Python is often used as a customization language for larger systems—users can customize products by coding bits of Python code onsite, without having to recompile the entire product (or even having its source code at all). In such worlds, the Python code already adds a dynamic flavor by itself.

To be even more dynamic, though, such systems can automatically reload the Python customization code periodically at runtime. That way, users’ changes are picked up while the system is running; there is no need to stop and restart each time the Python code is modified. Not all systems require such a dynamic approach, but for those that do, module reloads provide an easy-to-use dynamic customization tool.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

To create a module, you just write a text file containing Python statements; every source code file is automatically a module, and there is no syntax for declaring one. Import operations load module files into module objects in memory. You can also make a module by writing code in an external language like C or Java, but such extension modules are beyond the scope of this book.

The from statement imports an entire module, like the import statement, but as an extra step it also copies one or more variables from the imported module into the scope where the from appears. This enables you to use the imported names directly (name) instead of having to go through the module (module.name).

By default, a module is imported only once per process. The reload function forces a module to be imported again. It is mostly used to pick up new versions of a module’s source code during development, and in dynamic customization scenarios.

You must use import instead of from only when you need to access the same name in two different modules; because you’ll have to specify the names of the enclosing modules, the two names will be unique.

The from statement can obscure the meaning of a variable (which module it is defined in), can have problems with the reload call (names may reference prior versions of objects), and can corrupt namespaces (it might silently overwrite names you are using in your scope). The from * form is worse in most regards—it can seriously corrupt namespaces and obscure the meaning of variables, so it is probably best used sparingly.

What do you mean? An African or European swallow?

[51] Some languages act differently and provide for dynamic scoping, where scopes really may depend on runtime calls. This tends to make code trickier, though, because the meaning of a variable can differ over time.

Chapter 23. Module Packages

So far, when we’ve imported modules, we’ve been loading files. This represents typical module usage, and it’s probably the technique you’ll use for most imports you’ll code early on in your Python career. However, the module import story is a bit richer than I have thus far implied.

In addition to a module name, an import can name a directory path. A directory of Python code is said to be a package, so such imports are known as package imports. In effect, a package import turns a directory on your computer into another Python namespace, with attributes corresponding to the subdirectories and module files that the directory contains.

This is a somewhat advanced feature, but the hierarchy it provides turns out to be handy for organizing the files in a large system and tends to simplify module search path settings. As we’ll see, package imports are also sometimes required to resolve import ambiguities when multiple program files of the same name are installed on a single machine.

Because it is relevant to code in packages only, we’ll also introduce Python’s recent relative imports model and syntax here. As we’ll see, this model modifies search paths and extends the from statement for imports within packages.

Package Import Basics

So, how do package imports work? In the place where you have been naming a simple file in your import statements, you can instead list a path of names separated by periods:

import dir1.dir2.mod

The same goes for from statements:

from dir1.dir2.mod import x

The “dotted” path in these statements is assumed to correspond to a path through the directory hierarchy on your machine, leading to the file mod.py (or similar; the extension may vary). That is, the preceding statements indicate that on your machine there is a directory dir1, which has a subdirectory dir2, which contains a module file mod.py (or similar).

Furthermore, these imports imply that dir1 resides within some container directory dir0, which is a component of the Python module search path. In other words, the two import statements imply a directory structure that looks something like this (shown with DOS backslash separators):

dir0\dir1\dir2\mod.py               # Or mod.pyc, mod.so, etc.

The container directory dir0 needs to be added to your module search path (unless it’s the home directory of the top-level file), exactly as if dir1 were a simple module file.

More generally, the leftmost component in a package import path is still relative to a directory included in the sys.path module search path list we met in Chapter 21. From there down, though, the import statements in your script give the directory paths leading to the modules explicitly.

Packages and Search Path Settings

If you use this feature, keep in mind that the directory paths in your import statements can only be variables separated by periods. You cannot use any platform-specific path syntax in your import statements, such as C:\dir1, My Documents.dir2 or ../dir1—these do not work syntactically. Instead, use platform-specific syntax in your module search path settings to name the container directories.

For instance, in the prior example, dir0—the directory name you add to your module search path—can be an arbitrarily long and platform-specific directory path leading up to dir1. Instead of using an invalid statement like this:

import C:\mycode\dir1\dir2\mod      # Error: illegal syntax

add C:\mycode to your PYTHONPATH variable or a .pth file (assuming it is not the program’s home directory, in which case this step is not necessary), and say this in your script:

import dir1.dir2.mod

In effect, entries on the module search path provide platform-specific directory path prefixes, which lead to the leftmost names in import statements. import statements provide directory path tails in a platform-neutral fashion.[52]

Package __init__.py Files

If you choose to use package imports, there is one more constraint you must follow: each directory named within the path of a package import statement must contain a file named __init__.py, or your package imports will fail. That is, in the example we’ve been using, both dir1 and dir2 must contain a file called __init__.py; the container directory dir0 does not require such a file because it’s not listed in the import statement itself. More formally, for a directory structure such as this:

dir0\dir1\dir2\mod.py

and an import statement of the form:

import dir1.dir2.mod

the following rules apply:

dir1 and dir2 both must contain an __init__.py file.

dir0, the container, does not require an __init__.py file; this file will simply be ignored if present.

dir0, not dir0\dir1, must be listed on the module search path (i.e., it must be the home directory, or be listed in your PYTHONPATH, etc.).

The net effect is that this example’s directory structure should be as follows, with indentation designating directory nesting:

dir0\                               # Container on module search path
    dir1\
        __init__.py
        dir2\
            __init__.py
            mod.py

The __init__.py files can contain Python code, just like normal module files. They are partly present as a declaration to Python, however, and can be completely empty. As declarations, these files serve to prevent directories with common names from unintentionally hiding true modules that appear later on the module search path. Without this safeguard, Python might pick a directory that has nothing to do with your code, just because it appears in an earlier directory on the search path.

More generally, the __init__.py file serves as a hook for package-initialization-time actions, generates a module namespace for a directory, and implements the behavior of from * (i.e., from .. import *) statements when used with directory imports:

Package initialization

The first time Python imports through a directory, it automatically runs all the code in the directory’s __init__.py file. Because of that, these files are a natural place to put code to initialize the state required by files in a package. For instance, a package might use its initialization file to create required data files, open connections to databases, and so on. Typically, __init__.py files are not meant to be useful if executed directly; they are run automatically when a package is first accessed.

Module namespace initialization

In the package import model, the directory paths in your script become real nested object paths after an import. For instance, in the preceding example, after the import the expression dir1.dir2 works and returns a module object whose namespace contains all the names assigned by dir2’s __init__.py file. Such files provide a namespace for module objects created for directories, which have no real associated module files.

from * statement behavior

As an advanced feature, you can use __all__ lists in __init__.py files to define what is exported when a directory is imported with the from * statement form. In an __init__.py file, the __all__ list is taken to be the list of submodule names that should be imported when from * is used on the package (directory) name. If __all__ is not set, the from * statement does not automatically load submodules nested in the directory; instead, it loads just names defined by assignments in the directory’s __init__.py file, including any submodules explicitly imported by code in this file. For instance, the statement from submodule import X in a directory’s __init__.py makes the name X available in that directory’s namespace. (We’ll see additional roles for __all__ in Chapter 24.)

You can also simply leave these files empty, if their roles are beyond your needs (and frankly, they are often empty in practice). They must exist, though, for your directory imports to work at all.

Note

Don’t confuse package __init__.py files with the class __init__ constructor methods we’ll meet in the next part of the book. The former are files of code run when imports first step through a package directory, while the latter are called when an instance is created. Both have initialization roles, but they are otherwise very different.

Why Use Package Imports?

If you’re new to Python, make sure that you’ve mastered simple modules before stepping up to packages, as they are a somewhat advanced feature. They do serve useful roles, though, especially in larger programs: they make imports more informative, serve as an organizational tool, simplify your module search path, and can resolve ambiguities.

First of all, because package imports give some directory information in program files, they both make it easier to locate your files and serve as an organizational tool. Without package paths, you must often resort to consulting the module search path to find files. Moreover, if you organize your files into subdirectories for functional areas, package imports make it more obvious what role a module plays, and so make your code more readable. For example, a normal import of a file in a directory somewhere on the module search path, like this:

import utilities

offers much less information than an import that includes the path:

import database.client.utilities

Package imports can also greatly simplify your PYTHONPATH and .pth file search path settings. In fact, if you use explicit package imports for all your cross-directory imports, and you make those package imports relative to a common root directory where all your Python code is stored, you really only need a single entry on your search path: the common root. Finally, package imports serve to resolve ambiguities by making explicit exactly which files you want to import. The next section explores this role in more detail.

A Tale of Three Systems

The only time package imports are actually required is to resolve ambiguities that may arise when multiple programs with same-named files are installed on a single machine. This is something of an install issue, but it can also become a concern in general practice. Let’s turn to a hypothetical scenario to illustrate.

Suppose that a programmer develops a Python program that contains a file called utilities.py for common utility code and a top-level file named main.py that users launch to start the program. All over this program, its files say import utilities to load and use the common code. When the program is shipped, it arrives as a single .tar or .zip file containing all the program’s files, and when it is installed, it unpacks all its files into a single directory named system1 on the target machine:

system1\
    utilities.py        # Common utility functions, classes
    main.py             # Launch this to start the program
    other.py            # Import utilities to load my tools

Now, suppose that a second programmer develops a different program with files also called utilities.py and main.py, and again uses import utilities throughout the program to load the common code file. When this second system is fetched and installed on the same computer as the first system, its files will unpack into a new directory called system2 somewhere on the receiving machine (ensuring that they do not overwrite same-named files from the first system):

system2\
    utilities.py        # Common utilities
    main.py             # Launch this to run
    other.py            # Imports utilities

So far, there’s no problem: both systems can coexist and run on the same machine. In fact, you won’t even need to configure the module search path to use these programs on your computer—because Python always searches the home directory first (that is, the directory containing the top-level file), imports in either system’s files will automatically see all the files in that system’s directory. For instance, if you click on system1\main.py, all imports will search system1 first. Similarly, if you launch system2\main.py, system2 will be searched first instead. Remember, module search path settings are only needed to import across directory boundaries.

However, suppose that after you’ve installed these two programs on your machine, you decide that you’d like to use some of the code in each of the utilities.py files in a system of your own. It’s common utility code, after all, and Python code by nature wants to be reused. In this case, you want to be able to say the following from code that you’re writing in a third directory to load one of the two files:

import utilities
utilities.func('spam')

Now the problem starts to materialize. To make this work at all, you’ll have to set the module search path to include the directories containing the utilities.py files. But which directory do you put first in the path—system1 or system2?

The problem is the linear nature of the search path. It is always scanned from left to right, so no matter how long you ponder this dilemma, you will always get utilities.py from the directory listed first (leftmost) on the search path. As is, you’ll never be able to import it from the other directory at all. You could try changing sys.path within your script before each import operation, but that’s both extra work and highly error prone. By default, you’re stuck.

This is the issue that packages actually fix. Rather than installing programs as flat lists of files in standalone directories, you can package and install them as subdirectories under a common root. For instance, you might organize all the code in this example as an install hierarchy that looks like this:

root\
    system1\
        __init__.py
        utilities.py
        main.py
        other.py
    system2\
        __init__.py
        utilities.py
        main.py
        other.py
    system3\                    # Here or elsewhere
        __init__.py             # Your new code here
        myfile.py

Now, add just the common root directory to your search path. If your code’s imports are all relative to this common root, you can import either system’s utility file with a package import—the enclosing directory name makes the path (and hence, the module reference) unique. In fact, you can import both utility files in the same module, as long as you use an import statement and repeat the full path each time you reference the utility modules:

import system1.utilities
import system2.utilities
system1.utilities.function('spam')
system2.utilities.function('eggs')

The names of the enclosing directories here make the module references unique.

Note that you have to use import instead of from with packages only if you need to access the same attribute in two or more paths. If the name of the called function here was different in each path, from statements could be used to avoid repeating the full package path whenever you call one of the functions, as described earlier.

Also, notice in the install hierarchy shown earlier that __init__.py files were added to the system1 and system2 directories to make this work, but not to the root directory. Only directories listed within import statements in your code require these files; as you’ll recall, they are run automatically the first time the Python process imports through a package directory.

Technically, in this case the system3 directory doesn’t have to be under root—just the packages of code from which you will import. However, because you never know when your own modules might be useful in other programs, you might as well place them under the common root directory as well to avoid similar name-collision problems in the future.

Finally, notice that both of the two original systems’ imports will keep working unchanged. Because their home directories are searched first, the addition of the common root on the search path is irrelevant to code in system1 and system2; they can keep saying just import utilities and expect to find their own files. Moreover, if you’re careful to unpack all your Python systems under a common root like this, path configuration becomes simple: you’ll only need to add the common root directory, once.

Package Relative Imports

The coverage of package imports so far has focused mostly on importing package files from outside the package. Within the package itself, imports of package files can use the same path syntax as outside imports, but they can also make use of special intra-package search rules to simplify import statements. That is, rather than listing package import paths, imports within the package can be relative to the package.

The way this works is version-dependent today: Python 2.6 implicitly searches package directories first on imports, while 3.0 requires explicit relative import syntax. This 3.0 change can enhance code readability, by making same-package imports more obvious. If you’re starting out in Python with version 3.0, your focus in this section will likely be on its new import syntax. If you’ve used other Python packages in the past, though, you’ll probably also be interested in how the 3.0 model differs.

Changes in Python 3.0

The way import operations in packages work has changed slightly in Python 3.0. This change applies only to imports within files located in the package directories we’ve been studying in this chapter; imports in other files work as before. For imports in packages, though, Python 3.0 introduces two changes:

It modifies the module import search path semantics to skip the package’s own directory by default. Imports check only other components of the search path. These are known as “absolute” imports.

It extends the syntax of from statements to allow them to explicitly request that imports search the package’s directory only. This is known as “relative” import syntax.

These changes are fully present in Python 3.0. The new from statement relative syntax is also available in Python 2.6, but the default search path change must be enabled as an option. It’s currently scheduled to be added in the 2.7 release[53]—this change is being phased in this way because the search path portion is not backward compatible with earlier Pythons.

The impact of this change is that in 3.0 (and optionally in 2.6), you must generally use special from syntax to import modules located in the same package as the importer, unless you spell out a complete path from a package root. Without this syntax, your package is not automatically searched.

Relative Import Basics

In Python 3.0 and 2.6, from statements can now use leading dots (“.”) to specify that they require modules located within the same package (known as package relative imports), instead of modules located elsewhere on the module import search path (called absolute imports). That is:

In both Python 3.0 and 2.6, you can use leading dots in from statements to indicate that imports should be relative to the containing package—such imports will search for modules inside the package only and will not look for same-named modules located elsewhere on the import search path (sys.path). The net effect is that package modules override outside modules.

In Python 2.6, normal imports in a package’s code (without leading dots) currently default to a relative-then-absolute search path order—that is, they search the package’s own directory first. However, in Python 3.0, imports within a package are absolute by default—in the absence of any special dot syntax, imports skip the containing package itself and look elsewhere on the sys.path search path.

For example, in both Python 3.0 and 2.6, a statement of the form:

from . import spam                        # Relative to this package

instructs Python to import a module named spam located in the same package directory as the file in which this statement appears. Similarly, this statement:

from .spam import name

means “from a module named spam located in the same package as the file that contains this statement, import the variable name.”

The behavior of a statement without the leading dot depends on which version of Python you use. In 2.6, such an import will still default to the current relative-then-absolute search path order (i.e., searching the package’s directory first), unless a statement of the following form is included in the importing file:

from __future__ import  absolute_import   # Required until 2.7?

If present, this statement enables the Python 3.0 absolute-by-default default search path change, described in the next paragraph.

In 3.0, an import without a leading dot always causes Python to skip the relative components of the module import search path and look instead in the absolute directories that sys.path contains. For instance, in 3.0’s model, a statement of the following form will always find a string module somewhere on sys.path, instead of a module of the same name in the package:

import string                             # Skip this package's version

Without the from __future__ statement in 2.6, if there’s a string module in the package, it will be imported instead. To get the same behavior in 3.0 and in 2.6 when the absolute import change is enabled, run a statement of the following form to force a relative import:

from . import string                      # Searches this package only

This works in both Python 2.6 and 3.0 today. The only difference in the 3.0 model is that it is required in order to load a module that is located in the same package directory as the file in which this appears, when the module is given with a simple name.

Note that leading dots can be used to force relative imports only with the from statement, not with the import statement. In Python 3.0, the import modname statement is always absolute, skipping the containing package’s directory. In 2.6, this statement form still performs relative imports today (i.e., the package’s directory is searched first), but these will become absolute in Python 2.7, too. from statements without leading dots behave the same as import statements—absolute in 3.0 (skipping the package directory), and relative-then-absolute in 2.6 (searching the package directory first).

Other dot-based relative reference patterns are possible, too. Within a module file located in a package directory named mypkg, the following alternative import forms work as described:

from .string import name1, name2            # Imports names from mypkg.string
from . import string                        # Imports mypkg.string
from .. import string                       # Imports string sibling of mypkg

To understand these latter forms better, we need to understand the rationale behind this change.

Why Relative Imports?

This feature is designed to allow scripts to resolve ambiguities that can arise when a same-named file appears in multiple places on the module search path. Consider the following package directory:

mypkg\
    __init__.py
    main.py
    string.py

This defines a package named mypkg containing modules named mypkg.main and mypkg.string. Now, suppose that the main module tries to import a module named string. In Python 2.6 and earlier, Python will first look in the mypkg directory to perform a relative import. It will find and import the string.py file located there, assigning it to the name string in the mypkg.main module’s namespace.

It could be, though, that the intent of this import was to load the Python standard library’s string module instead. Unfortunately, in these versions of Python, there’s no straightforward way to ignore mypkg.string and look for the standard library’s string module located on the module search path. Moreover, we cannot resolve this with package import paths, because we cannot depend on any extra package directory structure above the standard library being present on every machine.

In other words, imports in packages can be ambiguous—within a package, it’s not clear whether an import spam statement refers to a module within or outside the package. More accurately, a local module or package can hide another hanging directly off of sys.path, whether intentionally or not.

In practice, Python users can avoid reusing the names of standard library modules they need for modules of their own (if you need the standard string, don’t name a new module string!). But this doesn’t help if a package accidentally hides a standard module; moreover, Python might add a new standard library module in the future that has the same name as a module of your own. Code that relies on relative imports is also less easy to understand, because the reader may be confused about which module is intended to be used. It’s better if the resolution can be made explicit in code.

The relative imports solution in 3.0

To address this dilemma, imports run within packages have changed in Python 3.0 (and as an option in 2.6) to be absolute. Under this model, an import statement of the following form in our example file mypkg/main.py will always find a string outside the package, via an absolute import search of sys.path:

import string                          # Imports string outside package

A from import without leading-dot syntax is considered absolute as well:

from string import name                # Imports name from string outside package

If you really want to import a module from your package without giving its full path from the package root, though, relative imports are still possible by using the dot syntax in the from statement:

from . import string                   # Imports mypkg.string (relative)

This form imports the string module relative to the current package only and is the relative equivalent to the prior import example’s absolute form; when this special relative syntax is used, the package’s directory is the only directory searched.

We can also copy specific names from a module with relative syntax:

from .string import name1, name2       # Imports names from mypkg.string

This statement again refers to the string module relative to the current package. If this code appears in our mypkg.main module, for example, it will import name1 and name2 from mypkg.string.

In effect, the “.” in a relative import is taken to stand for the package directory containing the file in which the import appears. An additional leading dot performs the relative import starting from the parent of the current package. For example, this statement:

from .. import spam                    # Imports a sibling of mypkg

will load a sibling of mypkg—i.e., the spam module located in the package’s own container directory, next to mypkg. More generally, code located in some module A.B.C can do any of these:

from . import D                        # Imports A.B.D     (. means A.B)
from .. import E                       # Imports A.E       (.. means A)

from .D import X                       # Imports A.B.D.X   (. means A.B)
from ..E import X                      # Imports A.E.X     (.. means A)

Relative imports versus absolute package paths

Alternatively, a file can sometimes name its own package explicitly in an absolute import statement. For example, in the following, mypkg will be found in an absolute directory on sys.path:

from mypkg import string                    # Imports mypkg.string (absolute)

However, this relies on both the configuration and the order of the module search path settings, while relative import dot syntax does not. In fact, this form requires that the directory immediately containing mypkg be included in the module search path. In general, absolute import statements must list all the directories below the package’s root entry in sys.path when naming packages explicitly like this:

from system.section.mypkg import string     # system container on sys.path only

In large or deep packages, that could be much more work than a dot:

from . import string                        # Relative import syntax

With this latter form, the containing package is searched automatically, regardless of the search path settings.

The Scope of Relative Imports

Relative imports can seem a bit perplexing on first encounter, but it helps if you remember a few key points about them:

Relative imports apply to imports within packages only. Keep in mind that this feature’s module search path change applies only to import statements within module files located in a package. Normal imports coded outside package files still work exactly as described earlier, automatically searching the directory containing the top-level script first.

Relative imports apply to the from statement only. Also remember that this feature’s new syntax applies only to from statements, not import statements. It’s detected by the fact that the module name in a from begins with one or more dots (periods). Module names that contain dots but don’t have a leading dot are package imports, not relative imports.

The terminology is ambiguous. Frankly, the terminology used to describe this feature is probably more confusing than it needs to be. Really, all imports are relative to something. Outside a package, imports are still relative to directories listed on the sys.path module search path. As we learned in Chapter 21, this path includes the program’s container directory, PYTHONPATH settings, path file settings, and standard libraries. When working interactively, the program container directory is simply the current working directory.

For imports made inside packages, 2.6 augments this behavior by searching the package itself first. In the 3.0 model, all that really changes is that normal “absolute” import syntax skips the package directory, but special “relative” import syntax causes it to be searched first and only. When we talk about 3.0 imports as being “absolute,” what we really mean is that they are relative to the directories on sys.path, but not the package itself. Conversely, when we speak of “relative” imports, we mean they are relative to the package directory only. Some sys.path entries could, of course, be absolute or relative paths too. (And I could probably make up something more confusing, but it would be a stretch!)

In other words, “package relative imports” in 3.0 really just boil down to a removal of 2.6’s special search path behavior for packages, along with the addition of special from syntax to explicitly request relative behavior. If you wrote your package imports in the past to not depend on 2.6’s special implicit relative lookup (e.g., by always spelling out full paths from a package root), this change is largely a moot point. If you didn’t, you’ll need to update your package files to use the new from syntax for local package files.

Module Lookup Rules Summary

With packages and relative imports, the module search story in Python 3.0 in its entirety can be summarized as follows:

Simple module names (e.g., A) are looked up by searching each directory on the sys.path list, from left to right. This list is constructed from both system defaults and user-configurable settings.

Packages are simply directories of Python modules with a special __init__.py file, which enables A.B.C directory path syntax in imports. In an import of A.B.C, for example, the directory named A is located relative to the normal module import search of sys.path, B is another package subdirectory within A, and C is a module or other importable item within B.

Within a package’s files, normal import statements use the same sys.path search rule as imports elsewhere. Imports in packages using from statements and leading dots, however, are relative to the package; that is, only the package directory is checked, and the normal sys.path lookup is not used. In from . import A, for example, the module search is restricted to the directory containing the file in which this statement appears.

Relative Imports in Action

But enough theory: let’s run some quick tests to demonstrate the concepts behind relative imports.

Imports outside packages

First of all, as mentioned previously, this feature does not impact imports outside a package. Thus, the following finds the standard library string module as expected:

C:\test> c:\Python30\python
>>> import string
>>> string
<module 'string' from 'c:\Python30\lib\string.py'>

But if we add a module of the same name in the directory we’re working in, it is selected instead, because the first entry on the module search path is the current working directory (CWD):

# test\string.py
print('string' * 8)

C:\test> c:\Python30\python
>>> import string
stringstringstringstringstringstringstringstring
>>> string
<module 'string' from 'string.py'>

In other words, normal imports are still relative to the “home” directory (the top-level script’s container, or the directory you’re working in). In fact, relative import syntax is not even allowed in code that is not in a file being used as part of a package:

>>> from . import string
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "<stdin>", line 1, in <module>
ValueError: Attempted relative import in non-package

In this and all examples in this section, code entered at the interactive prompt behaves the same as it would if run in a top-level script, because the first entry on sys.path is either the interactive working directory or the directory containing the top-level file. The only difference is that the start of sys.path is an absolute directory, not an empty string:

# test\main.py
import string
print(string)

C:\test> C:\python30\python main.py                   # Same results in 2.6
stringstringstringstringstringstringstringstring
<module 'string' from 'C:\test\string.py'>

Imports within packages

Now, let’s get rid of the local string module we coded in the CWD and build a package directory there with two modules, including the required but empty test\pkg\__init__.py file (which I’ll omit here):

C:\test> del string*
C:\test> mkdir pkg

# test\pkg\spam.py
import eggs                    # <== Works in 2.6 but not 3.0!
print(eggs.X)

# test\pkg\eggs.py
X = 99999
import string
print(string)

The first file in this package tries to import the second with a normal import statement. Because this is taken to be relative in 2.6 but absolute in 3.0, it fails in the latter. That is, 2.6 searches the containing package first, but 3.0 does not. This is the noncompatible behavior you have to be aware of in 3.0:

C:\test> c:\Python26\python
>>> import pkg.spam
<module 'string' from 'c:\Python26\lib\string.pyc'>
99999

C:\test> c:\Python30\python
>>> import pkg.spam
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "<stdin>", line 1, in <module>
  File "pkg\spam.py", line 1, in <module>
    import eggs
ImportError: No module named eggs

To make this work in both 2.6 and 3.0, change the first file to use the special relative import syntax, so that its import searches the package directory in 3.0, too:

# test\pkg\spam.py
from . import eggs             # <== Use package relative import in 2.6 or 3.0
print(eggs.X)

# test\pkg\eggs.py
X = 99999
import string
print(string)

C:\test> c:\Python26\python
>>> import pkg.spam
<module 'string' from 'c:\Python26\lib\string.pyc'>
99999

C:\test> c:\Python30\python
>>> import pkg.spam
<module 'string' from 'c:\Python30\lib\string.py'>
99999

Imports are still relative to the CWD

Notice in the preceding example that the package modules still have access to standard library modules like string. Really, their imports are still relative to the entries on the module search path, even if those entries are relative themselves. If you add a string module to the CWD again, imports in a package will find it there instead of in the standard library. Although you can skip the package directory with an absolute import in 3.0, you still can’t skip the home directory of the program that imports the package:

# test\string.py
print('string' * 8)

# test\pkg\spam.py
from . import eggs
print(eggs.X)

# test\pkg\eggs.py
X = 99999
import string                  # <== Gets string in CWD, not Python lib!
print(string)

C:\test> c:\Python30\python    # Same result in 2.6
>>> import pkg.spam
stringstringstringstringstringstringstringstring
<module 'string' from 'string.py'>
99999

Selecting modules with relative and absolute imports

To show how this applies to imports of standard library modules, reset the package one more time. Get rid of the local string module, and define a new one inside the package itself:

C:\test> del string*

# test\pkg\spam.py
import string                  # <== Relative in 2.6, absolute in 3.0
print(string)

# test\pkg\string.py
print('Ni' * 8)

Now, which version of the string module you get depends on which Python you use. As before, 3.0 interprets the import in the first file as absolute and skips the package, but 2.6 does not:

C:\test> c:\Python30\python
>>> import pkg.spam
<module 'string' from 'c:\Python30\lib\string.py'>

C:\test> c:\Python26\python
>>> import pkg.spam
NiNiNiNiNiNiNiNi
<module 'pkg.string' from 'pkg\string.py'>

Using relative import syntax in 3.0 forces the package to be searched again, as it is in 2.6—by using absolute or relative import syntax in 3.0, you can either skip or select the package directory explicitly. In fact, this is the use case that the 3.0 model addresses:

# test\pkg\spam.py
from . import string           # <== Relative in both 2.6 and 3.0
print(string)

# test\pkg\string.py
print('Ni' * 8)

C:\test> c:\Python30\python
>>> import pkg.spam
NiNiNiNiNiNiNiNi
<module 'pkg.string' from 'pkg\string.py'>

C:\test> c:\Python26\python
>>> import pkg.spam
NiNiNiNiNiNiNiNi
<module 'pkg.string' from 'pkg\string.py'>

It’s important to note that relative import syntax is really a binding declaration, not just a preference. If we delete the string.py file in this example, the relative import in spam.py fails in both 3.0 and 2.6, instead of falling back on the standard library’s version of this module (or any other):

# test\pkg\spam.py
from . import string           # <== Fails if no string.py here!

C:\test> C:\python30\python
>>> import pkg.spam
...text omitted...
ImportError: cannot import name string

Modules referenced by relative imports must exist in the package directory.

Imports are still relative to the CWD (again)

Although absolute imports let you skip package modules, they still rely on other components of sys.path. For one last test, let’s define two string modules of our own. In the following, there is one module by that name in the CWD, one in the package, and another in the standard library:

# test\string.py
print('string' * 8)

# test\pkg\spam.py
from . import string           # <== Relative in both 2.6 and 3.0
print(string)

# test\pkg\string.py
print('Ni' * 8)

When we import the string module with relative import syntax, we get the version in the package, as desired:

C:\test> c:\Python30\python    # Same result in 2.6
>>> import pkg.spam
NiNiNiNiNiNiNiNi
<module 'pkg.string' from 'pkg\string.py'>

When absolute syntax is used, though, the module we get varies per version again. 2.6 interprets this as relative to the package, but 3.0 makes it “absolute,” which in this case really just means it skips the package and loads the version relative to the CWD (not the version the standard library):

# test\string.py
print('string' * 8)

# test\pkg\spam.py
import string                  # <== Relative in 2.6, "absolute" in 3.0: CWD!
print(string)

# test\pkg\string.py
print('Ni' * 8)

C:\test> c:\Python30\python
>>> import pkg.spam
stringstringstringstringstringstringstringstring
<module 'string' from 'string.py'>

C:\test> c:\Python26\python
>>> import pkg.spam
NiNiNiNiNiNiNiNi
<module 'pkg.string' from 'pkg\string.pyc'>

As you can see, although packages can explicitly request modules within their own directories, their imports are otherwise still relative to the rest of the normal module search path. In this case, a file in the program using the package hides the standard library module the package may want. All that the change in 3.0 really accomplishes is allowing package code to select files either inside or outside the package (i.e., relatively or absolutely). Because import resolution can depend on an enclosing context that may not be foreseen, absolute imports in 3.0 are not a guarantee of finding a module in the standard library.

Experiment with these examples on your own for more insight. In practice, this is not usually as ad-hoc as it might seem: you can generally structure your imports, search paths, and module names to work the way you wish during development. You should keep in mind, though, that imports in larger systems may depend upon context of use, and the module import protocol is part of a successful library’s design.

Note

Now that you’ve learned about package-relative imports, also keep in mind that they may not always be your best option. Absolute package imports, relative to a directory on sys.path, are still sometimes preferred over both implicit package-relative imports in Python 2, and explicit package-relative import syntax in both Python 2 and 3.

Package-relative import syntax and Python 3.0’s new absolute import search rules at least require relative imports from a package to be made explicit, and thus easier to understand and maintain. Files that use imports with dots, though, are implicitly bound to a package directory and cannot be used elsewhere without code changes.

Naturally, the extent to which this may impact your modules can vary per package; absolute imports may also require changes when directories are reorganized.

Why You Will Care: Module Packages

Now that packages are a standard part of Python, it’s common to see larger third-party extensions shipped as sets of package directories, rather than flat lists of modules. The win32all Windows extensions package for Python, for instance, was one of the first to jump on the package bandwagon. Many of its utility modules reside in packages imported with paths. For instance, to load client-side COM tools, you use a statement like this:

from win32com.client import constants, Dispatch

This line fetches names from the client module of the win32com package (an install subdirectory).

Package imports are also pervasive in code run under the Jython Java-based implementation of Python, because Java libraries are organized into hierarchies as well. In recent Python releases, the email and XML tools are likewise organized into package subdirectories in the standard library, and Python 3.0 groups even more related modules into packages (including tkinter GUI tools, HTTP networking tools, and more). The following imports access various standard library tools in 3.0:

from email.message import Message
from tkinter.filedialog import askopenfilename
from http.server import CGIHTTPRequestHandler

Whether you create package directories or not, you will probably import from them eventually.

Test Your Knowledge: Answers

The __init__.py file serves to declare and initialize a module package; Python automatically runs its code the first time you import through a directory in a process. Its assigned variables become the attributes of the module object created in memory to correspond to that directory. It is also not optional—you can’t import through a directory with package syntax unless it contains this file.

Use the from statement with a package to copy names out of the package directly, or use the as extension with the import statement to rename the path to a shorter synonym. In both cases, the path is listed in only one place, in the from or import statement.

Each directory listed in an import or from statement must contain an __init__.py file. Other directories, including the directory containing the leftmost component of a package path, do not need to include this file.

You must use import instead of from with packages only if you need to access the same name defined in more than one path. With import, the path makes the references unique, but from allows only one version of any given name.

from mypkg import spam is an absolute import—the search for mypkg skips the package directory and the module is located in an absolute directory in sys.path. A statement from . import spam, on the other hand, is a relative import—spam is looked up relative to the package in which this statement is contained before sys.path is searched.

[52] The dot path syntax was chosen partly for platform neutrality, but also because paths in import statements become real nested object paths. This syntax also means that you get odd error messages if you forget to omit the .py in your import statements. For example, import mod.py is assumed to be a directory path import—it loads mod.py, then tries to load a mod\py.py, and ultimately issues a potentially confusing “No module named py” error message.

[53] Yes, there will be a 2.7 release, and possibly 2.8 and later releases, in parallel with new releases in the 3.X line. As described in the Preface, both the Python 2 and Python 3 lines are expected to be fully supported for years to come, to accommodate the large existing Python 2 user and code bases.

Data Hiding in Modules

As we’ve seen, a Python module exports all the names assigned at the top level of its file. There is no notion of declaring which names should and shouldn’t be visible outside the module. In fact, there’s no way to prevent a client from changing names inside a module if it wants to.

In Python, data hiding in modules is a convention, not a syntactical constraint. If you want to break a module by trashing its names, you can, but fortunately, I’ve yet to meet a programmer who would. Some purists object to this liberal attitude toward data hiding, claiming that it means Python can’t implement encapsulation. However, encapsulation in Python is more about packaging than about restricting.

Minimizing from * Damage: _X and __all__

As a special case, you can prefix names with a single underscore (e.g., _X) to prevent them from being copied out when a client imports a module’s names with a from * statement. This really is intended only to minimize namespace pollution; because from * copies out all names, the importer may get more than it’s bargained for (including names that overwrite names in the importer). Underscores aren’t “private” declarations: you can still see and change such names with other import forms, such as the import statement.

Alternatively, you can achieve a hiding effect similar to the _X naming convention by assigning a list of variable name strings to the variable __all__ at the top level of the module. For example:

__all__ = ["Error", "encode", "decode"]     # Export these only

When this feature is used, the from * statement will copy out only those names listed in the __all__ list. In effect, this is the converse of the _X convention: __all__ identifies names to be copied, while _X identifies names not to be copied. Python looks for an __all__ list in the module first; if one is not defined, from * copies all names without a single leading underscore.

Like the _X convention, the __all__ list has meaning only to the from * statement form and does not amount to a privacy declaration. Module writers can use either trick to implement modules that are well behaved when used with from *. (See also the discussion of __all__ lists in package __init__.py files in Chapter 23; there, these lists declare submodules to be loaded for a from *.)

Mixed Usage Modes: __name__ and __main__

Here’s another module-related trick that lets you both import a file as a module and run it as a standalone program. Each module has a built-in attribute called __name__, which Python sets automatically as follows:

If the file is being run as a top-level program file, __name__ is set to the string "__main__" when it starts.

If the file is being imported instead, __name__ is set to the module’s name as known by its clients.

The upshot is that a module can test its own __name__ to determine whether it’s being run or imported. For example, suppose we create the following module file, named runme.py, to export a single function called tester:

def tester():
    print("It's Christmas in Heaven...")

if __name__ == '__main__':           # Only when run
    tester()                         # Not when imported

This module defines a function for clients to import and use as usual:

% python
>>> import runme
>>> runme.tester()
It's Christmas in Heaven...

But, the module also includes code at the bottom that is set up to call the function when this file is run as a program:

% python runme.py
It's Christmas in Heaven...

In effect, a module’s __name__ variable serves as a usage mode flag, allowing its code to be leveraged as both an importable library and a top-level script. Though simple, you’ll see this hook used in nearly every realistic Python program file you are likely to encounter.

Perhaps the most common way you’ll see the __name__ test applied is for self-test code. In short, you can package code that tests a module’s exports in the module itself by wrapping it in a __name__ test at the bottom of the file. This way, you can use the file in clients by importing it, but also test its logic by running it from the system shell or via another launching scheme. In practice, self-test code at the bottom of a file under the __name__ test is probably the most common and simplest unit-testing protocol in Python. (Chapter 35 will discuss other commonly used options for testing Python code—as you’ll see, the unittest and doctest standard library modules provide more advanced testing tools.)

The __name__ trick is also commonly used when writing files that can be used both as command-line utilities and as tool libraries. For instance, suppose you write a file-finder script in Python. You can get more mileage out of your code if you package it in functions and add a __name__ test in the file to automatically call those functions when the file is run standalone. That way, the script’s code becomes reusable in other programs.

Unit Tests with __name__

In fact, we’ve already seen a prime example in this book of an instance where the __name__ check could be useful. In the section on arguments in Chapter 18, we coded a script that computed the minimum value from the set of arguments sent in:

def minmax(test, *args):
    res = args[0]
    for arg in args[1:]:
        if test(arg, res):
            res = arg
    return res

def lessthan(x, y): return x < y
def grtrthan(x, y): return x > y

print(minmax(lessthan, 4, 2, 1, 5, 6, 3))        # Self-test code
print(minmax(grtrthan, 4, 2, 1, 5, 6, 3))

This script includes self-test code at the bottom, so we can test it without having to retype everything at the interactive command line each time we run it. The problem with the way it is currently coded, however, is that the output of the self-test call will appear every time this file is imported from another file to be used as a tool—not exactly a user-friendly feature! To improve it, we can wrap up the self-test call in a __name__ check, so that it will be launched only when the file is run as a top-level script, not when it is imported (this new version of the module file is renamed min.py here):

print('I am:', __name__)

def minmax(test, *args):
    res = args[0]
    for arg in args[1:]:
        if test(arg, res):
            res = arg
    return res

def lessthan(x, y): return x < y
def grtrthan(x, y): return x > y

if __name__ == '__main__':
    print(minmax(lessthan, 4, 2, 1, 5, 6, 3))    # Self-test code
    print(minmax(grtrthan, 4, 2, 1, 5, 6, 3))

We’re also printing the value of __name__ at the top here to trace its value. Python creates and assigns this usage-mode variable as soon as it starts loading a file. When we run this file as a top-level script, its name is set to __main__, so its self-test code kicks in automatically:

% python min.py
I am: __main__
1
6

But, if we import the file, its name is not __main__, so we must explicitly call the function to make it run:

>>> import min
I am: min
>>> min.minmax(min.lessthan, 's', 'p', 'a', 'm')
'a'

Again, regardless of whether this is used for testing, the net effect is that we get to use our code in two different roles—as a library module of tools, or as an executable program.

Using Command-Line Arguments with __name__

Here’s a more substantial module example that demonstrates another way that the __name__ trick is commonly employed. The following module, formats.py, defines string formatting utilities for importers, but also checks its name to see if it is being run as a top-level script; if so, it tests and uses arguments listed on the system command line to run a canned or passed-in test. In Python, the sys.argv list contains command-line arguments—it is a list of strings reflecting words typed on the command line, where the first item is always the name of the script being run:

"""
Various specialized string display formatting utilities.
Test me with canned self-test or command-line arguments.
"""

def commas(N):
    """
    format positive integer-like N for display with
    commas between digit groupings: xxx,yyy,zzz
    """
    digits = str(N)
    assert(digits.isdigit())
    result = ''
    while digits:
        digits, last3 = digits[:-3], digits[-3:]
        result = (last3 + ',' + result) if result else last3
    return result

def money(N, width=0):
    """
    format number N for display with commas, 2 decimal digits,
    leading $ and sign, and optional padding: $  -xxx,yyy.zz
    """
    sign   = '-' if N < 0 else ''
    N      = abs(N)
    whole  = commas(int(N))
    fract  = ('%.2f' % N)[-2:]
    format = '%s%s.%s' % (sign, whole, fract)
    return '$%*s' % (width, format)

if __name__ == '__main__':
    def selftest():
        tests  = 0, 1        # fails: −1, 1.23
        tests += 12, 123, 1234, 12345, 123456, 1234567
        tests += 2 ** 32, 2 ** 100
        for test in tests:
            print(commas(test))

        print('')
        tests  = 0, 1, −1, 1.23, 1., 1.2, 3.14159
        tests += 12.34, 12.344, 12.345, 12.346
        tests += 2 ** 32, (2 ** 32 + .2345)
        tests += 1.2345, 1.2, 0.2345
        tests += −1.2345, −1.2, −0.2345
        tests += −(2 ** 32), −(2**32 + .2345)
        tests += (2 ** 100), −(2 ** 100)
        for test in tests:
            print('%s [%s]' % (money(test, 17), test))

    import sys
    if len(sys.argv) == 1:
        selftest()
    else:
        print(money(float(sys.argv[1]), int(sys.argv[2])))

This file works the same in Python 2.6 and 3.0. When run directly, it tests itself as before, but it uses options on the command line to control the test behavior. Run this file directly with no command-line arguments on your own to see what its self-test code prints. To test specific strings, pass them in on the command line along with a minimum field width:

C:\misc> python formats.py 999999999 0
$999,999,999.00

C:\misc> python formats.py −999999999 0
$-999,999,999.00

C:\misc> python formats.py 123456789012345 0
$123,456,789,012,345.00

C:\misc> python formats.py −123456789012345 25
$  −123,456,789,012,345.00

C:\misc> python formats.py 123.456 0
$123.46

C:\misc> python formats.py −123.454 0
$-123.45

C:\misc> python formats.py
...canned tests: try this yourself...

As before, because this code is instrumented for dual-mode usage, we can also import its tools normally in other contexts as library components:

>>> from formats import money, commas
>>> money(123.456)
'$123.46'
>>> money(-9999999.99, 15)
'$  −9,999,999.99'
>>> X = 99999999999999999999
>>> '%s (%s)' % (commas(X), X)
'99,999,999,999,999,999,999 (99999999999999999999)'

Because this file uses the docstring feature introduced in Chapter 15, we can use the help function to explore its tools as well—it serves as a general-purpose tool:

>>> import formats
>>> help(formats)
Help on module formats:

NAME
    formats

FILE
    c:\misc\formats.py

DESCRIPTION
    Various specialized string display formatting utilities.
    Test me with canned self-test or command-line arguments.

FUNCTIONS
    commas(N)
        format positive integer-like N for display with
        commas between digit groupings: xxx,yyy,zzz

    money(N, width=0)
        format number N for display with commas, 2 decimal digits,
        leading $ and sign, and optional padding: $  -xxx,yyy.zz

You can use command-line arguments in similar ways to provide general inputs to scripts that may also package their code as functions and classes for reuse by importers. For more advanced command-line processing, be sure to see the getopt and optparse modules in Python’s standard library and manuals. In some scenarios, you might also use the built-in input function introduced in Chapter 3 and used in Chapter 10 to prompt the shell user for test inputs instead of pulling them from the command line.

Note

Also see Chapter 7’s discussion of the new {,d} string format method syntax that will be available in Python 3.1 and later; this formatting extension separates thousands groups with commas much like the code here. The module listed here, though, adds money formatting and serves as a manual alternative for comma insertion for Python versions before 3.1.

Changing the Module Search Path

In Chapter 21, we learned that the module search path is a list of directories that can be customized via the environment variable PYTHONPATH, and possibly via .pth files. What I haven’t shown you until now is how a Python program itself can actually change the search path by changing a built-in list called sys.path (the path attribute in the built-in sys module). sys.path is initialized on startup, but thereafter you can delete, append, and reset its components however you like:

>>> import sys
>>> sys.path
['', 'C:\\users', 'C:\\Windows\\system32\\python30.zip', ...more deleted...]

>>> sys.path.append('C:\\sourcedir')         # Extend module search path
>>> import string                            # All imports search the new dir last

Once you’ve made such a change, it will impact future imports anywhere in the Python program, as all imports and all files share the single sys.path list. In fact, this list may be changed arbitrarily:

>>> sys.path = [r'd:\temp']                  # Change module search path
>>> sys.path.append('c:\\lp4e\\examples')    # For this process only
>>> sys.path
['d:\\temp', 'c:\\lp4e\\examples']

>>> import string
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "<stdin>", line 1, in <module>
ImportError: No module named string

Thus, you can use this technique to dynamically configure a search path inside a Python program. Be careful, though: if you delete a critical directory from the path, you may lose access to critical utilities. In the prior example, for instance, we no longer have access to the string module because we deleted the Python source library’s directory from the path.

Also, remember that such sys.path settings endure for only as long as the Python session or program (technically, process) that made them runs; they are not retained after Python exits. PYTHONPATH and .pth file path configurations live in the operating system instead of a running Python program, and so are more global: they are picked up by every program on your machine and live on after a program completes.

Modules Are Objects: Metaprograms

Because modules expose most of their interesting properties as built-in attributes, it’s easy to write programs that manage other programs. We usually call such manager programs metaprograms because they work on top of other systems. This is also referred to as introspection, because programs can see and process object internals. Introspection is an advanced feature, but it can be useful for building programming tools.

For instance, to get to an attribute called name in a module called M, we can use qualification or index the module’s attribute dictionary, exposed in the built-in __dict__ attribute we met briefly in Chapter 22. Python also exports the list of all loaded modules as the sys.modules dictionary (that is, the modules attribute of the sys module) and provides a built-in called getattr that lets us fetch attributes from their string names (it’s like saying object.attr, but attr is an expression that yields a string at runtime). Because of that, all the following expressions reach the same attribute and object:

M.name                                        # Qualify object
M.__dict__['name']                            # Index namespace dictionary manually
sys.modules['M'].name                         # Index loaded-modules table manually
getattr(M, 'name')                            # Call built-in fetch function

By exposing module internals like this, Python helps you build programs about programs.[54] For example, here is a module named mydir.py that puts these ideas to work to implement a customized version of the built-in dir function. It defines and exports a function called listing, which takes a module object as an argument and prints a formatted listing of the module’s namespace:

"""
mydir.py: a module that lists the namespaces of other modules
"""

seplen = 60
sepchr = '-'

def listing(module, verbose=True):
    sepline = sepchr * seplen
    if verbose:
        print(sepline)
        print('name:', module.__name__, 'file:', module.__file__)
        print(sepline)

    count = 0
    for attr in module.__dict__:              # Scan namespace keys
        print('%02d) %s' % (count, attr), end = ' ')
        if attr.startswith('__'):
            print('<built-in name>')          # Skip __file__, etc.
        else:
            print(getattr(module, attr))      # Same as .__dict__[attr]
        count += 1

    if verbose:
        print(sepline)
        print(module.__name__, 'has %d names' % count)
        print(sepline)

if __name__ == '__main__':
    import mydir
    listing(mydir)                            # Self-test code: list myself

Notice the docstring at the top; as in the prior formats.py example, because we may want to use this as a general tool, a docstring is coded to provide functional information accessible via __doc__ attributes or the help function (see Chapter 15 for details):

>>> import mydir
>>> help(mydir)
Help on module mydir:

NAME
    mydir - mydir.py: a module that lists the namespaces of other modules

FILE
    c:\users\veramark\mark\mydir.py

FUNCTIONS
    listing(module, verbose=True)

DATA
    sepchr = '-'
    seplen = 60

I’ve also provided self-test logic at the bottom of this module, which narcissistically imports and lists itself. Here’s the sort of output produced in Python 3.0 (to use this in 2.6, enable 3.0 print calls with the __future__ import described in Chapter 11—the end keyword is 3.0-only):

C:\Users\veramark\Mark> c:\Python30\python mydir.py
------------------------------------------------------------
name: mydir file: C:\Users\veramark\Mark\mydir.py
------------------------------------------------------------
00) seplen 60
01) __builtins__ <built-in name>
02) __file__ <built-in name>
03) __package__ <built-in name>
04) listing <function listing at 0x026D3B70>
05) __name__ <built-in name>
06) sepchr -
07) __doc__ <built-in name>
------------------------------------------------------------
mydir has 8 names
------------------------------------------------------------

To use this as a tool for listing other modules, simply pass the modules in as objects to this file’s function. Here it is listing attributes in the tkinter GUI module in the standard library (a.k.a. Tkinter in Python 2.6):

>>> import mydir
>>> import tkinter
>>> mydir.listing(tkinter)
------------------------------------------------------------
name: tkinter file: c:\PYTHON30\lib\tkinter\__init__.py
------------------------------------------------------------
00) getdouble <class 'float'>
01) MULTIPLE multiple
02) mainloop <function mainloop at 0x02913B70>
03) Canvas <class 'tkinter.Canvas'>
04) AtSelLast <function AtSelLast at 0x028FA7C8>
...many more name omitted...
151) StringVar <class 'tkinter.StringVar'>
152) ARC arc
153) At <function At at 0x028FA738>
154) NSEW nsew
155) SCROLL scroll
------------------------------------------------------------
tkinter has 156 names
------------------------------------------------------------

We’ll meet getattr and its relatives again later. The point to notice here is that mydir is a program that lets you browse other programs. Because Python exposes its internals, you can process objects generically.[55]